<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C06h"/><pb xml:id="F1823_v1_055" n="36"/>doubt that my tale conveys in its series internal evidence of the
          truth of the events of which it is composed.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p33"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p34"/>You may easily conceive that I was much gratified by the offered communication; yet I
          could not endure that he should renew his grief by a recital of his misfortunes. I felt
          the greatest eagerness to hear the promised narrative, partly from curiosity, and partly
          from a strong desire to ameliorate his fate, if it were in my power. I expressed these
          feelings in my answer.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p34"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p35"/>“I thank you,” he replied, “for <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_056" n="37"/>your sympathy, but it
          is useless; my fate is nearly fulfilled. I wait but for one event, and then I shall repose
          in peace. I understand your feeling,” continued he, perceiving that I wished to interrupt
          him; “but you are mistaken, my friend, if thus you will allow me to name you; nothing can
          alter my destiny: listen to my history, and you will perceive how irrevocably it is
          determined.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p35"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p36"/>He then told me, that he would commence his narrative the next day when I should be at
          leisure. This promise drew from me the warmest thanks. I have resolved every night, when I
          am not engaged, to record, as nearly as possible in his own words, what he has related
          during the day. If I should be engaged, I will at least make notes. This manuscript will
          doubtless afford you the greatest pleasure: but to me, <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_057" n="38"/>who know him, and who hear it from his own lips, with what interest and sympathy shall I
          read it in some future day!<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p36"/>
        <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_058" n="39"/>
        <head sID="novel1_letter4_div4_head3"/>FRANKENSTEIN;<head eID="novel1_letter4_div4_head3"/>
        <head sID="novel1_letter4_div4_head4"/>
      <hi sID="novel1_letter4_div4_head4_hi1"/>OR<hi eID="novel1_letter4_div4_head4_hi1"/>,<head eID="novel1_letter4_div4_head4"/>
        <head sID="novel1_letter4_div4_head5"/>THE MODERN PROMETHEUS.<head eID="novel1_letter4_div4_head5"/>
        <comment text="ebb: centered underscore a few lines below"/>
        </xml>
