<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C06"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p25"/>August 13th, 17—.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p25"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p26"/>My affection for my guest increases every day. He excites at once my admiration and my
          pity to an astonishing degree. How can I see so noble a creature destroyed by misery,
          without feeling the most poignant grief? He is so <pb xml:id="F1831_v_031" n="15"/>gentle,
          yet so wise; his mind is so cultivated; and when he speaks, although his words are culled
          with the choicest art, yet they flow with rapidity and unparalleled eloquence.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p26"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p27"/>He is now much recovered from his illness, and is continually on the deck, apparently
          watching for the sledge that preceded his own. Yet, although unhappy, he is not so utterly
          occupied by his own misery, but that he interests himself deeply in the projects of
          others. He has frequently conversed with me on mine, which I have communicated to him
          without disguise. He entered attentively into all my arguments in favour of my eventual
          success, and into every minute detail of the measures I had taken to secure it. I was
          easily led by the sympathy which he evinced, to use the language of my heart; to give
          utterance to the burning ardour of my soul; and to say, with all the fervour that warmed
          me, how gladly I would sacrifice my fortune, my existence, my every hope, to the
          furtherance of my enterprise. One man’s life or death were but a small price to pay for
          the acquirement of the knowledge which I sought; for the dominion I should acquire and
          transmit over the elemental foes of our race. As I spoke, a dark gloom spread over my
          listener’s countenance. At first I perceived that he tried to suppress his emotion; he
          placed his hands before his eyes; and my voice quivered and failed me, as I beheld tears
          trickle fast from between his fingers,—a groan burst from his heaving breast. I paused;
         —at length he spoke, in broken accents:—“Unhappy man! Do you share my madness? Have you
          drank also of the intoxicating draught? Hear me,—let me reveal my tale, and you will
          dash the cup from your lips!”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p27"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p28"/>Such words, you may imagine, strongly excited my curiosity; but the paroxysm of grief
          that had seized the stranger overcame his weakened powers, and many hours of repose and
          tranquil conversation were necessary to restore his composure.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p28"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p29"/>Having conquered the violence of his feelings, he appeared to despise himself for being
          the slave of passion; and quelling the dark tyranny of despair, he led me again to
          converse concerning myself personally. He asked me the history of my earlier years. The
          tale was quickly told: <pb xml:id="F1831_v_032" n="16"/>but it awakened various trains of
          reflection. I spoke of my desire of finding a friend—of my thirst for a more intimate
          sympathy with a fellow mind than had ever fallen to my lot; and expressed my conviction
          that a man could boast of little happiness, who did not enjoy this blessing.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p29"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p30"/>“I agree with you,” replied the stranger; “we are unfashioned creatures, but half made
          up, if one wiser, better, dearer than ourselves—such a friend ought to be—do not lend
          his aid to perfectionate our weak and faulty natures. I once had a friend, the most noble
          of human creatures, and am entitled, therefore, to judge respecting friendship. You have
          hope, and the world before you, and have no cause for despair. But I—I have lost every
          thing, and cannot begin life anew.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p30"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p31"/>As he said this, his countenance became expressive of a calm settled grief, that touched
          me to the heart. But he was silent, and presently retired to his cabin.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p31"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p32"/>Even broken in spirit as he is, no one can feel more deeply than he does the beauties of
          nature. The starry sky, the sea, and every sight afforded by these wonderful regions,
          seems still to have the power of elevating his soul from earth. Such a man has a double
          existence: he may suffer misery, and be overwhelmed by disappointments; yet, when he has
          retired into himself, he will be like a celestial spirit, that has a halo around him,
          within whose circle no grief or folly ventures.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p32"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p33"/>Will you smile at the enthusiasm I express concerning this divine wanderer? You would
          not, if you saw him. You have been tutored and refined by books and retirement from the
          world, and you are, therefore, somewhat fastidious; but this only renders you the more fit
          to appreciate the extraordinary merits of this wonderful man. Sometimes I have endeavoured
          to discover what quality it is which he possesses, that elevates him so immeasurably above
          any other person I ever knew. I believe it to be an intuitive discernment; a quick but
          never-failing power of judgment; a penetration into the causes of things, unequalled for
          clearness and precision; add to this a facility of expression, and a voice whose varied
          intonations are soul-subduing music.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p33"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p34"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1831_v_033" n="17"/>August 19. 17—.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p34"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p35"/>Yesterday the stranger said to me, “You may easily perceive, Captain Walton, that I have
          suffered great and unparalleled misfortunes. I had determined, at one time, that the
          memory of these evils should die with me; but you have won me to alter my determination.
          You seek for knowledge and wisdom, as I once did; and I ardently hope that the
          gratification of your wishes may not be a serpent to sting you, as mine has been. I do not
          know that the relation of my disasters will be useful to you; yet, when I reflect that you
          are pursuing the same course, exposing yourself to the same dangers which have rendered me
          what I am, I imagine that you may deduce an apt moral from my tale; one that may direct
          you if you succeed in your undertaking, and console you in case of failure. Prepare to
          hear of occurrences which are usually deemed marvellous. Were we among the tamer scenes of
          nature, I might fear to encounter your unbelief, perhaps your ridicule; but many things
          will appear possible in these wild and mysterious regions, which would provoke the
          laughter of those unacquainted with the ever-varied powers of nature:—nor can I doubt
          but that my tale conveys in its series internal evidence of the truth of the events of
          which it is composed.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p35"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p36"/>You may easily imagine that I was much gratified by the offered communication; yet I
          could not endure that he should renew his grief by a recital of his misfortunes. I felt
          the greatest eagerness to hear the promised narrative, partly from curiosity, and partly
          from a strong desire to ameliorate his fate, if it were in my power. I expressed these
          feelings in my answer.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p36"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p37"/>“I thank you,” he replied, “for your sympathy, but it is useless; my fate is nearly
          fulfilled. I wait but for one event, and then I shall repose in peace. I understand your
          feeling,” continued he, perceiving that I wished to interrupt him; “but you are mistaken,
          my friend, if thus you will allow me to name you; nothing can alter my destiny: listen to
          my history, and you will perceive how irrevocably it is determined.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p37"/>
        <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p38"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1831_v_034" n="18"/>He then told me, that he would commence his narrative
          the next day when I should be at leisure. This promise drew from me the warmest thanks. I
          have resolved every night, when I am not imperatively occupied by my duties, to record, as
          nearly as possible in his own words, what he has related during the day. If I should be
          engaged, I will at least make notes. This manuscript will doubtless afford you the
          greatest pleasure: but to me, who know him, and who hear it from his own lips, with what
          interest and sympathy shall I read it in some future day! Even now, as I commence my task,
          his full-toned voice swells in my ears; his lustrous eyes dwell on me with all their
          melancholy sweetness; I see his thin hand raised in animation, while the lineaments of his
          face are irradiated by the soul within. Strange and harrowing must be his story; frightful
          the storm which embraced the gallant vessel on its course, and wrecked it—thus!<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p38"/>
        <comment text="ebb: centered underscore a few lines below"/>
      </xml>
