<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C24c2"/>For some time I was lost in conjecture as to the cause of this; but yesterday
    an idea struck me, and if it is well founded, I conjure you to avow it. Reserve on such
    a point would be not only use<pb xml:id="F1823_v2_365" n="92"/>less, but draw down
    treble misery on us all.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p3"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p4"/>I trembled violently at this exordium, and my father continued—<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p4"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p5"/>“I confess, my son, that I have always looked forward to your marriage with your cousin
    as the tie of our domestic comfort, and the stay of my declining years. You were
    attached to each other from your earliest infancy; you studied together, and appeared,
    in dispositions and tastes, entirely suited to one another. But so blind is the
    experience of man, that what I conceived to be the best assistants to my plan may have
    entirely destroyed it. You, perhaps, regard her as your sister, without any wish that
    she might become your wife. Nay, you may have met with another whom you may love; and,
    considering yourself as bound in <pb xml:id="F1823_v2_366" n="93"/>honour to your
    cousin, this struggle may occasion the poignant misery which you appear to feel.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p5"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p6"/>“My dear father, re-assure yourself. I love my cousin tenderly and sincerely. I never
    saw any woman, who excited, as Elizabeth does, my warmest admiration and affection. My
    future hopes and prospects are entirely bound up in the expectation of our union.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p6"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div18_p7"/>“The expression of your sentiments on this subject, my dear Victor, gives me more
    pleasure than I have for some time experienced. If you feel thus, we shall assuredly be
    happy, however present events may cast a gloom over us.</xml>
