<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C24d"/>But it is this gloom which
    appears to have taken so strong a hold of your mind, that I wish to dissipate. Tell me,
    therefore, whether you object to an immediate solemnisation of the marriage. We have
    been unfortunate, and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_149" n="133"/>recent events have drawn us from
    that every-day tranquillity befitting my years and infirmities. You are younger; yet I
    do not suppose, possessed as you are of a competent fortune, that an early marriage
    would at all interfere with any future plans of honour and utility that you may have
    formed. Do not suppose, however, that I wish to dictate happiness to you, or that a
    delay on your part would cause me any serious uneasiness. Interpret my words with
    candour, and answer me, I conjure you, with confidence and sincerity.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p7"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p8"/>I listened to my father in silence, and remained for some time incapable of offering
    any reply. I revolved rapidly in my mind a multitude of thoughts, and endeavoured to
    arrive at some conclusion. Alas! to me the idea of an immediate union with my Elizabeth
    was one of horror and dismay. I was bound by a solemn promise, which I had not yet
    fulfilled, and dared not break; or, if I did, what manifold miseries might not impend
    over me and my devoted family! Could I enter into a festival with this deadly weight yet
    hanging round my neck, and bowing me to the ground. I must perform my engagement, and
    let the monster depart with his mate, before I allowed myself to enjoy the delight of an
    union from which I expected peace.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p8"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div18_p9"/>I remembered also the necessity imposed upon me of either journeying to England, or
    entering into a long correspondence with those philosophers of that country, whose
    knowledge and discoveries were of indispensable use to me in my present undertaking. The
    latter method of obtaining the desired intelligence was dilatory and unsatisfactory:
    besides,</xml>
