<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C24l"/>dreary
    imaginations, I passed through many beautiful and majestic scenes; but my eyes were
    fixed and unobserving. I could only think of the bourne of my travels, and the work
    which was to occupy me whilst they endured.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p16"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p17"/>After some days spent in listless indolence, during which I traversed many leagues, I
    arrived at Strasburgh, where I waited two days for Clerval. He came. Alas, how great was
    the contrast between <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_017" n="013"/>us! He was alive to every new
    scene; joyful when he saw the beauties of the setting sun, and more happy when he beheld
    it rise, and recommence a new day. He pointed out to me the shifting colours of the
    landscape, and the appearances of the sky. “This is what it is to live,” he cried, “now
    I enjoy existence! But you, my dear Frankenstein, wherefore are you desponding and
    sorrowful?” In truth, I was occupied by gloomy thoughts, and neither saw the descent of
    the evening star, nor the golden sun-rise reflected in the Rhine.—And you, my friend,
    would be far more amused with the journal of Clerval, who observed the scenery with an
    eye of feeling and delight, than to listen to my reflections. I, a miserable wretch,
    haunted by a curse that shut up every avenue to enjoyment.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p17"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p18"/>We had agreed to descend the Rhine <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_018" n="014"/>in a boat from
    Strasburgh to Rotterdam, whence we might take shipping for London. During this voyage,
    we passed by many willowy islands, and saw several beautiful towns. We staid a day at
    Manheim, and, on the fifth from our departure from Strasburgh, arrived at Mayence. The
    course of the Rhine below Mayence becomes much more picturesque. The river descends
    rapidly, and winds between hills, not high, but steep, and of beautiful forms. We saw
    many ruined castles standing on the edges of precipices, surrounded by black woods, high
    and inaccessible. This part of the Rhine, indeed, presents a singularly variegated
    landscape. In one spot you view rugged hills, ruined castles overlooking tremendous
    precipices, with the dark Rhine rushing beneath; and, on the sudden turn of a
    promontory, flourishing vineyards, with <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_019" n="015"/>green
    sloping banks, and a meandering river, and populous towns, occupy the scene.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p18"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p19"/>We travelled at the time of the vintage, and heard the song of the labourers, as we
    glided down the stream. Even I, depressed in mind <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p19_add1"/>by remor<add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p19_add1"/>, and my spirits continually agitated
    by gloomy feelings, even I was pleased. I lay at the bottom of the boat, and, as I gazed
    on the cloudless blue sky, I seemed to drink in a tranquillity to which I had long been
    a stranger. And if these were my sensations, who can describe those of Henry? He felt as
    if he had been transported to Fairy-land, and enjoyed a happiness seldom tasted by man.
    “I have seen,” he said, “the most beautiful scenes of my own country; I have visited the
    lakes of Lucerne and Uri, where the snowy mountains descend almost perpendicu<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_020" n="016"/>larly to the water, casting black and impenetrable
    shades, which would cause a gloomy and mournful appearance, were it not for the most
    verdant islands that relieve the eye by their gay appearance; I have seen this lake
    agitated by a tempest, when the wind tore up whirlwinds of water, and gave you an idea
    of what the water-spout must be on the great ocean, and the waves dash with fury the
    base of the mountain, where the priest and his mistress were overwhelmed by an
    avalanche, and where their dying voices are still said to be heard amid the pauses of
    the nightly wind; I have seen the mountains of La Valais, and the Pays de Vaud: but this
    country, Victor, pleases me more than all those wonders. The mountains of Switzerland
    are more majestic and strange; but there is a charm in the banks of this divine river, 
    <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_021" n="017"/>that I never before saw equalled. Look at that
    castle which overhangs yon precipice; and that also on the island, almost concealed
    amongst the foliage of those lovely trees; and now that group of labourers coming from
    among their vines; and that village half-hid in the recess of the mountain. Oh, surely,
    the spirit that inhabits and guards this place has a soul more in harmony with man, than
    those who pile the glacier, or retire to the inaccessible peaks of the mountains of our own country.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter17_div4_div19_p19"/>
</xml>
