<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C08a"/>
    <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="3"/>
    <head sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_head1"/>CHAPTER III.<head eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_head1"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p1"/> W<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p1_hi1"/>HEN<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p1_hi1"/> I had attained the age of seventeen, my parents
    resolved that I should become a student at the university of Ingolstadt. I had hitherto
    attended the schools of Geneva; but my father thought it necessary, for the completion
    of my education, that I should be made acquainted with other customs than those of my
    native country. My departure was therefore fixed at an early date; but, before the day
    resolved upon could arrive, the first misfortune of my life occurred—an omen, as it
    were, of my future misery.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p1"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p2"/>Elizabeth had caught the scarlet fever; her illness was severe, and she was in the
    greatest danger. During her illness, many arguments had been urged to persuade my mother
    to refrain from attending upon her. She had, at first, yielded to our entreaties; but
    when she heard that the life of her favourite was menaced, she could no longer control
    her anxiety. She attended her sick bed,—her watchful attentions triumphed over the
    malignity of the distemper,—Elizabeth was saved, but the consequences of this
    imprudence were fatal to her preserver. On the third day my mother sickened; her fever
    was accompanied by the most alarming symptoms, and the looks of her medical attendants
    prognosticated the worst event. On her death-bed the fortitude and benignity of this
    best of women did not desert her. She joined the hands of Elizabeth and myself:—“My
    children,” she said, “my firmest hopes of future happiness were placed on the prospect
    of your union. This expectation will now be the consolation of your father. Elizabeth,
    my love, you must supply my place to my younger children. Alas! I regret that I am taken
    from you; and, happy and beloved as I have been, <pb xml:id="F1831_v_046" n="30"/>is it
    not hard to quit you all? But these are not thoughts befitting me; I will endeavour to
    resign myself cheerfully to death, and will indulge a hope of meeting you in another
    world.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p2"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p3"/>She died calmly; and her countenance expressed affection even in death. I need not
    describe the feelings of those whose dearest ties are rent by that most irreparable
    evil; the void that presents itself to the soul; and the despair that is exhibited on
    the countenance. It is so long before the mind can persuade itself that she, whom we saw
    every day, and whose very existence appeared a part of our own, can have departed for
    ever—that the brightness of a beloved eye can have been extinguished, and the sound of
    a voice so familiar, and dear to the ear, can be hushed, never more to be heard. These
    are the reflections of the first days; but when the lapse of time proves the reality of
    the evil, then the actual bitterness of grief commences. Yet from whom has not that rude
    hand rent away some dear connection? and why should I describe a sorrow which all have
    felt, and must feel? The time at length arrives, when grief is rather an indulgence than
    a necessity; and the smile that plays upon the lips, although it may be deemed a
    sacrilege, is not banished. My mother was dead, but we had still duties which we ought
    to perform; we must continue our course with the rest, and learn to think ourselves
    fortunate, whilst one remains whom the spoiler has not seized.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p3"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p4"/>My departure for Ingolstadt, which had been deferred by these events, was now again
    determined upon. I obtained from my father a respite of some weeks.
</xml>
