<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C08e"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p8"/>I threw myself into the chaise that was to convey me away, and indulged in the most
    melancholy reflections. I, who had ever been surrounded by amiable companions,
    continually engaged in endeavouring to bestow mutual pleasure, I was now alone. In the
    university, whither I was going, I must form my own friends, and be my own protector. My
    life had hitherto been remarkably secluded and domestic; and this had given me
    invincible repugnance to new countenances. I loved my brothers, Elizabeth, and Clerval;
    these were “old familiar faces;” but I believed myself totally unfitted for the company
    of strangers. Such were my reflections as I commenced my journey; but as I proceeded, my
    spirits and hopes rose. I ardently desired the acquisition of knowledge. I had often,
    when at home, thought it hard to remain during my youth cooped up in one place, and had
    longed to enter the world, and take my <pb xml:id="F1831_v_048" n="32"/>station among
    other human beings. Now my desires were complied with, and it would, indeed, have been
    folly to repent.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p8"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p9"/>I had sufficient leisure for these and many other reflections during my journey to
    Ingolstadt, which was long and fatiguing. At length the high white steeple of the town
    met my eyes. I alighted, and was conducted to my solitary apartment, to spend the
    evening as I pleased.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p9"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p10"/>The next morning I delivered my letters of introduction, and paid a visit to some of
    the principal professors. Chance—or rather the evil influence, the Angel of
    Destruction, which asserted omnipotent sway over me from the moment I turned my
    reluctant steps from my father’s door—led me first to M. Krempe, professor of natural
    philosophy. He was an uncouth man, but deeply embued in the secrets of his science. He
    asked me several questions concerning my progress in the different branches of science
    appertaining to natural philosophy. I replied carelessly; and, partly in contempt,
    mentioned the names of my alchymists as the principal authors I had studied. The
    professor stared: “Have you,” he said, “really spent your time in studying such
    nonsense?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p10"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p11"/>I replied in the affirmative. “Every minute,” continued M. Krempe with warmth, “every
    instant that you have wasted on those books is utterly and entirely lost. You have
    burdened your memory with exploded systems and useless names. Good God! in what desert
    land have you lived, where no one was kind enough to inform you that these fancies,
    which you have so greedily imbibed, are a thousand years old, and as musty as they are
    ancient? I little expected, in this enlightened and scientific age, to find a disciple
    of Albertus Magnus and Paracelsus. My dear sir, you must begin your studies entirely
    anew.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p11"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p12"/>So saying, he stept aside, and wrote down a list of several books treating of natural
    philosophy, which he desired me to procure; and dismissed me, after mentioning that in
    the beginning of the following week he intended to commence a course of lectures upon
    natural philosophy in its general relations, and that M. Waldman, a fellow-professor,
    would lecture upon chemistry the alternate days that he omitted.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p12"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p13"/>
    <pb xml:id="F1831_v_049" n="33"/>I returned home, not disappointed, for I have said
    that I had long considered those authors useless whom the professor reprobated; but I
    returned, not at all the more inclined to recur to these studies in any shape. M. Krempe
    was a little squat man, with a gruff voice and a repulsive countenance; the teacher,
    therefore, did not prepossess me in favour of his</xml>
