<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C11"/>
      <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="5"/>
      <head sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_head1"/>CHAPTER V.<head eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_head1"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/>C<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/>LERVAL<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1_hi1"/> then put the following letter into my hands.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p1"/>

     <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1"/>
      <ab sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1"/>
         <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi1"/>To<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi1"/> V. F<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi2"/>RANKENSTEIN<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1_hi2"/>.<ab eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1_ab1"/>
      <del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_del1"/>
   
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/>“<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_hi1"/>MY DEAR COUSIN<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2_hi1"/>,<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p2"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/>“I cannot describe to you the uneasiness we have all felt concerning your health. We
            cannot help imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the extent of your disorder: for
            it is now several months since we have seen your hand-writing; and all this time you
            have been obliged to dictate your letters to Henry. Surely, Victor, you must have <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_127" n="115"/>been exceedingly ill; <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del1"/>and this makes us all very wretched, as much so nearly as after the death of your dear mother.<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del1"/>
      <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add1"/>and this suspicion fills us with anguish. I perceive that your father <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add1_del1"/>conceals<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add1_del1"/> attempts to conceal his fears from me; but cheerfulness has flown from our little circle, only to be restored by a certain assuranance that there is no foundation for our anxiety. At one time<add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add1"/> My uncle <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del2"/>was<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del2"/>
      <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add2"/>being<add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_add2"/> almost
            persuaded that you were indeed dangerously ill, <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del3"/>and<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3_del3"/> could hardly be restrained from
            undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. Clerval always writes that you are getting better;
            I eagerly hope that you will confirm this intelligence soon in your own hand-writing;
            for indeed, indeed, Victor, we are all very miserable on this account. Relieve us from
            this fear, and we shall be the happiest creatures in the world. Your father’s health is
            now so vigorous, that he appears ten years younger since last winter. Ernest also is so
            much improved, that you would hardly know him: he is now nearly sixteen, and has lost
            that sickly appearance which he had some years ago; he is grown quite robust and
            active.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p3"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_128" n="116"/>“My uncle and I conversed a long time last night
            about what profession Ernest should follow. His constant illness when young has deprived
            him of the habits of application; and now that he enjoys good health, he is continually
            in the open air, climbing the hills, or rowing on the lake. I therefore proposed that he
            should be a farmer; which you know, Cousin, is a favourite scheme of mine. A farmer’s is
            a very healthy happy life; and the least hurtful, or rather the most beneficial
            profession of any. My uncle had an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that
            through his interest he might become a judge. But, besides that he is not at all fitted
            for such an occupation, it is certainly more creditable to cultivate the earth for the
            sustenance of man, than to be the confidant, and sometimes the accomplice, of his vices;
            which is <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_129" n="117"/>the profession of a lawyer. I said, that
            the employments of a prosperous farmer, if they were not a more honourable, they were at
            least a happier species of occupation than that of a judge, whose misfortune it was
            always to meddle with the dark side of human nature. My uncle smiled, and said, that I
            ought to be an advocate myself, which put an end to the conversation on that
            subject.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p4"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/>“And now I must tell you a little story that will please, and perhaps amuse you. Do you
            not remember Justine Moritz? Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore,
            in a few words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom
            Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but,
            through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_130" n="118"/>her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt
            observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to
            allow her to live at her house. The republican institutions of our country have produced
            simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that
            surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several classes of its
            inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised, their manners
            are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a
            servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned the duties
            of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include the idea of
            ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p5"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_131" n="119"/>“After what I have said, I dare say you well
            remember the heroine of my little tale: for Justine was a great favourite of your’s; and
            I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an ill humour, one glance from
            Justine could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty
            of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment
            for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she
            had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful
            little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions, I never heard
            one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress.
            Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the
              <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_132" n="120"/>greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt.
            She thought her the model of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology
            and manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p6"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/>“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to notice
            poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious affection.
            Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/>“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her
            neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she
            began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise
            her partiality. She was a Roman Catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_133" n="121"/>the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few
            months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant
            mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our house: she was much altered since the
            death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which
            had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of
            a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance.
            She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of
            having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw
            Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now
            at peace for ever. She died on the first approach of cold wea<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_134" n="122"/>ther, at the beginning of this last winter. Justine has returned to us;
            and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and extremely
            pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind me of my
            dear aunt.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/>“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish
            you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark
            eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek,
            which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9_hi1"/>wives<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9_hi1"/>, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of
            age.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/>“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the
            good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_135" n="123"/>received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a
            young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the
            rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered
            several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already
            recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively
            pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but
            she is very much admired, and a favourite with every body.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/>“I have written myself into good spirits, dear cousin; yet I cannot conclude without
            again anxiously inquiring concerning your health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill,
            write yourself, and make your father and all <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_136" n="124"/>of us
            happy; or——I cannot bear to think of the other side of the question; my tears already
            flow. Adieu, my dearest cousin.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/>“E<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi1"/>LIZABETH<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi1"/> L<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi2"/>AVENZA<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12_hi2"/>.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/>“Geneva, March 18th, 17—.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/>
      <note sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_note1"/>This letter ought to be re-written.<note eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_note1"/>
      <!--2018-04-25 ebb: This collation unit is identical to the 1818 text (no changes in Thomas copy here).-->
      </xml>
