<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C26a"/>
    <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="19"/>
    <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_044" n="040"/>
    <head sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_head1"/>CHAPTER III.<head eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_head1"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p1"/>I <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p1_hi1"/>SAT<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p1_hi1"/> one evening in my laboratory; the sun had set, and the
    moon was just rising from the sea; I had not sufficient light for my employment, and I
    remained idle, in a pause of consideration of whether I should leave my labour for the
    night, or hasten its conclusion by an unremitting attention to it. As I sat, a train of
    reflection occurred to me, which led me to consider the effects of what I was now doing.
    Three years before I was engaged in the same manner, and had created a fiend whose
    unparalleled barbarity had desolated my <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_045" n="041"/>heart, and
    filled it for ever with the bitterest remorse. I was now about to form another being, of
    whose dispositions I was alike ignorant; she might become ten thousand times more
    malignant than her mate, and delight, for its own sake, in murder and wretchedness. He
    had sworn to quit the neighbourhood of man, and hide himself in deserts; but she had
    not; and she, who in all probability was to become a thinking and reasoning animal,
    might refuse to comply with a compact made before her creation. They might even hate
    each other; the creature who already lived loathed his own deformity, and might he not
    conceive a greater abhorrence for it when it came before his eyes in the female form?
    She also might turn with disgust from him to the superior beauty of man; she might quit
    him, and he be again alone, exasperated by the fresh <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_046" n="042"/>provocation of being deserted by one of his own species.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p1"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p2"/>Even if they were to leave Europe, and inhabit the deserts of the new world, yet one of
    the first results of those sympathies for which the dæmon thirsted would be children,
    and a race of devils would be propagated upon the earth, who might make the very
    existence of the species of man a condition precarious and full of terror. Had I a
    right, for my own benefit, to inflict this curse upon everlasting generations? I had
    before been moved by the sophisms of the being I had created; I had been struck
    senseless by his fiendish threats: but now, for the first time, the wickedness of my
    promise burst upon me; I shuddered to think that future ages might curse me as their
    pest, whose selfishness had not hesitated to buy its own peace at <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_047" n="043"/>the price perhaps of the existence of the whole
    human race.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p2"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p3"/>I trembled, and my heart failed within me; when, on looking up, I saw, by the light of
    the moon, the dæmon at the casement. A ghastly grin wrinkled his lips as he gazed on me,
    where I sat fulfilling the task which he had allotted to me. Yes, he had followed me in
    my travels; he had loitered in forests, hid himself in caves, or taken refuge in wide
    and desert heaths; and he now came to mark my progress, and claim the fulfilment of my
    promise.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p3"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p4"/>As I looked on him, his countenance expressed the utmost extent of malice and
    treachery. I thought with a sensation of madness on my promise of creating another like to
    him, and, trembling with passion, tore to pieces the thing on which I was engaged. The
    wretch saw me destroy the creature on <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_048" n="044"/>whose future
    existence he depended for happiness, and, with a howl of devilish despair and revenge,
    withdrew.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p4"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p5"/>I left the room, and, locking the door, made a solemn vow in my own heart never to
    resume my labours; and then, with trembling steps, I sought my own apartment. I was
    alone; none were near me to dissipate the gloom, and relieve me from the sickening
    oppression of the most terrible reveries.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p5"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p6"/>Several hours past, and I remained near my window gazing on the sea; it was almost
    motionless, for the winds were hushed, and all nature reposed under the eye of the quiet
    moon. A few fishing vessels alone specked the water, and now and then the gentle breeze
    wafted the sound of voices, as the fishermen called to one another. I felt the silence,
    although I was hardly conscious of its extreme profundity, <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_049" n="045"/>until my ear was suddenly arrested by the paddling of oars near the shore,
    and a person landed close to my house.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p6"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p7"/>In a few minutes after, I heard the creaking of my door, as if some one endeavoured to
    open it softly. I trembled from head to foot; I felt a presentiment of who it was, and
    wished to rouse one of the peasants who dwelt in a cottage not far from mine; but I was
    overcome by the sensation of helplessness, so often felt in frightful dreams, when you
    in vain endeavour to fly from an impending danger, and was rooted to the spot.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p7"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p8"/>Presently I heard the sound of footsteps along the passage; the door opened, and the
    wretch whom I dreaded appeared. Shutting the door, he approached me, and said, in a
    smothered voice—<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p8"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p9"/>“You have destroyed the work <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_050" n="046"/>which you began;
    what is it that you intend? Do you dare to break your promise? I have endured toil and
    misery: I left Switzerland with you; I crept along the shores of the Rhine, among its
    willow islands, and over the summits of its hills. I have dwelt many months in the
    heaths of England, and among the deserts of Scotland. I have endured incalculable
    fatigue, and cold, and hunger; do you dare destroy my hopes?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p9"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p10"/>“Begone! I do break my promise; never will I create another like yourself, equal in
    deformity and wickedness.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p10"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p11"/>“Slave, I before reasoned with you, but you have proved yourself unworthy of my
    condescension. Remember that I have power; you believe yourself miserable, but I can
    make you so wretched that the light of day will be <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_051" n="047"/>hateful to you. You are my creator, but I am your master;—obey!”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p11"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p12"/>“The hour of my weakness is past, and the period of your power is arrived. Your threats
    cannot move me to do an act of wickedness; but they confirm me in a resolution of not
    creating you a companion in vice. Shall I, in cool blood, set loose upon the earth a
    dæmon, whose delight is in death and wretchedness. Begone! I am firm, and your words
    will only exasperate my rage.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p12"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p13"/>The monster saw my determination in my face, and gnashed his teeth in the impotence of
    anger. “Shall each man,” cried he, “find a wife for his bosom, and each beast have his
    mate, and I be alone? I had feelings of affection, and they were requited by detestation
    and scorn. Man, you may hate; but beware! Your hours will pass in dread and <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_052" n="048"/>misery, and soon the bolt will fall which must
    ravish from you your happiness for ever. Are you to be happy, while I grovel in the
    intensity of my wretchedness? You can blast my other passions; but revenge
    remains—revenge, henceforth dearer than light or food! I may die; but first you, my
    tyrant and tormentor, shall curse the sun that gazes on your misery. Beware; for I am
    fearless, and therefore powerful. I will watch with the wiliness of a snake, that I may
    sting with its venom. Man, you shall repent of the injuries you inflict.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p13"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p14"/>“Devil, cease; and do not poison the air with these sounds of malice. I have declared
    my resolution to you, and I am no coward to bend beneath words. Leave me; I am
    inexorable.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p14"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p15"/>“It is well. I go; but remember, I shall be with you on your wedding-night.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p15"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p16"/>
    <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_053" n="049"/>I started forward, and exclaimed, “Villain!
    before you sign my death-warrant, be sure that you are yourself safe.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p16"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p17"/>I would have seized him; but he eluded me, and quitted the house with precipitation: in
    a few moments I saw him in his boat, which shot across the waters with an arrowy
    swiftness, and was soon lost amidst the waves.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p17"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p18"/>All was again silent; but his words rung in my ears. I burned with rage to pursue the
    murderer of my peace, and precipitate him into the ocean. I walked up and down my room
    hastily and perturbed, while my imagination conjured up a thousand images to torment and
    sting me. Why had I not followed him, and closed with him in mortal strife? But I had
    suffered him to depart, and he had directed his course towards the main land. I shud<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_054" n="050"/>dered to think who might be the next victim
    sacrificed to his insatiate revenge. And then I thought again of his words—“<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p18_hi1"/>I will be with you on your wedding-night<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p18_hi1"/>.” That then was the period
    fixed for the fulfilment of my destiny. In that hour I should die, and at once satisfy
    and extinguish his malice. The prospect did not move me to fear; yet when I thought of
    my beloved Elizabeth,—of her tears and endless sorrow, when she should find her lover so
    barbarously snatched from her,—tears, the first I had shed for many months, streamed
    from my eyes, and I resolved not to fall before my enemy without a bitter struggle.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p18"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p19"/>The night passed away, and the sun rose from the ocean; my feelings became calmer, if
    it may be called calmness, when the violence of rage sinks into the depths of despair. I
    left the <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_055" n="051"/>house, the horrid scene of the last
    night’s contention, and walked on the beach of the sea, which I almost regarded as an
    insuperable barrier between me and my fellow-creatures; nay, a wish that such should
    prove the fact stole across me. I desired that I might pass my life on that barren rock,
    wearily it is true, but uninterrupted by any sudden shock of misery. If I returned, it
    was to be sacrificed, or to see those whom I most loved die under the grasp of a dæmon
    whom I had myself created.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p19"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p20"/>I walked about the isle like a restless spectre, separated from all it loved, and
    miserable in the separation. When it became noon, and the sun rose higher, I lay down on
    the grass, and was overpowered by a deep sleep. I had been awake the whole of the
    preceding night, my nerves were agitated, <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_056" n="052"/>and my
    eyes inflamed by watching and misery. The sleep into which I now sunk refreshed me; and
    when I awoke, I again felt as if I belonged to a race of human beings like myself, and I
    began to reflect upon what had passed with greater composure; yet still the words of the
    fiend rung in my ears like a death-knell, they appeared like a dream, yet distinct and
    oppressive as a reality.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p20"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p21"/>The sun had far descended, and I still sat on the shore, satisfying my appetite, which
    had become ravenous, with an oaten cake, when I saw a fishing-boat land close to me, and
    one of the men brought me a packet; it contained letters from Geneva, and one from
    Clerval, entreating me to join him. He said that</xml>
