<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C26e"/>into a reverie, so despairing and
            frightful, that even now, when the scene is on the point of closing before me for ever,
            I shudder to reflect on it.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p25"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p26"/>Some hours passed thus; but by degrees, as the sun declined towards the horizon, the
            wind died away into a gentle breeze, and the sea became free from breakers. But these
            gave place to a heavy swell; I felt sick, and hardly able to hold the rudder, when
            suddenly <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_063" n="059"/>I saw a line of high land towards the
      south.<note sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p26_note1"/>Thomas copy: pencil mark joins paragraphs.<note eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p26_note1"/> Almost spent, as I was, by fatigue, and the dreadful suspense I endured for several
            hours, this sudden certainty of life rushed like a flood of warm joy to my heart, and
            tears gushed from my eyes.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p26"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p27"/>How mutable are our feelings, and how strange is that clinging love we have of life
            even in the excess of misery! I constructed another sail with a part of my dress, and
            eagerly steered my course towards the land. It had a wild and rocky appearance; but, as
            I approached nearer, I easily perceived the traces of cultivation. I saw vessels near
            the shore, and found myself suddenly transported back to the neighbourhood of civilized
            man. I eagerly traced the windings of the land, and hailed a steeple which I at length
            saw <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_064" n="060"/>issuing from behind a small promontory. As I
            was in a state of extreme debility, I resolved to sail directly towards the town as a
            place where I could most easily procure nourishment. Fortunately I had money with me. As
            I turned the promontory, I perceived a small neat town and a good harbour, which I
            entered, my heart bounding with joy at my unexpected escape.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p27"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p28"/>As I was occupied in fixing the boat and arranging the sails, several people crowded
            towards the spot. They seemed very much surprised at my appearance; but, instead of
            offering me any assistance, whispered together with gestures that at any other time
            might have produced in me a slight sensation of alarm. As it was, I merely remarked that
            they spoke English; and I therefore addressed them in that language: “My good friends,”
            said I, “will you be so <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_065" n="061"/>kind as to tell me the
            name of this town, and inform me where I am?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p28"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p29"/>“You will know that soon enough,” replied a man with a gruff voice. “May be you are
            come to a place that will not prove much to your taste; but you will not be consulted as
            to your quarters, I promise you.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p29"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p30"/>I was exceedingly surprised on receiving so rude an answer from a stranger; and I was
            also disconcerted on perceiving the frowning and angry countenances of his companions.
            “Why do you answer me so roughly?” I replied: “surely it is not the custom of Englishmen
            to receive strangers so inhospitably.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p30"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p31"/>“I do not know,” said the man, “what the custom of the English may be; but it is the
            custom of the Irish to hate villains.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p31"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p32"/>While this strange dialogue continued, <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_066" n="062"/>I
            perceived the crowd rapidly increase. Their faces expressed a mixture of curiosity and
            anger, which annoyed, and in some degree alarmed me. I inquired the way to the inn; but
            no one replied. I then moved forward, and a murmuring sound arose from the crowd as they
            followed and surrounded me; when an ill-looking man approaching, tapped me on the
            shoulder, and said, “Come, Sir, you must follow me to Mr. Kirwin’s, to give an account
            of yourself.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p32"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p33"/>“Who is Mr. Kirwin? Why am I to give an account of myself? Is not this a free
            country?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p33"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p34"/>“Ay, Sir, free enough for honest folks. Mr. Kirwin is a magistrate; and you are to give
            an account of the death of a gentleman who was found murdered here last night.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p34"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p35"/>This answer startled me; but I presently <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_067" n="063"/>recovered myself. I was innocent; that could easily be proved: accordingly I followed
            my conductor in silence, and was led to one of the best houses in the town. I was ready
            to sink from fatigue and hunger; but, being surrounded by a crowd, I thought it politic
            to rouse all my strength, that no physical debility might be construed into apprehension
            or conscious guilt. Little did I then expect the calamity that was in a few moments to
            overwhelm me, and extinguish in horror and despair all fear of ignominy or death.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p35"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p36"/>I must pause here; for it requires all my fortitude to recall the memory of the
            frightful events which I am about to relate, in proper detail, to my recollection.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter19_div4_div21_p36"/>
      <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="19"/>

      </xml>
