<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="f1818_C02">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 2: Witness f1818, Collation unit C02</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-05-17 09:45:57.032761 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab type="alignmentChunk" xml:id="C02">
               <seg xml:id="C02_app1-#f1818_start"/>&lt;milestone n="1" type="start" unit="novel"/&gt;FRANKENSTEIN;OR,
            THEMODERN <seg xml:id="C02_app1-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app2-#f1818_start"/>PROMETHEUS.&lt;milestone n="1" type="start" unit="letter"/&gt;LETTER <seg xml:id="C02_app2-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app3-#f1818_start"/>I <seg xml:id="C02_app3-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app4-#f1818_start"/>&lt;ab&gt; <seg xml:id="C02_app4-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app5-#f1818_start"/>To <seg xml:id="C02_app5-#f1818_end"/>
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app6-#f1818_start"/>Mrs. SAVILLE, <seg xml:id="C02_app6-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app7-#f1818_start"/>England. &lt;/ab&gt;&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p6__Start"/&gt;St. <seg xml:id="C02_app7-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app8-#f1818_start"/>Petersburgh, Dec. 11th, 17—.&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p6__End"/&gt;&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p7__Start"/&gt;YOU will rejoice to hear that no disaster has
            accompanied the commencement of an enterprise which you have regarded with such evil
            forebodings. I arrived here yesterday; and my first task is to assure my dear sister of
            my welfare, and increasing confidence in the success of my undertaking.&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p7__End"/&gt;&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p8__Start"/&gt;I am already
            far north of London; and as I walk in the streets of Petersburgh, I feel a cold northern
            breeze play upon my cheeks, which braces my nerves, and fills me with delight. Do you
            understand this feeling? This breeze, which has travelled from the regions towards which
            I am advancing, gives me a foretaste of those icy climes. Inspirited by this wind of
            promise, my day dreams become more fervent and vivid. I try in vain to be persuaded that
            the pole is the seat of frost and desolation; it ever presents itself to my imagination
            as the region of beauty and delight. There, Margaret, the sun is <seg xml:id="C02_app8-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app10-#f1818_start"/>for <seg xml:id="C02_app10-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app11-#f1818_start"/>ever visible; <seg xml:id="C02_app11-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app12-#f1818_start"/>its broad disk just skirting the horizon, and diffusing a perpetual
            splendour. There—for with your leave, my sister, I will put some trust in preceding
            navigators—there snow and frost are banished; and, sailing over a calm sea, we may be
            wafted to a land surpassing in wonders and in beauty every region hitherto discovered on
            the habitable globe. Its productions and features may be without example, as the <seg xml:id="C02_app12-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app13-#f1818_start"/>phænomena <seg xml:id="C02_app13-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app14-#f1818_start"/>of the heavenly bodies undoubtedly are in those undiscovered solitudes.
            What may not be expected in a country of eternal <seg xml:id="C02_app14-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app15-#f1818_start"/>light? <seg xml:id="C02_app15-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app16-#f1818_start"/>I may there discover the wondrous power which attracts the needle; and may
            regulate a thousand celestial observations, that require only this voyage to render
            their seeming eccentricities consistent for ever. I shall satiate my ardent curiosity
            with the sight of a part of the world never before visited, and may tread a land never
            before imprinted by the foot of man. These are my enticements, and they are sufficient
            to conquer all fear of danger or death, and to induce me to commence this laborious
            voyage with the joy a child feels when he embarks in a little boat, with his holiday
            mates, on an expedition of discovery up his native river. But, supposing all these
            conjectures to be false, you cannot contest the inestimable benefit which I shall confer
            on all mankind to the last generation, by discovering a passage near the pole to those
            countries, to reach which at present so many months are requisite; or by ascertaining
            the secret of the magnet, which, if at all possible, can only be effected by an
            undertaking such as mine.&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p8__End"/&gt;&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p9__Start"/&gt;These reflections have dispelled the agitation with
            which I began my letter, and I feel my heart glow with an enthusiasm which elevates me
            to heaven; for nothing contributes so much to <seg xml:id="C02_app16-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app17-#f1818_start"/>tranquillize <seg xml:id="C02_app17-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app18-#f1818_start"/>the mind as a steady purpose,—a point on which the soul may fix its
            intellectual eye. This expedition has been the favourite dream of my early years. I have
            read with ardour the accounts of the various voyages which have been made in the
            prospect of arriving at the North Pacific Ocean through the seas which surround the
            pole. You may remember, that a history of all the voyages made for purposes of discovery
            composed the whole of our good uncle Thomas’s library. My education was neglected, yet I
            was passionately fond of reading. These volumes were my study day and night, and my
            familiarity with them increased that regret which I had felt, as a child, on learning
            that my father’s dying injunction had forbidden my uncle to allow me to embark in a <seg xml:id="C02_app18-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app19-#f1818_start"/>sea-faring <seg xml:id="C02_app19-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app20-#f1818_start"/>life.&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p9__End"/&gt;&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p10__Start"/&gt;These visions faded when I perused, for the first
            time, those poets whose effusions entranced my soul, and lifted it to heaven. I also
            became a poet, and for one year lived in a Paradise of my own creation; I imagined that
            I also might obtain a niche in the temple where the names of Homer and <seg xml:id="C02_app20-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app21-#f1818_start"/>Shakespeare <seg xml:id="C02_app21-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app22-#f1818_start"/>are consecrated. You are well acquainted with my failure, and how heavily
            I bore the disappointment. But just at that time I inherited the fortune of my cousin,
            and my thoughts were turned into the channel of their earlier bent.&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p10__End"/&gt;&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p11__Start"/&gt;Six years
            have passed since I resolved on my present undertaking. I can, even now, remember the
            hour from which I dedicated myself to this great enterprise. I commenced by inuring my
            body to hardship. I accompanied the whale-fishers on several expeditions to the North
            Sea; I voluntarily endured cold, famine, thirst, and want of sleep; I often worked
            harder than the common sailors during the day, and devoted my nights to the study of
            mathematics, the theory of medicine, and those branches of physical science from which a
            naval adventurer might derive the greatest practical advantage. Twice I actually hired
            myself as an under-mate in a Greenland whaler, and acquitted myself to admiration. I
            must own I felt a little proud, when my captain offered me the second dignity in the
            vessel, and entreated me to remain with the greatest earnestness; so valuable did he
            consider my services.&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p11__End"/&gt;&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p12__Start"/&gt;And now, dear Margaret, do I not deserve to
            accomplish some great purpose? My life might have been passed in ease and luxury; but I
            preferred glory to every enticement that wealth placed in my path. Oh, that some
            encouraging voice would answer in the affirmative! My courage and my resolution is firm;
            but my hopes fluctuate, and my spirits are often depressed. I am about to proceed on a
            long and difficult <seg xml:id="C02_app22-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app23-#f1818_start"/>voyage; <seg xml:id="C02_app23-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app24-#f1818_start"/>the emergencies of which will demand all my fortitude: I am required not
            only to raise the spirits of others, but sometimes to sustain my own, when <seg xml:id="C02_app24-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app25-#f1818_start"/>their’s <seg xml:id="C02_app25-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app26-#f1818_start"/>are failing.&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p12__End"/&gt;&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p13__Start"/&gt;This is the most favourable period for travelling in
            Russia. They fly quickly over the snow in their sledges; the motion is pleasant, and, in
            my opinion, far more agreeable than that of an English stage-coach. The cold is not
            excessive, if you are <seg xml:id="C02_app26-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app27-#f1818_start"/>wrapt <seg xml:id="C02_app27-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C02_app28-#f1818_start"/>in <seg xml:id="C02_app28-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app29-#f1818_start"/>furs, a <seg xml:id="C02_app29-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app30-#f1818_start"/>dress which I have already adopted; for there is a great difference
            between walking the deck and remaining seated motionless for hours, when no exercise
            prevents the blood from actually freezing in your veins. I have no ambition to lose my
            life on the post-road between St. Petersburgh and Archangel.&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p13__End"/&gt;&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p14__Start"/&gt;I shall
            depart for the latter town in a fortnight or three weeks; and my intention is to hire a
            ship there, which can easily be done by paying the insurance for the owner, and to
            engage as many sailors as I think necessary among those who are accustomed to the
            whale-fishing. I do not intend to sail until the month of <seg xml:id="C02_app30-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app31-#f1818_start"/>June: <seg xml:id="C02_app31-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app32-#f1818_start"/>and when shall I return? Ah, dear sister, how can I answer this question?
            If I succeed, many, many months, perhaps years, will pass before you and I may meet. If
            I fail, you will see me again soon, or never.&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p14__End"/&gt;&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p15__Start"/&gt;Farewell, my
            dear, <seg xml:id="C02_app32-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app33-#f1818_start"/>excellent, <seg xml:id="C02_app33-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            
               <seg xml:id="C02_app34-#f1818_start"/>Margaret. Heaven shower down blessings on you, and save me, that I may
            again and again testify my gratitude for all your love and kindness.&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p15__End"/&gt;&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p16__Start"/&gt;Your
            affectionate brother,&lt;p loc="novel1_letter1_p16__End"/&gt;&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p17__Start"/&gt;R. WALTON.&lt;p
            loc="novel1_letter1_p17__End"/&gt;&lt;milestone n="1" type="end" unit="letter"/&gt; <seg xml:id="C02_app34-#f1818_end"/>
               
               
               
            </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
