<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C14B"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p24"/>
    <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_188" n="176"/>“Oh, Justine! forgive me for having for one
    moment distrusted you. Why did you confess? But do not mourn, my dear girl; I will every
    where proclaim your innocence, and force belief. Yet you must die; you, my playfellow,
    my companion, my more than sister. I never can survive so horrible a misfortune.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p24"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p25"/>“Dear, sweet Elizabeth, do not weep. You ought to raise me with thoughts of a better
    life, and elevate me from the petty cares of this world of injustice and strife. Do not
    you, excellent friend, drive me to despair.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p25"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p26"/>“I will try to comfort you; but this, I fear, is an evil too deep and poignant to admit
    of consolation, for there is no hope. Yet heaven bless thee, my dearest Justine, with
    resignation, and a confidence elevated beyond this world. Oh! how I hate its shews and
    mock<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_189" n="177"/>eries! when one creature is murdered,
    another is immediately deprived of life in a slow torturing manner; then the
    executioners, their hands yet reeking with the blood of innocence, believe that they
    have done a great deed. They call this <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p26_hi1"/>retribution<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p26_hi1"/>. Hateful name!
    When that word is pronounced, I know greater and more horrid punishments are going to be
    inflicted than the gloomiest tyrant has ever invented to satiate his utmost revenge. Yet
    this is not consolation for you, my Justine, unless indeed that you may glory in
    escaping from so miserable a den. Alas! I would I were in peace with my aunt and my
    lovely William, escaped from a world which is hateful to me, and the visages of men
    which I abhor.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p26"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p27"/>Justine smiled languidly. “This, dear lady, is despair, and not resignation. I must not
    learn the lesson that <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_190" n="178"/>you would teach me. Talk of
    something else, something that will bring peace, and not increase of misery.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p27"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p28"/>During this conversation I had retired to a corner of the prison-room, where I could
    conceal the horrid anguish that possessed me. Despair! Who dared talk of that? The
    poor victim, who on the morrow was to pass the dreary boundary between life and death,
    felt not as I did, such deep and bitter agony. I gnashed my teeth, and ground them
    together, uttering a groan that came from my inmost soul. Justine started. When she saw
    who it was, she approached me, and said, “Dear Sir, you are very kind to visit me; you,
    I hope, do not believe that I am guilty.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p28"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p29"/>I could not answer. “No, Justine,” said Elizabeth; “he is more convinced of your
    innocence than I was; for <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_191" n="179"/>even when he heard that
    you had confessed, he did not credit it.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p29"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p30"/>“I truly thank him. In these last moments I feel the sincerest gratitude towards those
    who think of me with kindness. How sweet is the affection of others to such a wretch as
    I am! It removes more than half my misfortune; and I feel as if I could die in peace,
    now that my innocence is acknowledged by you, dear lady, and your cousin.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p30"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p31"/>Thus the poor sufferer tried to comfort others and herself. She indeed gained the
    resignation she desired. But I, the true murderer, felt the never-dying worm alive in my
    bosom, which allowed of no hope or consolation. Elizabeth also wept, and was unhappy;
    but her’s also was the misery of innocence, which, like a cloud that passes over the
    fair moon, for a while hides, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_192" n="180"/>but cannot tarnish
    its brightness. Anguish and despair had penetrated into the core of my heart; I bore a
    hell within me, which nothing could extinguish. We staid several hours with Justine; and
    it was with great difficulty that Elizabeth could tear herself away. “I wish,” cried
    she, “that I were to die with you; I cannot live in this world of misery.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p31"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p32"/>Justine assumed an air of cheerfulness, while she with difficulty repressed her bitter
    tears. She embraced Elizabeth, and said, in a voice of half-suppressed emotion,
    “Farewell, sweet lady, dearest Elizabeth, my beloved and only friend; may heaven in its
    bounty bless and preserve you; may this be the last misfortune that you will ever
    suffer. Live, and be happy, and make others so.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p32"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p33"/>As we returned, Elizabeth said, “You <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_193" n="181"/>know not, my
    dear Victor, how much I am relieved, now that I trust in the innocence of this
    unfortunate girl. I never could again have known peace, if I had been deceived in my
    reliance on her. For the moment that I did believe her guilty, I felt an anguish that I
    could not have long sustained. Now my heart is lightened. The innocent suffers; but she
    whom I thought amiable and good has not betrayed the trust I reposed in her, and I am
    consoled.<comment text="RM: sic close quote missing ”"/>
    <p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p33"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p34"/>Amiable cousin! such were your thoughts, mild and gentle as your own dear eyes and
    voice. But I—I was a wretch, and none ever conceived of the misery that I then
    endured.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p34"/>
    <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="7"/>
    <head sID="novel1_letter4_div4_head6"/>END OF VOL. I.<head eID="novel1_letter4_div4_head6"/>
    <milestone unit="volume" n="2"/>
    <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="start" n="2"/>
    <include href="standOff_Includes/1818_frontMatter2.xml" parse="xml"/>
    <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="end" n="2"/>
</xml>
