<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C14d"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p28"/>During this conversation I had retired to a corner of the prison-room, where I could
    conceal the horrid anguish that possessed me. Despair! Who dared talk of that? The
    poor victim, who on the morrow was to pass the dreary boundary between life and death,
    felt not as I did, such deep and bitter agony. I gnashed my teeth, and ground them
    together, uttering a groan that came from my inmost soul. Justine started. When she saw
    who it was, she approached me, and said, “Dear Sir, you are very kind to visit me; you,
    I hope, do not believe that I am guilty.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p28"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p29"/>I could not answer. “No, Justine,” said Elizabeth; “he is more convinced of your
    innocence than I was; for <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_191" n="179"/>even when he heard that
    you had confessed, he did not credit it.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p29"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p30"/>“I truly thank him. In these last moments I feel the sincerest gratitude towards those
    who think of me with kindness. How sweet is the affection of others to such a wretch as
    I am! It removes more than half my misfortune; and I feel as if I could die in peace,
    now that my innocence is acknowledged by you, dear lady, and your cousin.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p30"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p31"/>Thus the poor sufferer tried to comfort others and herself. She indeed gained the
    resignation she desired. But I, the true murderer, felt the never-dying worm alive in my
    bosom, which allowed of no hope or consolation. Elizabeth also wept, and was unhappy;
    but her’s also was the misery of innocence, which, like a cloud that passes over the
    fair moon, for a while hides, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_192" n="180"/>but cannot tarnish
    its brightness. Anguish and despair had penetrated into the core of my heart; I bore a
    hell within me, which nothing could extinguish. We staid several hours with Justine; and
    it was with great difficulty that Elizabeth could tear herself away. “I wish,” cried
    she, “that I were to die with you; I cannot live in this world of misery.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p31"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p32"/>Justine assumed an air of cheerfulness, while she with difficulty repressed her bitter
    tears. She embraced Elizabeth, and said, in a voice of half-suppressed emotion,
    “Farewell, sweet lady, dearest Elizabeth, my beloved and only friend; may heaven in its
    bounty bless and preserve you; may this be the last misfortune that you will ever
    suffer. Live, and be happy, and make others so.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p32"/>
</xml>
