<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness fThomas, Collation unit C25</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app1-fThomas__Pt1">
            <milestone n="18" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <pb n="021" xml:id="F1818_v3_025"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_head1">CHAPTER II.</head>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app1-fThomas__Pt2">L<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1_hi1">ONDON</hi> 
               </seg>was our present point of rest; we determined to remain several months in this wonderful and celebrated city. <seg xml:id="C25_app9-fThomas">Clerval desired </seg>the intercourse of the men of genius and talent who flourished at <seg xml:id="C25_app13-fThomas">this </seg>time; but this <seg xml:id="C25_app15-fThomas">was </seg>with <seg xml:id="C25_app17-fThomas">me </seg>a secondary <seg xml:id="C25_app19-fThomas">object; </seg>I was principally occupied with the means of obtaining the information necessary for the completion of my <seg xml:id="C25_app23-fThomas">promise, </seg>and quickly availed myself of the letters of introduction that I had brought with <seg xml:id="C25_app29-fThomas">me, </seg>addressed to the <seg xml:id="C25_app33-fThomas">most </seg>distinguished natural <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app37-fThomas__Pt1">philosophers.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app37-fThomas__Pt2">If </seg>this journey had taken place during <seg xml:id="C25_app41-fThomas">
               <pb n="022" xml:id="F1818_v3_026"/>my </seg>days of study and <seg xml:id="C25_app43-fThomas">happiness, </seg>it would have afforded me inexpressible pleasure. But a blight had come over my <seg xml:id="C25_app51-fThomas">existence, </seg>and I only visited these people for the sake of the information they might <seg xml:id="C25_app57-fThomas">give </seg>me on the subject in which <seg xml:id="C25_app61-fThomas">my interest </seg>was so <seg xml:id="C25_app63-fThomas">terribly profound. </seg>Company was <seg xml:id="C25_app65-fThomas">irksome </seg>to me; when <seg xml:id="C25_app69-fThomas">alone, </seg>I could fill my mind with the sights of heaven and earth; the voice of <seg xml:id="C25_app73-fThomas">Henry </seg>soothed <seg xml:id="C25_app75-fThomas">me, </seg>and I could <seg xml:id="C25_app77-fThomas">thus </seg>cheat myself into a transitory peace. But <seg xml:id="C25_app79-fThomas">busy uninteresting </seg>joyous faces brought back despair to my heart. I saw an insurmountable <seg xml:id="C25_app81-fThomas">barrier </seg>placed between me and my <seg xml:id="C25_app83-fThomas">fellow-men; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app84-fThomas">this </seg>barrier was sealed with the blood of William and <seg xml:id="C25_app86-fThomas">Justine; </seg>and to reflect on <seg xml:id="C25_app88-fThomas">the events connected with </seg>those <seg xml:id="C25_app90-fThomas">names </seg>filled my soul with <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app92-fThomas__Pt1">anguish.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app92-fThomas__Pt2">But </seg>in <seg xml:id="C25_app94-fThomas">Clerval </seg>I saw the image of my former self; he was <seg xml:id="C25_app98-fThomas">inquisitive, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app100-fThomas">an<pb n="023" xml:id="F1818_v3_027"/>xious </seg>to gain experience and <seg xml:id="C25_app102-fThomas">instruction. </seg>The difference of manners <seg xml:id="C25_app106-fThomas">which </seg>he observed was to him an inexhaustible source <seg xml:id="C25_app112-fThomas">of instruction and amusement. </seg>He was for ever <seg xml:id="C25_app117-fThomas">busy; </seg>and the only check to his enjoyments was my <seg xml:id="C25_app121-fThomas">sorrowful and </seg>dejected <seg xml:id="C25_app123-fThomas">mien. </seg>I tried to conceal this as much as <seg xml:id="C25_app127-fThomas">possible, </seg>that I might not debar him from the <seg xml:id="C25_app131-fThomas">pleasures </seg>natural to <seg xml:id="C25_app135-fThomas">one </seg>who was entering on a new scene of life, undisturbed by any care or <seg xml:id="C25_app139-fThomas">bitter recollection. </seg>I often refused to accompany <seg xml:id="C25_app141-fThomas">him, alleging </seg>another <seg xml:id="C25_app143-fThomas">engagement, </seg>that I might remain <seg xml:id="C25_app147-fThomas">alone. </seg>I now also began to collect the materials necessary for my new <seg xml:id="C25_app155-fThomas">creation, </seg>and this was to me like the torture of single drops of water continually falling on the <seg xml:id="C25_app163-fThomas">head. </seg>Every thought that was devoted to it was an extreme anguish, and every word that I spoke in allusion to it <seg xml:id="C25_app171-fThomas">
               <pb n="024" xml:id="F1818_v3_028"/>caused </seg>my lips to <seg xml:id="C25_app174-fThomas">quiver, </seg>and my heart to <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app176-fThomas__Pt1">palpitate.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app176-fThomas__Pt2">After </seg>passing some months in <seg xml:id="C25_app178-fThomas">London, </seg>we received a letter from a person in <seg xml:id="C25_app182-fThomas">Scotland, </seg>who had formerly been our <seg xml:id="C25_app188-fThomas">visitor </seg>at Geneva. He mentioned the beauties of his native <seg xml:id="C25_app192-fThomas">country, and </seg>asked us if those were not sufficient allurements to induce us to prolong our journey as far north as <seg xml:id="C25_app200-fThomas">Perth, </seg>where he resided. <seg xml:id="C25_app202-fThomas">Clerval </seg>eagerly desired to accept this <seg xml:id="C25_app206-fThomas">invitation; </seg>and I, although I abhorred society, wished to view again mountains and <seg xml:id="C25_app212-fThomas">streams, </seg>and all the wondrous works <seg xml:id="C25_app218-fThomas">with which </seg>Nature <seg xml:id="C25_app220-fThomas">adorns </seg>her chosen <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app222-fThomas__Pt1">dwelling-places.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app222-fThomas__Pt2">We </seg>had arrived in <seg xml:id="C25_app224-fThomas">England at </seg>the beginning of <seg xml:id="C25_app228-fThomas">October, </seg>and it was now <seg xml:id="C25_app230-fThomas">February. </seg>We accordingly determined to commence our journey towards the north at the expiration of another month. In this expedition we did not <seg xml:id="C25_app240-fThomas">
               <pb n="025" xml:id="F1818_v3_029"/>intend </seg>to follow the great road to <seg xml:id="C25_app242-fThomas">Edinburgh, </seg>but to visit Windsor, Oxford, <seg xml:id="C25_app244-fThomas">Matlock, </seg>and the Cumberland <seg xml:id="C25_app248-fThomas">lakes, </seg>resolving to arrive at the completion of this tour about the end of July. I packed <seg xml:id="C25_app254-fThomas">up </seg>my chemical <seg xml:id="C25_app256-fThomas">instruments, </seg>and the materials I had <seg xml:id="C25_app260-fThomas">collected, </seg>resolving to finish my labours in some obscure nook in the <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app264-fThomas__Pt1">northern highlands of Scotland.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app264-fThomas__Pt2">We </seg>quitted London on the <seg xml:id="C25_app266-fThomas">27th </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app268-fThomas">March, </seg>and remained a few days at <seg xml:id="C25_app270-fThomas">Windsor, </seg>rambling in its beautiful forest. This was a new scene to us mountaineers; the <seg xml:id="C25_app274-fThomas">majestic oaks, </seg>the quantity of <seg xml:id="C25_app276-fThomas">game, </seg>and the <seg xml:id="C25_app278-fThomas">herds </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app280-fThomas">stately deer, </seg>were all novelties to <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app284-fThomas__Pt1">us.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app284-fThomas__Pt2">From </seg>thence we proceeded to Oxford. <seg xml:id="C25_app286-fThomas">As </seg>we <seg xml:id="C25_app288-fThomas">entered this city, our minds </seg>were <seg xml:id="C25_app290-fThomas">filled </seg>with the <seg xml:id="C25_app292-fThomas">remembrance </seg>of the <seg xml:id="C25_app294-fThomas">events that had been transacted there more than a century </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app296-fThomas">a half </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app297-fThomas">
               <pb n="026" xml:id="F1818_v3_030"/>before. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app298-fThomas">It was here that Charles I. had collected his forces. This city had remained faithful to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app299-fThomas">him, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app300-fThomas">after </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app302-fThomas">whole nation </seg>had <seg xml:id="C25_app304-fThomas">forsaken his cause </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app306-fThomas">join </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app308-fThomas">standard of parliament and liberty. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C25_app310-fThomas">memory </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app312-fThomas">that unfortunate king, and his companions, </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app314-fThomas">amiable Falkland, the insolent </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app315-fThomas">Gower, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app316-fThomas">his queen, and son, gave </seg>a <seg xml:id="C25_app318-fThomas">peculiar interest to every part </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app320-fThomas">the city, which they might be supposed to have inhabited. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C25_app322-fThomas">spirit </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app324-fThomas">elder days found a dwelling here, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app326-fThomas">we delighted to trace its footsteps. If these feelings had not found an imaginary gratification, </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app328-fThomas">appearance </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app330-fThomas">the city had yet </seg>in <seg xml:id="C25_app332-fThomas">itself sufficient beauty to obtain our admiration. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C25_app334-fThomas">colleges are ancient and picturesque; </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app336-fThomas">streets are almost magnificent; and the lovely Isis, which flows beside </seg>it <seg xml:id="C25_app338-fThomas">through meadows </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app340-fThomas">exquisite verdure, is spread forth into a </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app341-fThomas">
               <pb n="027" xml:id="F1818_v3_031"/>placid </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app342-fThomas__Pt1">expanse of waters, which reflects its majestic assemblage of towers, and spires, and domes, embosomed among aged trees.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app342-fThomas__Pt2">I enjoyed this scene; and yet my enjoyment was embittered both by </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app344-fThomas">memory of the past, and </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app346-fThomas">anticipation </seg>of the <seg xml:id="C25_app348-fThomas">future. I was formed </seg>for <seg xml:id="C25_app350-fThomas">peaceful happiness. During my youthful days discontent never visited my mind; and if I was ever overcome by <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p8_hi1">ennui</hi>, the sight </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app352-fThomas">what is beautiful </seg>in <seg xml:id="C25_app354-fThomas">nature, or </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app356-fThomas">study of what is excellent and sublime in </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app358-fThomas">productions </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app360-fThomas">man, could always interest my heart, and communicate elasticity to my spirits. But I am a blasted tree; the bolt has entered my soul; and I felt then that I should survive </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app362-fThomas">exhibit, what I shall soon cease </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app364-fThomas">be—a miserable spectacle </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app366-fThomas">wrecked humanity, pitiable </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app368-fThomas">others, and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app369-fThomas">abhorrent </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app370-fThomas">to </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app371-fThomas__Pt1">myself.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app371-fThomas__Pt2">
               <pb n="028" xml:id="F1818_v3_032"/>We </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app372-fThomas">passed a considerable period at Oxford, rambling among its environs, and endeavouring to identify every spot which might relate to </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app374-fThomas">most animating epoch of English history. Our little voyages </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app376-fThomas">discovery were often prolonged by the successive objects that presented themselves. We visited the tomb </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app378-fThomas">the illustrious Hampden, and </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app380-fThomas">field on which that patriot fell. For a moment my soul was elevated from its debasing and miserable </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app381-fThomas">fears </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app382-fThomas">to contemplate </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app384-fThomas">divine ideas </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app386-fThomas">liberty </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app388-fThomas">self-sacrifice, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app389-fThomas">of which these sights were the monuments and the remembrancers. For an instant I dared to shake off my chains, and look around me with </seg>a <seg xml:id="C25_app391-fThomas">free and lofty spirit; but </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app393-fThomas">iron </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app394-fThomas">had eaten into my flesh, and I sank again, trembling </seg>and <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app396-fThomas__Pt1">hopeless, into my miserable self.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p10">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app396-fThomas__Pt2">We left Oxford with regret, and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app397-fThomas">pro<pb n="029" xml:id="F1818_v3_033"/>ceeded </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app398-fThomas">to </seg>Matlock, which was our <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p10_hi1">next place <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app402-fThomas__Pt1">of rest</seg>
               </hi>
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app402-fThomas__Pt2">. The country in the neighbourhood </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app404-fThomas">this village resembled, </seg>to a <seg xml:id="C25_app406-fThomas">greater degree, </seg>the scenery of Switzerland; but every thing is on a lower <seg xml:id="C25_app410-fThomas">scale, </seg>and the green <seg xml:id="C25_app412-fThomas">hills </seg>want the <seg xml:id="C25_app414-fThomas">crown </seg>of distant white <seg xml:id="C25_app416-fThomas">Alps, </seg>which always attend on the piny <seg xml:id="C25_app418-fThomas">mountains </seg>of <seg xml:id="C25_app420-fThomas">my native </seg>country. We visited the wondrous <seg xml:id="C25_app424-fThomas">cave, </seg>and the little cabinets of natural <seg xml:id="C25_app430-fThomas">history, </seg>where the curiosities are disposed in the same manner as in the collections at Servox <seg xml:id="C25_app436-fThomas">and Chamounix. </seg>The latter <seg xml:id="C25_app438-fThomas">name </seg>made me <seg xml:id="C25_app440-fThomas">tremble, </seg>when pronounced by <seg xml:id="C25_app442-fThomas">Henry; </seg>and I hastened to quit <seg xml:id="C25_app446-fThomas">Matlock, with which that terrible scene was </seg>thus <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app448-fThomas__Pt1">associated.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p11">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app448-fThomas__Pt2">From </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app449-fThomas">Derby </seg>still journeying northward, we passed two months <seg xml:id="C25_app451-fThomas">in </seg>Cumberland and <seg xml:id="C25_app453-fThomas">Westmoreland. </seg>I could now almost fancy myself among the <seg xml:id="C25_app458-fThomas">
               <pb n="030" xml:id="F1818_v3_034"/>Swiss </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app459-fThomas">mountains. </seg>The little patches of snow which yet lingered <seg xml:id="C25_app463-fThomas">on </seg>the northern sides of the <seg xml:id="C25_app465-fThomas">mountains, </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app467-fThomas">lakes, </seg>and the dashing of the rocky <seg xml:id="C25_app471-fThomas">streams, </seg>were all familiar and dear sights to me. Here also we made some <seg xml:id="C25_app475-fThomas">acquaintances, </seg>who almost contrived to cheat me into happiness. The delight of <seg xml:id="C25_app479-fThomas">Clerval </seg>was proportionably greater than mine; his mind expanded in the company of men of <seg xml:id="C25_app485-fThomas">talent, </seg>and he found in <seg xml:id="C25_app489-fThomas">his own nature </seg>greater <seg xml:id="C25_app491-fThomas">capacities </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app493-fThomas">resources </seg>than he could <seg xml:id="C25_app495-fThomas">have </seg>imagined himself to have possessed while he associated with his inferiors. <seg xml:id="C25_app501-fThomas">“I </seg>could pass my life <seg xml:id="C25_app503-fThomas">here,” </seg>said he to <seg xml:id="C25_app505-fThomas">me; “and </seg>among these mountains I should <seg xml:id="C25_app509-fThomas">scarcely </seg>regret Switzerland and the <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app513-fThomas__Pt1">Rhine.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p12">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app513-fThomas__Pt2">But </seg>he found that a <seg xml:id="C25_app515-fThomas">traveller’s </seg>life is one that includes much pain amidst its enjoyments. His feelings <seg xml:id="C25_app521-fThomas">are </seg>for ever <seg xml:id="C25_app523-fThomas">on </seg>the <seg xml:id="C25_app525-fThomas">stretch; </seg>and when he <seg xml:id="C25_app529-fThomas">be<pb n="031" xml:id="F1818_v3_035"/>gins </seg>to sink into <seg xml:id="C25_app531-fThomas">repose, </seg>he <seg xml:id="C25_app533-fThomas">finds </seg>himself obliged to quit <seg xml:id="C25_app535-fThomas">that on which he rests in pleasure </seg>for something <seg xml:id="C25_app537-fThomas">new, </seg>which again <seg xml:id="C25_app539-fThomas">engages </seg>his <seg xml:id="C25_app541-fThomas">attention, and </seg>which also he <seg xml:id="C25_app545-fThomas">forsakes </seg>for <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app547-fThomas__Pt1">other novelties.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p13">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app547-fThomas__Pt2">We </seg>had scarcely visited the various lakes of Cumberland and <seg xml:id="C25_app551-fThomas">Westmoreland, </seg>and conceived an affection for some of the <seg xml:id="C25_app555-fThomas">inhabitants, </seg>when the period of our appointment with our Scotch friend <seg xml:id="C25_app561-fThomas">approached, </seg>and we left <seg xml:id="C25_app563-fThomas">them </seg>to travel on. For my own part I was not sorry. I had now neglected <seg xml:id="C25_app567-fThomas">my </seg>promise for some <seg xml:id="C25_app571-fThomas">time, </seg>and I feared the effects of the <seg xml:id="C25_app575-fThomas">dæmon’s </seg>disappointment. He might remain in <seg xml:id="C25_app579-fThomas">Switzerland, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app581-fThomas">wreak </seg>his vengeance <seg xml:id="C25_app583-fThomas">on </seg>my <seg xml:id="C25_app585-fThomas">relatives. </seg>This idea <seg xml:id="C25_app587-fThomas">pursued me, </seg>and tormented me at every moment <seg xml:id="C25_app591-fThomas">from which </seg>I might otherwise have snatched repose and peace. I waited for my letters with feverish <seg xml:id="C25_app595-fThomas">im<pb n="032" xml:id="F1818_v3_036"/>patience: </seg>if they were <seg xml:id="C25_app599-fThomas">delayed, </seg>I was <seg xml:id="C25_app601-fThomas">miserable, </seg>and overcome by a thousand fears; and when they <seg xml:id="C25_app605-fThomas">arrived, </seg>and I saw the superscription of Elizabeth or my <seg xml:id="C25_app609-fThomas">father, </seg>I hardly dared to read <seg xml:id="C25_app611-fThomas">and ascertain </seg>my fate. Sometimes I thought that the fiend followed <seg xml:id="C25_app615-fThomas">me, </seg>and might <seg xml:id="C25_app617-fThomas">expedite my remissness by </seg>murdering my <seg xml:id="C25_app619-fThomas">companion. When </seg>these <seg xml:id="C25_app621-fThomas">thoughts possessed me, </seg>I would not quit Henry for a <seg xml:id="C25_app623-fThomas">moment, </seg>but followed him as his <seg xml:id="C25_app625-fThomas">shadow, </seg>to protect him from <seg xml:id="C25_app627-fThomas">the </seg>fancied rage of his destroyer. I felt as if I had committed some great <seg xml:id="C25_app631-fThomas">crime, </seg>the consciousness of which haunted me. I was <seg xml:id="C25_app633-fThomas">guiltless, </seg>but I had indeed drawn down a horrible curse <seg xml:id="C25_app635-fThomas">upon my head, as </seg>mortal as that of <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app637-fThomas__Pt1">crime.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p14">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app637-fThomas__Pt2">I </seg>visited Edinburgh with languid eyes and <seg xml:id="C25_app641-fThomas">mind; </seg>and yet that city might have <seg xml:id="C25_app643-fThomas">interested </seg>the most unfortunate being. <seg xml:id="C25_app645-fThomas">Clerval </seg>did not like it so well <seg xml:id="C25_app647-fThomas">
               <pb n="033" xml:id="F1818_v3_037"/>as Oxford; </seg>for the antiquity of <seg xml:id="C25_app650-fThomas">the latter </seg>city was <seg xml:id="C25_app652-fThomas">more </seg>pleasing to him. But the beauty <seg xml:id="C25_app654-fThomas">and regularity </seg>of the new town of <seg xml:id="C25_app656-fThomas">Edinburgh, </seg>its <seg xml:id="C25_app658-fThomas">romantic castle, and its environs, </seg>the most <seg xml:id="C25_app660-fThomas">delightful </seg>in the <seg xml:id="C25_app662-fThomas">world, Arthur’s </seg>Seat, <seg xml:id="C25_app664-fThomas">St. Bernard’s Well, </seg>and the Pentland <seg xml:id="C25_app666-fThomas">Hills, compensated him for the change, and filled him with cheerfulness and admiration. </seg>But I was impatient to arrive at the termination of my <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app670-fThomas__Pt1">journey.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p15">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app670-fThomas__Pt2">We </seg>left Edinburgh in a <seg xml:id="C25_app674-fThomas">week, </seg>passing through <seg xml:id="C25_app676-fThomas">C<del xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p15_del1">o</del>upar, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app677-fThomas">St. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app678-fThomas">Andrews, </seg>and along the banks of the <seg xml:id="C25_app682-fThomas">Tay, </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app684-fThomas">Perth, </seg>where our friend expected <seg xml:id="C25_app686-fThomas">us. </seg>But I was in <seg xml:id="C25_app690-fThomas">no </seg>mood to laugh and talk with <seg xml:id="C25_app692-fThomas">strangers, </seg>or enter into their feelings or plans with the good humour expected from a <seg xml:id="C25_app694-fThomas">guest; </seg>and accordingly I told <seg xml:id="C25_app696-fThomas">Clerval </seg>that I wished to make the tour of Scotland <seg xml:id="C25_app700-fThomas">alone. “Do </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app701-fThomas">
               <pb n="034" xml:id="F1818_v3_038"/>you,” </seg>said I, <seg xml:id="C25_app703-fThomas">“enjoy </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app704-fThomas">yourself, </seg>and let this be our <seg xml:id="C25_app706-fThomas">rendezvous. </seg>I may be absent a month or <seg xml:id="C25_app708-fThomas">two; </seg>but do not interfere with my <seg xml:id="C25_app712-fThomas">motions, </seg>I entreat <seg xml:id="C25_app714-fThomas">you: </seg>leave me to peace and solitude for a short <seg xml:id="C25_app718-fThomas">time; </seg>and when I <seg xml:id="C25_app720-fThomas">return, </seg>I hope it will be with a lighter <seg xml:id="C25_app724-fThomas">heart, </seg>more congenial to your own <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app728-fThomas__Pt1">temper.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p16">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app728-fThomas__Pt2">Henry </seg>wished to dissuade <seg xml:id="C25_app732-fThomas">me; but, </seg>seeing me bent on this <seg xml:id="C25_app736-fThomas">plan, ceased </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app738-fThomas">remonstrate. He </seg>entreated me to write often. <seg xml:id="C25_app742-fThomas">“I </seg>had rather be with <seg xml:id="C25_app746-fThomas">you,” </seg>he said, <seg xml:id="C25_app748-fThomas">“in </seg>your solitary <seg xml:id="C25_app750-fThomas">rambles, </seg>than with these Scotch <seg xml:id="C25_app752-fThomas">people, </seg>whom I do not <seg xml:id="C25_app754-fThomas">know: </seg>hasten <seg xml:id="C25_app756-fThomas">then, </seg>my dear <seg xml:id="C25_app758-fThomas">friend, </seg>to <seg xml:id="C25_app760-fThomas">return, </seg>that I may again feel myself somewhat at <seg xml:id="C25_app766-fThomas">home, </seg>which I cannot do in your <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app768-fThomas__Pt1">absence.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p17">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app768-fThomas__Pt2">Having </seg>parted from my <seg xml:id="C25_app770-fThomas">friend, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C25_app772-fThomas">determined </seg>to visit some remote spot of <seg xml:id="C25_app774-fThomas">Scotland, </seg>and finish my work in <seg xml:id="C25_app776-fThomas">solitude. </seg>I did not doubt but that the <seg xml:id="C25_app779-fThomas">
               <pb n="035" xml:id="F1818_v3_039"/>monster </seg>followed me, and would discover himself to <seg xml:id="C25_app784-fThomas">me </seg>when I should have finished, <seg xml:id="C25_app786-fThomas">that </seg>he might receive his <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app788-fThomas__Pt1">companion.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p18">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app788-fThomas__Pt2">With </seg>this resolution I traversed the northern <seg xml:id="C25_app792-fThomas">highlands, </seg>and fixed on one of the <seg xml:id="C25_app794-fThomas">remotest of the Orkneys as </seg>the scene labours. It was a place fitted for such a <seg xml:id="C25_app800-fThomas">work, </seg>being hardly more than a <seg xml:id="C25_app802-fThomas">rock, </seg>whose high sides were continually beaten upon by the <seg xml:id="C25_app806-fThomas">waves. </seg>The soil was <seg xml:id="C25_app808-fThomas">barren, scarcely </seg>affording pasture for a few miserable <seg xml:id="C25_app812-fThomas">cows, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C25_app814-fThomas">oatmeal </seg>for its <seg xml:id="C25_app816-fThomas">inhabitants, </seg>which consisted of five persons, whose gaunt and scraggy limbs gave tokens of their <seg xml:id="C25_app820-fThomas">miserable </seg>fare. Vegetables and bread, when they indulged in such luxuries, and even fresh <seg xml:id="C25_app826-fThomas">water, </seg>was to be procured from the main <seg xml:id="C25_app830-fThomas">land, </seg>which was about five miles <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app834-fThomas__Pt1">distant.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p19">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app834-fThomas__Pt2">On </seg>the whole island there were but <seg xml:id="C25_app838-fThomas">
               <pb n="036" xml:id="F1818_v3_040"/>three </seg>miserable <seg xml:id="C25_app840-fThomas">huts, </seg>and one of these was vacant when I arrived. This I <seg xml:id="C25_app844-fThomas">hired. </seg>It contained but two <seg xml:id="C25_app848-fThomas">rooms, and </seg>these exhibited all the squalidness of the most miserable <seg xml:id="C25_app852-fThomas">penury. </seg>The thatch had fallen <seg xml:id="C25_app854-fThomas">in, </seg>the walls were <seg xml:id="C25_app858-fThomas">unplastered, </seg>and the door was off its hinges. I ordered it to be repaired, bought some <seg xml:id="C25_app866-fThomas">furniture, </seg>and took <seg xml:id="C25_app868-fThomas">possession; </seg>an incident which <seg xml:id="C25_app872-fThomas">would, doubtless, </seg>have occasioned some <seg xml:id="C25_app878-fThomas">surprise, </seg>had not all the senses of the cottagers been benumbed by want and squalid <seg xml:id="C25_app884-fThomas">poverty. </seg>As it <seg xml:id="C25_app886-fThomas">was, </seg>I lived ungazed at and unmolested, hardly thanked for the pittance of food and clothes which I <seg xml:id="C25_app894-fThomas">gave; </seg>so much does suffering blunt even the coarsest sensations of <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app898-fThomas__Pt1">men.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p20">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app898-fThomas__Pt2">In </seg>this retreat I devoted the morning to <seg xml:id="C25_app900-fThomas">labour; </seg>but in the evening, when the weather <seg xml:id="C25_app904-fThomas">permitted, </seg>I walked on the stony beach of the <seg xml:id="C25_app908-fThomas">sea, </seg>to listen to the <seg xml:id="C25_app912-fThomas">
               <pb n="037" xml:id="F1818_v3_041"/>waves </seg>as they <seg xml:id="C25_app914-fThomas">roared, </seg>and dashed at my <seg xml:id="C25_app918-fThomas">feet. </seg>It was a <seg xml:id="C25_app920-fThomas">monotonous, </seg>yet <seg xml:id="C25_app922-fThomas">ever-changing </seg>scene. I thought of Switzerland; it was far different from this desolate and appalling <seg xml:id="C25_app926-fThomas">landscape. Its </seg>hills are covered with <seg xml:id="C25_app928-fThomas">vines, </seg>and its cottages are scattered <seg xml:id="C25_app932-fThomas">thickly </seg>in the <seg xml:id="C25_app934-fThomas">plains. </seg>Its fair lakes reflect a blue and gentle <seg xml:id="C25_app938-fThomas">sky; and, </seg>when troubled by the <seg xml:id="C25_app942-fThomas">winds, their tumult </seg>is but <seg xml:id="C25_app944-fThomas">as </seg>the play of a lively <seg xml:id="C25_app948-fThomas">infant, </seg>when compared to the roarings of the giant <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app952-fThomas__Pt1">ocean.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p21">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app952-fThomas__Pt2">In this </seg>manner I distributed my occupations when I first arrived; <seg xml:id="C25_app958-fThomas">but, </seg>as I proceeded in my <seg xml:id="C25_app960-fThomas">labour, </seg>it became every day more horrible and irksome to me. Sometimes I could not prevail on myself to enter my <seg xml:id="C25_app970-fThomas">laboratory </seg>for several <seg xml:id="C25_app972-fThomas">days; </seg>and at other times I <seg xml:id="C25_app974-fThomas">toiled </seg>day and night in order to <seg xml:id="C25_app976-fThomas">complete my work. </seg>It <seg xml:id="C25_app978-fThomas">was indeed </seg>a filthy <seg xml:id="C25_app983-fThomas">process </seg>in <seg xml:id="C25_app985-fThomas">which </seg>I <seg xml:id="C25_app987-fThomas">was engaged. During </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app988-fThomas">
               <pb n="038" xml:id="F1818_v3_042"/>my </seg>first <seg xml:id="C25_app990-fThomas">experiment, </seg>a kind of enthusiastic frenzy had blinded me to the horror of my employment; my mind was intently fixed on the <seg xml:id="C25_app998-fThomas">sequel </seg>of my <seg xml:id="C25_app1000-fThomas">labour, </seg>and my eyes were shut to the horror of my proceedings. But now I went to it in cold <seg xml:id="C25_app1004-fThomas">blood, </seg>and my heart often sickened at the work of my <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app1008-fThomas__Pt1">hands.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p22">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app1008-fThomas__Pt2">Thus situated, </seg>employed in the most detestable occupation, <seg xml:id="C25_app1012-fThomas">immersed </seg>in a solitude <seg xml:id="C25_app1014-fThomas">where </seg>nothing could for an instant call my <seg xml:id="C25_app1016-fThomas">attention </seg>from the actual scene in which I was engaged, my spirits <seg xml:id="C25_app1020-fThomas">became unequal; </seg>I <seg xml:id="C25_app1022-fThomas">grew </seg>restless and <seg xml:id="C25_app1024-fThomas">nervous. </seg>Every moment I feared to meet my persecutor. Sometimes I sat with my eyes fixed on the <seg xml:id="C25_app1032-fThomas">ground, </seg>fearing to raise <seg xml:id="C25_app1034-fThomas">them </seg>lest they should <seg xml:id="C25_app1036-fThomas">encounter the </seg>object which I so much dreaded to <seg xml:id="C25_app1038-fThomas">behold. </seg>I feared to wander <seg xml:id="C25_app1040-fThomas">from </seg>the sight of my <seg xml:id="C25_app1042-fThomas">fellow-creatures, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C25_app1043-fThomas">
               <pb n="039" xml:id="F1818_v3_043"/>lest </seg>when alone he should come to claim his <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app1049-fThomas__Pt1">companion.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p23">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app1049-fThomas__Pt2">In </seg>the mean time I worked <seg xml:id="C25_app1053-fThomas">on, </seg>and my labour was already considerably <seg xml:id="C25_app1059-fThomas">advanced. </seg>I looked towards its completion <seg xml:id="C25_app1063-fThomas">with a tremulous and eager hope, which </seg>I <seg xml:id="C25_app1065-fThomas">dared not trust myself to question, but which </seg>was <seg xml:id="C25_app1067-fThomas">intermixed with obscure forebodings of evil, that made my heart sicken in my </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C25_app1068-fThomas__Pt1">bosom.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C25_app1068-fThomas__Pt2">
            <milestone n="18" type="end" unit="chapter"/> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>