<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness fThomas, Collation unit C09</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1-fThomas__Pt1">
            <milestone n="3" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <pb n="078" xml:id="F1818_v1_090"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_head1">CHAPTER III.</head>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1-fThomas__Pt2"> 
               </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app2-fThomas">F<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p1_hi1">ROM</hi> 
               </seg>this day natural <seg xml:id="C09_app4-fThomas">philosophy, </seg>and particularly <seg xml:id="C09_app6-fThomas">chemistry, in the most comprehensive sense of the term, </seg>became nearly my sole <seg xml:id="C09_app8-fThomas">occupation. </seg>I read with ardour those <seg xml:id="C09_app12-fThomas">works, </seg>so full of genius and <seg xml:id="C09_app14-fThomas">discrimination, </seg>which modern <seg xml:id="C09_app16-fThomas">inquirers have written </seg>on these subjects. I attended the lectures, and cultivated the <seg xml:id="C09_app18-fThomas">acquaintance, </seg>of the men of science of the university; and I found even in <seg xml:id="C09_app24-fThomas">M. </seg>Krempe a great deal of sound sense and real <seg xml:id="C09_app28-fThomas">information, combined, </seg>it is <seg xml:id="C09_app30-fThomas">true, </seg>with a repulsive <seg xml:id="C09_app32-fThomas">physiognomy </seg>and manners, but not on that account the less valuable. In M. Waldman I found <seg xml:id="C09_app38-fThomas">
               <pb n="079" xml:id="F1818_v1_091"/>a </seg>true friend. His gentleness was never tinged by <seg xml:id="C09_app42-fThomas">dogmatism; </seg>and his instructions were given with an air of frankness and good <seg xml:id="C09_app48-fThomas">nature, </seg>that banished every idea of pedantry. <seg xml:id="C09_app54-fThomas">It </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app55-fThomas">was, perhaps, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app56-fThomas">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app58-fThomas">amiable character of this man that </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app59-fThomas">inclined </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app60-fThomas">me more to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app62-fThomas">that </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app64-fThomas">branch of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app65-fThomas">natural </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app66-fThomas">philosophy which </seg>he <seg xml:id="C09_app68-fThomas">professed, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app69-fThomas">than an intrinsic </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app71-fThomas">love </seg>for the <seg xml:id="C09_app75-fThomas">science itself. But this </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app77-fThomas">state </seg>of <seg xml:id="C09_app79-fThomas">mind had </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app81-fThomas">place </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app83-fThomas">only in </seg>the <seg xml:id="C09_app85-fThomas">first steps towards </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app86-fThomas">knowledge: </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app87-fThomas">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app89-fThomas">more fully I entered </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app91-fThomas">into </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app92-fThomas">the science, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app93-fThomas">the more </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app94-fThomas">exclusively </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app95-fThomas">I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app97-fThomas">pursued </seg>it <seg xml:id="C09_app100-fThomas">for its own sake. That </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app101-fThomas">application, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app102-fThomas">which at first had been a matter </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app104-fThomas">of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app106-fThomas">duty </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app108-fThomas">resolution, now </seg>became so ardent and <seg xml:id="C09_app112-fThomas">eager, </seg>that the stars often <seg xml:id="C09_app114-fThomas">disappeared </seg>in the light of morning <seg xml:id="C09_app118-fThomas">whilst </seg>I was yet <seg xml:id="C09_app120-fThomas">engaged </seg>in my <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app122-fThomas__Pt1">laboratory.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app122-fThomas__Pt2">As </seg>I applied so closely, it may be easily conceived that <seg xml:id="C09_app126-fThomas">I improved </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app127-fThomas">ra<pb n="080" xml:id="F1818_v1_092"/>pidly. </seg>My ardour was indeed the astonishment of the <seg xml:id="C09_app129-fThomas">students; </seg>and my <seg xml:id="C09_app131-fThomas">proficiency, </seg>that of <seg xml:id="C09_app134-fThomas">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app135-fThomas">masters. </seg>Professor Krempe often asked <seg xml:id="C09_app139-fThomas">me, </seg>with a sly <seg xml:id="C09_app141-fThomas">smile, </seg>how Cornelius Agrippa went <seg xml:id="C09_app143-fThomas">on? whilst </seg>M. <seg xml:id="C09_app145-fThomas">Waldman </seg>expressed the most heartfelt exultation in my progress. Two years passed in this <seg xml:id="C09_app153-fThomas">manner, </seg>during which I paid no visit to Geneva, but was <seg xml:id="C09_app159-fThomas">engaged, </seg>heart and <seg xml:id="C09_app161-fThomas">soul, </seg>in the pursuit of some <seg xml:id="C09_app165-fThomas">discoveries, </seg>which I hoped to make. None but those who have experienced <seg xml:id="C09_app173-fThomas">them </seg>can conceive of the enticements of <seg xml:id="C09_app177-fThomas">science. </seg>In other studies you go as far as others have <seg xml:id="C09_app181-fThomas">gone </seg>before <seg xml:id="C09_app183-fThomas">you, </seg>and there is nothing more to <seg xml:id="C09_app187-fThomas">know; </seg>but in a scientific pursuit there is continual food for discovery and wonder. A mind of moderate <seg xml:id="C09_app199-fThomas">capacity, which </seg>closely pursues one <seg xml:id="C09_app203-fThomas">study, </seg>must infallibly arrive at great proficiency in <seg xml:id="C09_app207-fThomas">that study; and I, </seg>who <seg xml:id="C09_app209-fThomas">con<pb n="081" xml:id="F1818_v1_093"/>tinually </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app211-fThomas">sought </seg>the attainment of one <seg xml:id="C09_app213-fThomas">object of pursuit, </seg>and was <seg xml:id="C09_app215-fThomas">solely wrapt </seg>up in <seg xml:id="C09_app219-fThomas">this, </seg>improved so <seg xml:id="C09_app221-fThomas">rapidly, that, </seg>at the end of two <seg xml:id="C09_app227-fThomas">years, </seg>I made <seg xml:id="C09_app229-fThomas">some </seg>discoveries in the improvement of some chemical <seg xml:id="C09_app233-fThomas">instruments, </seg>which procured me great esteem and admiration at the university. When I <seg xml:id="C09_app237-fThomas">had </seg>arrived at this point, and <seg xml:id="C09_app243-fThomas">had become as well acquainted with </seg>the <seg xml:id="C09_app245-fThomas">theory and practice of natural philosophy as depended on the lessons of any of the professors at Ingolstadt, my residence there </seg>being no longer conducive to my <seg xml:id="C09_app249-fThomas">improvements, </seg>I thought of returning to my friends and my native town, when an incident happened that protracted my <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app259-fThomas__Pt1">stay.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app259-fThomas__Pt2">One </seg>of <seg xml:id="C09_app261-fThomas">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app262-fThomas">phænomena </seg>which had peculiarly attracted my attention was the structure of the human <seg xml:id="C09_app268-fThomas">frame, and, indeed, </seg>any animal endued with life. <seg xml:id="C09_app272-fThomas">Whence, </seg>I often asked <seg xml:id="C09_app274-fThomas">myself, </seg>did <seg xml:id="C09_app276-fThomas">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app277-fThomas">
               <pb n="082" xml:id="F1818_v1_094"/>principle </seg>of life <seg xml:id="C09_app279-fThomas">proceed? </seg>It was a bold question, and one <seg xml:id="C09_app281-fThomas">which </seg>has ever been considered as a <seg xml:id="C09_app283-fThomas">mystery; </seg>yet <seg xml:id="C09_app285-fThomas">with </seg>how many things are we <seg xml:id="C09_app287-fThomas">upon </seg>the brink of becoming <seg xml:id="C09_app291-fThomas">acquainted, </seg>if cowardice or carelessness did not restrain <seg xml:id="C09_app295-fThomas">our </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app296-fThomas">inquiries. </seg>I revolved these circumstances in my <seg xml:id="C09_app298-fThomas">mind, </seg>and determined thenceforth to apply myself more particularly to <seg xml:id="C09_app304-fThomas">those </seg>branches of natural philosophy which <seg xml:id="C09_app308-fThomas">relate to physiology. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app309-fThomas">The event of these enquiries interested my understanding, I may say my imagination, until I was exalted </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app310-fThomas">to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app311-fThomas">a kind of transport. And indeed </seg>Unless I had been animated by an almost supernatural enthusiasm, my application to this study would have been <seg xml:id="C09_app317-fThomas">irksome, </seg>and almost intolerable. To examine the causes of <seg xml:id="C09_app321-fThomas">life, </seg>we must first have recourse to death. I became acquainted with <seg xml:id="C09_app331-fThomas">the </seg>science of <seg xml:id="C09_app333-fThomas">anatomy: </seg>but this was not <seg xml:id="C09_app337-fThomas">sufficient; </seg>I must also observe the natural decay and corruption of the human body. In my education my father had taken the <seg xml:id="C09_app343-fThomas">
               <pb n="083" xml:id="F1818_v1_095"/>greatest </seg>precautions that my mind <seg xml:id="C09_app346-fThomas">should </seg>be impressed <seg xml:id="C09_app349-fThomas">with no </seg>supernatural horrors. I do not ever remember <seg xml:id="C09_app353-fThomas">to have </seg>trembled at <seg xml:id="C09_app355-fThomas">a tale </seg>of <seg xml:id="C09_app357-fThomas">superstition, </seg>or to have feared the apparition of a <seg xml:id="C09_app361-fThomas">spirit. </seg>Darkness had no effect upon my <seg xml:id="C09_app363-fThomas">fancy; </seg>and a <seg xml:id="C09_app365-fThomas">church-yard </seg>was to me merely the receptacle of bodies deprived of <seg xml:id="C09_app373-fThomas">life, which, </seg>from being the seat of beauty and <seg xml:id="C09_app375-fThomas">strength, had become </seg>food for the worm. Now I was <seg xml:id="C09_app379-fThomas">led </seg>to examine the <seg xml:id="C09_app381-fThomas">cause and </seg>progress of this <seg xml:id="C09_app385-fThomas">decay, </seg>and forced to spend days and nights in vaults and <seg xml:id="C09_app389-fThomas">charnel </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app391-fThomas">houses. </seg>My attention was fixed upon every <seg xml:id="C09_app396-fThomas">object the </seg>most insupportable to the delicacy of the human feelings. I saw how the fine form of man <seg xml:id="C09_app402-fThomas">was </seg>degraded and <seg xml:id="C09_app404-fThomas">wasted; </seg>I beheld the corruption of death succeed to the blooming cheek of <seg xml:id="C09_app408-fThomas">life; </seg>I saw how the <seg xml:id="C09_app410-fThomas">worm inherited </seg>the wonders of the eye and brain. I <seg xml:id="C09_app414-fThomas">
               <pb n="084" xml:id="F1818_v1_096"/>paused, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app415-fThomas">examining </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app417-fThomas">analysing </seg>all the minutiæ of <seg xml:id="C09_app421-fThomas">causation, </seg>as exemplified in the change from life to death, and death to life, <seg xml:id="C09_app427-fThomas">until </seg>from the midst of this darkness a sudden light broke in upon <seg xml:id="C09_app431-fThomas">me—a </seg>light so brilliant and <seg xml:id="C09_app433-fThomas">wondrous, </seg>yet so <seg xml:id="C09_app435-fThomas">simple, </seg>that while I became dizzy with the immensity of the prospect which it illustrated, I was <seg xml:id="C09_app443-fThomas">surprised </seg>that among so many men of <seg xml:id="C09_app447-fThomas">genius, </seg>who had <seg xml:id="C09_app450-fThomas">directed their </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app451-fThomas">inquiries </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app452-fThomas">towards </seg>the same <seg xml:id="C09_app454-fThomas">science, </seg>that I alone should <seg xml:id="C09_app456-fThomas">be reserved to </seg>discover <seg xml:id="C09_app458-fThomas">so </seg>astonishing <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app460-fThomas__Pt1">a secret.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app460-fThomas__Pt2">Remember, </seg>I am not recording the vision of a <seg xml:id="C09_app466-fThomas">madman. </seg>The sun does not more certainly shine in the <seg xml:id="C09_app472-fThomas">heavens, </seg>than that <seg xml:id="C09_app474-fThomas">which </seg>I now <seg xml:id="C09_app476-fThomas">affirm </seg>is true. Some miracle might have produced <seg xml:id="C09_app480-fThomas">it, yet </seg>the stages of <seg xml:id="C09_app484-fThomas">the </seg>discovery were distinct and probable. After days and nights of incredible <seg xml:id="C09_app490-fThomas">labour </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app492-fThomas">fatigue, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app493-fThomas">
               <pb n="085" xml:id="F1818_v1_097"/>I </seg>succeeded in discovering the cause of generation and <seg xml:id="C09_app497-fThomas">life; nay, </seg>more, I <seg xml:id="C09_app499-fThomas">became </seg>myself capable of bestowing animation upon lifeless <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app503-fThomas__Pt1">matter.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app503-fThomas__Pt2">The astonishment which </seg>I <seg xml:id="C09_app505-fThomas">had </seg>at <seg xml:id="C09_app507-fThomas">first experienced </seg>on this discovery soon gave place to delight and rapture. After so much <seg xml:id="C09_app513-fThomas">time </seg>spent in painful <seg xml:id="C09_app517-fThomas">labour, to </seg>arrive at <seg xml:id="C09_app519-fThomas">once </seg>at the <seg xml:id="C09_app521-fThomas">summit </seg>of my <seg xml:id="C09_app523-fThomas">desires, </seg>was the most gratifying <seg xml:id="C09_app525-fThomas">consummation of my toils. </seg>But this discovery was <seg xml:id="C09_app529-fThomas">so </seg>great and <seg xml:id="C09_app531-fThomas">overwhelming, </seg>that all the steps <seg xml:id="C09_app535-fThomas">by </seg>which I had <seg xml:id="C09_app537-fThomas">been progressively </seg>led to it were <seg xml:id="C09_app539-fThomas">obliterated, and I beheld </seg>only the result. What had been the study and desire of the wisest men since the creation of the <seg xml:id="C09_app547-fThomas">world, </seg>was now <seg xml:id="C09_app549-fThomas">within </seg>my <seg xml:id="C09_app551-fThomas">grasp. </seg>Not that, like a magic <seg xml:id="C09_app555-fThomas">scene, </seg>it all opened upon me at <seg xml:id="C09_app559-fThomas">once: </seg>the information I had obtained was of a nature rather <seg xml:id="C09_app565-fThomas">to </seg>direct my <seg xml:id="C09_app567-fThomas">endeavours </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app568-fThomas">so </seg>soon as I should point them towards <seg xml:id="C09_app574-fThomas">
               <pb n="086" xml:id="F1818_v1_098"/>the </seg>object of my search, than to exhibit that object already accomplished. I was like the <seg xml:id="C09_app583-fThomas">Arabian </seg>who had been buried with the dead, and found a passage to <seg xml:id="C09_app587-fThomas">life </seg>aided only by one <seg xml:id="C09_app590-fThomas">glimmering, </seg>and seemingly <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app592-fThomas__Pt1">ineffectual, light.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app592-fThomas__Pt2">I </seg>see by your <seg xml:id="C09_app594-fThomas">eagerness, </seg>and the wonder and hope which your eyes express, my friend, that you expect to be informed of the secret with which I am <seg xml:id="C09_app606-fThomas">acquainted; that </seg>cannot <seg xml:id="C09_app608-fThomas">be: </seg>listen patiently <seg xml:id="C09_app610-fThomas">until </seg>the end of my <seg xml:id="C09_app614-fThomas">story, </seg>and you will easily perceive why I am reserved upon that <seg xml:id="C09_app618-fThomas">subject. </seg>I will not lead you on, unguarded and ardent as I then was, to your destruction and infallible misery. Learn from me, if not by my <seg xml:id="C09_app630-fThomas">precepts, </seg>at least by my <seg xml:id="C09_app632-fThomas">example, </seg>how dangerous is the acquirement of <seg xml:id="C09_app636-fThomas">knowledge, </seg>and how much happier that <seg xml:id="C09_app640-fThomas">man </seg>is who believes his <seg xml:id="C09_app642-fThomas">
               <pb n="087" xml:id="F1818_v1_099"/>native </seg>town <seg xml:id="C09_app645-fThomas">to be </seg>the world, than he <seg xml:id="C09_app647-fThomas">who </seg>aspires to become greater than his nature will <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app653-fThomas__Pt1">allow.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app653-fThomas__Pt2">When </seg>I found <seg xml:id="C09_app655-fThomas">so astonishing a </seg>power placed <seg xml:id="C09_app659-fThomas">within </seg>my hands, I hesitated a long time concerning the <seg xml:id="C09_app663-fThomas">manner </seg>in which I should <seg xml:id="C09_app665-fThomas">employ </seg>it. Although I possessed the capacity of bestowing <seg xml:id="C09_app673-fThomas">animation, </seg>yet to <seg xml:id="C09_app677-fThomas">prepare </seg>a <seg xml:id="C09_app679-fThomas">frame for </seg>the <seg xml:id="C09_app681-fThomas">reception of it, </seg>with all its intricacies of <seg xml:id="C09_app683-fThomas">fibres, muscles, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app685-fThomas">veins, still </seg>remained a work of inconceivable <seg xml:id="C09_app687-fThomas">difficulty and labour. </seg>I doubted at first whether I should attempt the creation of a <seg xml:id="C09_app691-fThomas">being </seg>like <seg xml:id="C09_app694-fThomas">myself </seg>or one of simpler organization; but my imagination was too much exalted by my first success to permit me to doubt of my ability to <seg xml:id="C09_app706-fThomas">give life to </seg>an animal as complex and wonderful as man. The materials at present within my command hardly appeared adequate to so <seg xml:id="C09_app714-fThomas">arduous </seg>an <seg xml:id="C09_app716-fThomas">
               <pb n="088" xml:id="F1818_v1_100"/>undertaking; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app717-fThomas">but </seg>I doubted not that I should <seg xml:id="C09_app719-fThomas">ultimately succeed. </seg>I prepared myself for a multitude of <seg xml:id="C09_app725-fThomas">reverses; </seg>my operations <seg xml:id="C09_app729-fThomas">might </seg>be <seg xml:id="C09_app731-fThomas">incessantly baffled, </seg>and at last my work be <seg xml:id="C09_app735-fThomas">imperfect: </seg>yet, when <seg xml:id="C09_app737-fThomas">I </seg>considered the improvement <seg xml:id="C09_app739-fThomas">which </seg>every day takes place in science and <seg xml:id="C09_app743-fThomas">mechanics, I </seg>was encouraged to hope my present attempts would <seg xml:id="C09_app749-fThomas">at </seg>least lay the foundations of future <seg xml:id="C09_app751-fThomas">success. Nor </seg>could I consider the magnitude and <seg xml:id="C09_app757-fThomas">complexity </seg>of my plan <seg xml:id="C09_app759-fThomas">as </seg>any argument of its impracticability. <seg xml:id="C09_app761-fThomas">It </seg>was with these feelings <seg xml:id="C09_app763-fThomas">that I </seg>began the creation of a human being. As the <seg xml:id="C09_app767-fThomas">minuteness </seg>of the parts <seg xml:id="C09_app769-fThomas">formed </seg>a great <seg xml:id="C09_app773-fThomas">hindrance </seg>to my <seg xml:id="C09_app775-fThomas">speed, </seg>I resolved, contrary to my first intention, to make <seg xml:id="C09_app779-fThomas">the being </seg>of a gigantic stature; that is to <seg xml:id="C09_app783-fThomas">say, </seg>about eight feet in height, and proportionably large. After having formed this <seg xml:id="C09_app791-fThomas">de<pb n="089" xml:id="F1818_v1_101"/>termination, </seg>and having spent <seg xml:id="C09_app793-fThomas">some </seg>months in successfully collecting and arranging my materials, I <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app799-fThomas__Pt1">began.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app799-fThomas__Pt2">No </seg>one can conceive the variety of feelings which <seg xml:id="C09_app805-fThomas">bore </seg>me <seg xml:id="C09_app807-fThomas">onwards, like a hurricane, in the first enthusiasm of success. </seg>Life and death appeared to me ideal bounds, which I should first break <seg xml:id="C09_app811-fThomas">through, </seg>and pour a torrent of light into our dark world. A new <seg xml:id="C09_app817-fThomas">species </seg>would bless me as its <seg xml:id="C09_app819-fThomas">creator </seg>and source; many happy and excellent <seg xml:id="C09_app823-fThomas">natures </seg>would owe their <seg xml:id="C09_app825-fThomas">being </seg>to me. No father could claim the gratitude of his child so completely as I should deserve <seg xml:id="C09_app835-fThomas">their’s. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app836-fThomas">Pursuing these reflections, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C09_app838-fThomas">thought, </seg>that if I could bestow <seg xml:id="C09_app840-fThomas">animation </seg>upon lifeless <seg xml:id="C09_app844-fThomas">matter, </seg>I might in process of time (although I now found it impossible) renew life where death had apparently devoted the body to <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app852-fThomas__Pt1">corruption.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app852-fThomas__Pt2">
               <pb n="090" xml:id="F1818_v1_102"/>These </seg>thoughts supported my <seg xml:id="C09_app854-fThomas">spirits, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app855-fThomas">while </seg>I pursued my <seg xml:id="C09_app857-fThomas">undertaking </seg>with unremitting <seg xml:id="C09_app859-fThomas">ardour. </seg>My cheek <seg xml:id="C09_app861-fThomas">had </seg>grown pale with study, and my person <seg xml:id="C09_app865-fThomas">had become emaciated with </seg>confinement. <seg xml:id="C09_app867-fThomas">Sometimes, </seg>on the very brink of <seg xml:id="C09_app869-fThomas">certainty, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C09_app871-fThomas">failed; </seg>yet still <seg xml:id="C09_app875-fThomas">I </seg>clung to the hope which the next day or the next hour might <seg xml:id="C09_app883-fThomas">realize. </seg>One secret which I alone <seg xml:id="C09_app887-fThomas">possessed </seg>was the hope to which I <seg xml:id="C09_app891-fThomas">had dedicated myself; </seg>and the moon gazed on my midnight <seg xml:id="C09_app895-fThomas">labours, while, </seg>with unrelaxed and breathless <seg xml:id="C09_app897-fThomas">eagerness, </seg>I pursued nature to her <seg xml:id="C09_app900-fThomas">hiding </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app901-fThomas">places. </seg>Who shall <seg xml:id="C09_app903-fThomas">conceive </seg>the horrors of my secret <seg xml:id="C09_app905-fThomas">toil, </seg>as I dabbled among the unhallowed damps of the grave, or tortured the living animal to animate <seg xml:id="C09_app915-fThomas">the </seg>lifeless clay? My limbs now <seg xml:id="C09_app919-fThomas">tremble, </seg>and my eyes swim with the <seg xml:id="C09_app921-fThomas">remembrance; </seg>but then a <seg xml:id="C09_app923-fThomas">resistless, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app926-fThomas">almost </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app927-fThomas">frantic </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app928-fThomas">impulse, </seg>urged me <seg xml:id="C09_app930-fThomas">forward; </seg>I seemed to <seg xml:id="C09_app932-fThomas">
               <pb n="091" xml:id="F1818_v1_103"/>have </seg>lost all soul or sensation but for <seg xml:id="C09_app936-fThomas">this </seg>one pursuit. It was indeed <seg xml:id="C09_app940-fThomas">but </seg>a passing <seg xml:id="C09_app942-fThomas">trance, </seg>that only made me feel with <seg xml:id="C09_app944-fThomas">renewed </seg>acuteness <seg xml:id="C09_app946-fThomas">so </seg>soon <seg xml:id="C09_app948-fThomas">as, </seg>the unnatural <seg xml:id="C09_app950-fThomas">stimulus ceasing </seg>to operate, I had returned to my old habits. I collected bones from <seg xml:id="C09_app955-fThomas">charnel </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app956-fThomas">houses; </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app958-fThomas">disturbed, </seg>with profane <seg xml:id="C09_app960-fThomas">fingers, </seg>the <seg xml:id="C09_app962-fThomas">tremendous </seg>secrets of the human frame. In a solitary <seg xml:id="C09_app966-fThomas">chamber, or </seg>rather <seg xml:id="C09_app968-fThomas">cell, </seg>at the top of the <seg xml:id="C09_app970-fThomas">house, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C09_app972-fThomas">separated </seg>from all <seg xml:id="C09_app974-fThomas">the </seg>other <seg xml:id="C09_app976-fThomas">apartments </seg>by a gallery and <seg xml:id="C09_app980-fThomas">staircase, </seg>I kept my workshop of filthy <seg xml:id="C09_app986-fThomas">creation; </seg>my <seg xml:id="C09_app988-fThomas">eyeballs </seg>were starting from their sockets in attending to the <seg xml:id="C09_app992-fThomas">details </seg>of my employment. The dissecting room and the <seg xml:id="C09_app1000-fThomas">slaughter-house </seg>furnished many of my <seg xml:id="C09_app1004-fThomas">materials; </seg>and often did my human nature turn <seg xml:id="C09_app1008-fThomas">with loathing </seg>from my <seg xml:id="C09_app1010-fThomas">occupation, whilst, </seg>still urged on by an eagerness which perpetually <seg xml:id="C09_app1014-fThomas">increased, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1015-fThomas">
               <pb n="092" xml:id="F1818_v1_104"/>I </seg>brought my work near to a <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1019-fThomas__Pt1">conclusion.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p10">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1019-fThomas__Pt2">The </seg>summer months passed while I was thus <seg xml:id="C09_app1023-fThomas">engaged, </seg>heart and soul, in one pursuit. It was a most beautiful <seg xml:id="C09_app1027-fThomas">season; </seg>never did the fields bestow a more plentiful harvest, or the vines <seg xml:id="C09_app1033-fThomas">yield </seg>a more luxuriant <seg xml:id="C09_app1037-fThomas">vintage: </seg>but my eyes were <seg xml:id="C09_app1039-fThomas">insensible </seg>to the charms of <seg xml:id="C09_app1041-fThomas">nature. </seg>And the same feelings which <seg xml:id="C09_app1045-fThomas">made </seg>me neglect the scenes around me caused me also to forget those friends who were so many miles <seg xml:id="C09_app1053-fThomas">absent, </seg>and whom I had not seen for so long a time. I knew my silence disquieted <seg xml:id="C09_app1059-fThomas">them; </seg>and I well remembered the words of my <seg xml:id="C09_app1063-fThomas">father: “I </seg>know that while <seg xml:id="C09_app1065-fThomas">you </seg>are pleased with <seg xml:id="C09_app1067-fThomas">yourself, </seg>you <seg xml:id="C09_app1069-fThomas">will </seg>think of us with <seg xml:id="C09_app1071-fThomas">affection, and </seg>we shall hear regularly from <seg xml:id="C09_app1073-fThomas">you. </seg>You must pardon <seg xml:id="C09_app1075-fThomas">me, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1076-fThomas">if </seg>I regard any interruption <seg xml:id="C09_app1080-fThomas">in </seg>your <seg xml:id="C09_app1082-fThomas">correspondence </seg>as a proof <seg xml:id="C09_app1084-fThomas">
               <pb n="093" xml:id="F1818_v1_105"/>that </seg>your other <seg xml:id="C09_app1086-fThomas">duties </seg>are equally <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1088-fThomas__Pt1">neglected.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p11">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1088-fThomas__Pt2">I </seg>knew well therefore what would be <seg xml:id="C09_app1096-fThomas">my father’s feelings; </seg>but I could not tear my thoughts from my <seg xml:id="C09_app1100-fThomas">employment, </seg>loathsome in <seg xml:id="C09_app1102-fThomas">itself, </seg>but which had taken <seg xml:id="C09_app1104-fThomas">an irresistible </seg>hold of my imagination. I <seg xml:id="C09_app1110-fThomas">wished, </seg>as it <seg xml:id="C09_app1112-fThomas">were, </seg>to <seg xml:id="C09_app1114-fThomas">procrastinate all </seg>that related to my feelings of <seg xml:id="C09_app1116-fThomas">affection until </seg>the great <seg xml:id="C09_app1118-fThomas">object, which </seg>swallowed up every habit of my <seg xml:id="C09_app1120-fThomas">nature, </seg>should be <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1122-fThomas__Pt1">completed.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p12">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1122-fThomas__Pt2">I </seg>then thought that my father would be unjust <seg xml:id="C09_app1128-fThomas">if </seg>he ascribed my neglect to <seg xml:id="C09_app1132-fThomas">vice, </seg>or faultiness on my part; but I am now convinced that he was <seg xml:id="C09_app1140-fThomas">justified </seg>in conceiving <seg xml:id="C09_app1142-fThomas">that </seg>I should not be altogether free from <seg xml:id="C09_app1150-fThomas">blame. </seg>A human being in perfection ought always to preserve a calm and peaceful <seg xml:id="C09_app1158-fThomas">mind, </seg>and never to allow passion or <seg xml:id="C09_app1160-fThomas">a </seg>transitory desire to disturb his tranquillity. <seg xml:id="C09_app1164-fThomas">
               <pb n="094" xml:id="F1818_v1_106"/>I </seg>do not think that the pursuit of knowledge is <seg xml:id="C09_app1168-fThomas">an </seg>exception to this rule. If the <seg xml:id="C09_app1172-fThomas">study </seg>to which you apply yourself has a tendency to weaken your <seg xml:id="C09_app1178-fThomas">affections, </seg>and to destroy your taste for those simple pleasures in which no alloy can possibly <seg xml:id="C09_app1182-fThomas">mix, </seg>then that study is certainly <seg xml:id="C09_app1184-fThomas">unlawful, </seg>that is to <seg xml:id="C09_app1188-fThomas">say, </seg>not befitting the human mind. If this rule <seg xml:id="C09_app1196-fThomas">were always </seg>observed; if no man allowed any pursuit whatsoever to interfere with <seg xml:id="C09_app1200-fThomas">the </seg>tranquillity <seg xml:id="C09_app1202-fThomas">of </seg>his domestic <seg xml:id="C09_app1204-fThomas">affections, </seg>Greece had <seg xml:id="C09_app1206-fThomas">not </seg>been <seg xml:id="C09_app1208-fThomas">enslaved; </seg>Cæsar would have spared his <seg xml:id="C09_app1212-fThomas">country; </seg>America would have been discovered more <seg xml:id="C09_app1216-fThomas">gradually; </seg>and the empires of Mexico and Peru had not been <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1220-fThomas__Pt1">destroyed.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p13">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1220-fThomas__Pt2">But </seg>I forget that I am <seg xml:id="C09_app1222-fThomas">moralizing </seg>in the most <seg xml:id="C09_app1225-fThomas">interesting </seg>part of my tale; and your looks remind me to <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1229-fThomas__Pt1">proceed.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p14">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1229-fThomas__Pt2">My </seg>father made no reproach in his <seg xml:id="C09_app1231-fThomas">
               <pb n="095" xml:id="F1818_v1_107"/>letters; </seg>and only took notice of my silence by <seg xml:id="C09_app1237-fThomas">inquiring </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1238-fThomas">into my occupations </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1239-fThomas">more </seg>particularly than <seg xml:id="C09_app1243-fThomas">before. Winter, spring, </seg>and summer passed away during my <seg xml:id="C09_app1247-fThomas">labours; </seg>but I did not watch the blossom or the expanding <seg xml:id="C09_app1253-fThomas">leaves—sights </seg>which before <seg xml:id="C09_app1255-fThomas">always yielded </seg>me supreme <seg xml:id="C09_app1257-fThomas">delight, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1258-fThomas">so </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1259-fThomas">deeply </seg>was I <seg xml:id="C09_app1261-fThomas">engrossed </seg>in my occupation. The leaves of that year <seg xml:id="C09_app1263-fThomas">had </seg>withered before my work drew near <seg xml:id="C09_app1267-fThomas">to </seg>a <seg xml:id="C09_app1269-fThomas">close; </seg>and now every day <seg xml:id="C09_app1271-fThomas">shewed </seg>me more plainly how well I had succeeded. But my enthusiasm was checked by my <seg xml:id="C09_app1276-fThomas">anxiety, </seg>and I appeared rather like one doomed by slavery to toil in the <seg xml:id="C09_app1282-fThomas">mines, </seg>or any other <seg xml:id="C09_app1284-fThomas">unwholesome trade, </seg>than an artist occupied <seg xml:id="C09_app1288-fThomas">by </seg>his favourite employment. Every night <seg xml:id="C09_app1294-fThomas">I was </seg>oppressed <seg xml:id="C09_app1296-fThomas">by a slow fever, </seg>and I became <seg xml:id="C09_app1298-fThomas">nervous </seg>to a most painful degree; <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1302-fThomas__Pt1">
               </seg>
               <del xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter3_div4_div3_p14_del1">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1302-fThomas__Pt2">a </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1304-fThomas">disease </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1305-fThomas">that </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1306-fThomas">I regretted the more because </seg>I <seg xml:id="C09_app1308-fThomas">had </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1310-fThomas">hitherto </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1311-fThomas">en<pb n="096" xml:id="F1818_v1_108"/>joyed </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1312-fThomas">most </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1313-fThomas">excellent </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1314-fThomas">health, and </seg>had <seg xml:id="C09_app1316-fThomas">always </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1318-fThomas">boasted </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1319-fThomas">of </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C09_app1320-fThomas">the firmness </seg>of <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1322-fThomas__Pt1">my nerves.</seg>
               </del>
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1322-fThomas__Pt2">my voice became broken, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1323-fThomas">my </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1324-fThomas">trembling hands almost refused to accomplish their task; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1325-fThomas">I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1326-fThomas">became as timid as a love-sick girl, and alternate tremor and passionate ardour took the place of wholesome sensation </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1327-fThomas">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1328-fThomas">regulated ambition. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C09_app1329-fThomas">But </seg>I believed that exercise and amusement would <seg xml:id="C09_app1335-fThomas">soon </seg>drive away <seg xml:id="C09_app1338-fThomas">such symptoms; </seg>and I promised myself both of <seg xml:id="C09_app1342-fThomas">these, </seg>when my creation should be <seg part="I" xml:id="C09_app1346-fThomas__Pt1">complete.</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C09_app1346-fThomas__Pt2">
            <milestone n="3" type="end" unit="chapter"/>
            <pb n="097" xml:id="F1818_v1_109"/> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>