<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C15</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app1-f1831__Pt1">
            <milestone n="9" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_head1">CHAPTER IX.</head>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app1-f1831__Pt2">N<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p1_hi1">OTHING</hi> 
               </seg>is more painful <seg xml:id="C15_app3-f1831">to </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app5-f1831">human mind, than, after the feelings have </seg>been worked up by a <seg xml:id="C15_app7-f1831">quick </seg>succession of events, <seg xml:id="C15_app9-f1831">the </seg>dead <seg xml:id="C15_app11-f1831">calmness </seg>of inaction and certainty <seg xml:id="C15_app13-f1831">which follows, </seg>and deprives the <seg xml:id="C15_app17-f1831">soul </seg>both of hope <seg xml:id="C15_app19-f1831">and </seg>fear. Justine <seg xml:id="C15_app23-f1831">died; </seg>she <seg xml:id="C15_app25-f1831">rested; and </seg>I was <seg xml:id="C15_app27-f1831">alive. </seg>The blood flowed freely in my <seg xml:id="C15_app29-f1831">veins, </seg>but a weight of despair and remorse pressed on my <seg xml:id="C15_app35-f1831">heart, </seg>which <seg xml:id="C15_app37-f1831">nothing </seg>could <seg xml:id="C15_app39-f1831">remove. Sleep </seg>fled from my <seg xml:id="C15_app43-f1831">eyes; </seg>I wandered like an evil <seg xml:id="C15_app47-f1831">spirit, </seg>for I <seg xml:id="C15_app49-f1831">had </seg>committed deeds of <seg xml:id="C15_app51-f1831">mischief beyond </seg>description horrible, and <seg xml:id="C15_app54-f1831">more, </seg>much <seg xml:id="C15_app56-f1831">more </seg>(I persuaded <seg xml:id="C15_app60-f1831">myself), </seg>was yet <seg xml:id="C15_app62-f1831">behind. </seg>Yet my heart overflowed with <seg xml:id="C15_app64-f1831">kindness, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app66-f1831">the love of virtue. </seg>I had begun life with benevolent <seg xml:id="C15_app70-f1831">intentions, </seg>and thirsted for the moment when I <seg xml:id="C15_app74-f1831">should </seg>put them in <seg xml:id="C15_app76-f1831">practice, </seg>and make myself useful to my <seg xml:id="C15_app78-f1831">fellow-beings. Now </seg>all was <seg xml:id="C15_app80-f1831">blasted: </seg>instead of <seg xml:id="C15_app84-f1831">that serenity </seg>of <seg xml:id="C15_app86-f1831">conscience, </seg>which allowed me to look back <seg xml:id="C15_app90-f1831">upon the past </seg>with <seg xml:id="C15_app92-f1831">self-satisfaction, </seg>and from thence to gather promise of new <seg xml:id="C15_app94-f1831">hopes, </seg>I was seized by remorse and <seg xml:id="C15_app98-f1831">the sense of </seg>guilt, <seg xml:id="C15_app100-f1831">which </seg>hurried <seg xml:id="C15_app102-f1831">me </seg>away to a hell <seg xml:id="C15_app106-f1831">of </seg>intense <seg xml:id="C15_app108-f1831">tortures, </seg>such as no language can <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app110-f1831__Pt1">describe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app110-f1831__Pt2">
               <pb n="75" xml:id="F1831_v_091"/>This </seg>state of mind <seg xml:id="C15_app112-f1831">preyed </seg>upon my <seg xml:id="C15_app114-f1831">health, </seg>which had <seg xml:id="C15_app116-f1831">perhaps never </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app117-f1831">entirely </seg>recovered <seg xml:id="C15_app119-f1831">from </seg>the first shock it had sustained. I shunned the face of man; all sound of joy or complacency was torture to <seg xml:id="C15_app127-f1831">me; </seg>solitude was my only <seg xml:id="C15_app131-f1831">consolation—deep, </seg>dark, <seg xml:id="C15_app133-f1831">deathlike </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app135-f1831__Pt1">solitude.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app135-f1831__Pt2">My </seg>father observed with pain <seg xml:id="C15_app139-f1831">the </seg>alteration perceptible in my <seg xml:id="C15_app141-f1831">disposition </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app143-f1831">habits, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app145-f1831">and </seg>endeavoured <seg xml:id="C15_app147-f1831">by arguments deduced from </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app151-f1831">feelings </seg>of <seg xml:id="C15_app153-f1831">his serene conscience and guiltless life, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app155-f1831">to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app156-f1831">inspire me with fortitude, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app157-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app158-f1831">awaken in me the courage </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app159-f1831">to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app160-f1831">dispel the dark cloud which brooded over me. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app161-f1831">“Do </seg>you think, <seg xml:id="C15_app163-f1831">Victor,” </seg>said <seg xml:id="C15_app165-f1831">he, “that </seg>I do not suffer <seg xml:id="C15_app167-f1831">also? </seg>No one could <seg xml:id="C15_app169-f1831">love </seg>a child more than I <seg xml:id="C15_app171-f1831">loved </seg>your <seg xml:id="C15_app173-f1831">brother;” (tears </seg>came into his eyes as he <seg xml:id="C15_app177-f1831">spoke;) </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app178-f1831">“but </seg>is it not <seg xml:id="C15_app180-f1831">a </seg>duty to the <seg xml:id="C15_app184-f1831">survivors, </seg>that we should refrain from augmenting their unhappiness by an appearance of immoderate <seg xml:id="C15_app190-f1831">grief? </seg>It is also a duty owed to yourself; for excessive sorrow prevents improvement or enjoyment, or even the discharge of <seg xml:id="C15_app198-f1831">daily usefulness, </seg>without which no man is fit for <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app200-f1831__Pt1">society.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app200-f1831__Pt2">This </seg>advice, although good, was <seg xml:id="C15_app202-f1831">totally inapplicable </seg>to my case; I should have been the first to hide my <seg xml:id="C15_app206-f1831">grief, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app208-f1831">console </seg>my <seg xml:id="C15_app211-f1831">friends, </seg>if remorse had not mingled <seg xml:id="C15_app213-f1831">its </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app214-f1831">bitterness, and terror </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app215-f1831">its </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app216-f1831">alarm </seg>with my other sensations. Now I could only answer my father with a look of <seg xml:id="C15_app222-f1831">despair, </seg>and endeavour to hide myself from his <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app226-f1831__Pt1">view.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app226-f1831__Pt2">About </seg>this time we retired to our house at Belrive. This change was <seg xml:id="C15_app236-f1831">particularly agreeable </seg>to <seg xml:id="C15_app238-f1831">me. </seg>The shutting of the gates regularly at ten <seg xml:id="C15_app246-f1831">o’clock, </seg>and the impossibility of <seg xml:id="C15_app248-f1831">remaining </seg>on the lake after that <seg xml:id="C15_app250-f1831">hour, had </seg>rendered our residence within the walls of Geneva very irksome to me. I was now <seg xml:id="C15_app256-f1831">free. </seg>Often, after the rest of the family had retired for the <seg xml:id="C15_app260-f1831">night, </seg>I took the <seg xml:id="C15_app262-f1831">boat, </seg>and passed <seg xml:id="C15_app264-f1831">many hours </seg>upon the <seg xml:id="C15_app266-f1831">water. Sometimes, </seg>with my sails <seg xml:id="C15_app268-f1831">set, </seg>I was carried by the <seg xml:id="C15_app270-f1831">wind; </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app272-f1831">sometimes, </seg>after rowing into the middle of the <seg xml:id="C15_app278-f1831">lake, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C15_app280-f1831">left </seg>the boat to <seg xml:id="C15_app284-f1831">pursue </seg>its own <seg xml:id="C15_app286-f1831">course, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app288-f1831">gave </seg>way to my own miserable reflections. I was often <seg xml:id="C15_app292-f1831">tempted, </seg>when <seg xml:id="C15_app294-f1831">all </seg>was <seg xml:id="C15_app296-f1831">at </seg>peace around <seg xml:id="C15_app298-f1831">me, </seg>and I the only unquiet thing that wandered restless in a scene so beautiful and <seg xml:id="C15_app302-f1831">heavenly—if </seg>I except some bat, or <seg xml:id="C15_app307-f1831">the frogs, </seg>whose harsh and interrupted croaking <seg xml:id="C15_app311-f1831">was </seg>heard only when I <seg xml:id="C15_app313-f1831">ap<pb n="76" xml:id="F1831_v_092"/>proached </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app315-f1831">shore—often, </seg>I say, I was tempted to plunge into the silent <seg xml:id="C15_app321-f1831">lake, that </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app323-f1831">waters might </seg>close over me and my calamities for ever. But I was <seg xml:id="C15_app325-f1831">restrained, </seg>when I thought of the heroic <seg xml:id="C15_app327-f1831">and suffering Elizabeth, </seg>whom I tenderly loved, and whose existence was bound up in mine. I thought also of my <seg xml:id="C15_app337-f1831">father, </seg>and surviving <seg xml:id="C15_app339-f1831">brother: </seg>should I by my base desertion leave them exposed and unprotected to the <seg xml:id="C15_app345-f1831">malice </seg>of the fiend whom I had let <seg xml:id="C15_app351-f1831">loose </seg>among <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app353-f1831__Pt1">them?</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app353-f1831__Pt2">At </seg>these moments I wept <seg xml:id="C15_app357-f1831">bitterly, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app358-f1831">and </seg>wished that peace would revisit my mind only that I might afford them consolation and <seg xml:id="C15_app368-f1831">happiness. </seg>But that <seg xml:id="C15_app370-f1831">could </seg>not <seg xml:id="C15_app372-f1831">be. </seg>Remorse <seg xml:id="C15_app374-f1831">extinguished </seg>every <seg xml:id="C15_app376-f1831">hope. </seg>I had been the <seg xml:id="C15_app378-f1831">author </seg>of unalterable <seg xml:id="C15_app380-f1831">evils; </seg>and I lived in daily <seg xml:id="C15_app382-f1831">fear, lest </seg>the monster whom I had created <seg xml:id="C15_app386-f1831">should perpetrate some </seg>new wickedness. <seg xml:id="C15_app388-f1831">I </seg>had <seg xml:id="C15_app390-f1831">an obscure </seg>feeling that all was not over, and that he would still commit some <seg xml:id="C15_app396-f1831">signal crime, </seg>which by its enormity <seg xml:id="C15_app398-f1831">should </seg>almost efface the recollection of the past. <seg xml:id="C15_app400-f1831">There </seg>was always scope for <seg xml:id="C15_app406-f1831">fear, </seg>so long as any thing I loved remained <seg xml:id="C15_app414-f1831">behind. </seg>My abhorrence of this fiend cannot be <seg xml:id="C15_app418-f1831">conceived. </seg>When I thought of <seg xml:id="C15_app420-f1831">him, </seg>I gnashed my <seg xml:id="C15_app424-f1831">teeth, </seg>my eyes became <seg xml:id="C15_app426-f1831">inflamed, </seg>and I ardently wished to extinguish that life which I had so thoughtlessly bestowed. When I reflected on his crimes and malice, my hatred and <seg xml:id="C15_app437-f1831">revenge </seg>burst all bounds of <seg xml:id="C15_app439-f1831">moderation. </seg>I would have made a pilgrimage to the <seg xml:id="C15_app443-f1831">highest peak </seg>of the <seg xml:id="C15_app445-f1831">Andes, </seg>could <seg xml:id="C15_app447-f1831">I, </seg>when <seg xml:id="C15_app449-f1831">there, </seg>have precipitated him to their <seg xml:id="C15_app451-f1831">base. </seg>I wished to see him <seg xml:id="C15_app457-f1831">again, </seg>that I might wreak the utmost extent of <seg xml:id="C15_app461-f1831">abhorrence </seg>on his <seg xml:id="C15_app464-f1831">head, </seg>and avenge the deaths of William and <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app468-f1831__Pt1">Justine.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app468-f1831__Pt2">Our </seg>house was the house of <seg xml:id="C15_app474-f1831">mourning. </seg>My <seg xml:id="C15_app476-f1831">father’s </seg>health was deeply shaken by the horror of the recent events. Elizabeth was sad and <seg xml:id="C15_app482-f1831">desponding; </seg>she no longer took delight in her ordinary occupations; all pleasure seemed to her <seg xml:id="C15_app488-f1831">sacrilege toward </seg>the dead; <seg xml:id="C15_app490-f1831">eternal </seg>woe and <seg xml:id="C15_app492-f1831">tears </seg>she then thought was the just tribute she should pay to innocence so blasted and destroyed. She was no longer that happy <seg xml:id="C15_app500-f1831">creature, </seg>who in earlier youth wandered with me on the banks of the <seg xml:id="C15_app508-f1831">lake, </seg>and talked with <seg xml:id="C15_app510-f1831">ecstasy </seg>of our future <seg xml:id="C15_app512-f1831">prospects. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app513-f1831">The first of those sorrows which are <pb n="77" xml:id="F1831_v_093"/>sent to wean us from </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app519-f1831">earth, had visited her, </seg>and <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app522-f1831__Pt1">its dimming influence quenched her dearest smiles.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app522-f1831__Pt2">“When </seg>I reflect, my dear <seg xml:id="C15_app525-f1831">cousin,” </seg>said <seg xml:id="C15_app527-f1831">she, “on </seg>the miserable death of Justine Moritz, I no longer see the world and its works as they before appeared to me. <seg xml:id="C15_app539-f1831">Before, I </seg>looked upon the accounts of vice and <seg xml:id="C15_app543-f1831">injustice, </seg>that I read in books or heard from <seg xml:id="C15_app547-f1831">others, </seg>as tales of ancient <seg xml:id="C15_app549-f1831">days, </seg>or imaginary <seg xml:id="C15_app553-f1831">evils; at </seg>least they were remote, and more familiar to reason than to <seg xml:id="C15_app565-f1831">the imagination; </seg>but now misery has come <seg xml:id="C15_app569-f1831">home, </seg>and men appear to me as monsters thirsting for each <seg xml:id="C15_app573-f1831">other’s </seg>blood. Yet I am certainly <seg xml:id="C15_app577-f1831">unjust. Every body </seg>believed that poor girl to be <seg xml:id="C15_app579-f1831">guilty; </seg>and if she <seg xml:id="C15_app583-f1831">could </seg>have committed the crime for which she suffered, assuredly she would have been the most depraved of human creatures. For the sake of a few <seg xml:id="C15_app591-f1831">jewels, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app592-f1831">to </seg>have murdered the son of her benefactor and friend, a child whom she had nursed from its <seg xml:id="C15_app598-f1831">birth, </seg>and appeared to love as <seg xml:id="C15_app600-f1831">if </seg>it had been her <seg xml:id="C15_app604-f1831">own! </seg>I could not consent to the death of any human <seg xml:id="C15_app608-f1831">being; but </seg>certainly I should have thought such a <seg xml:id="C15_app612-f1831">creature </seg>unfit to remain in the society of men. <seg xml:id="C15_app614-f1831">But </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app616-f1831">she </seg>was <seg xml:id="C15_app618-f1831">innocent. I know, I </seg>feel she was <seg xml:id="C15_app620-f1831">innocent; </seg>you are of the same <seg xml:id="C15_app624-f1831">opinion, </seg>and that confirms me. <seg xml:id="C15_app628-f1831">Alas! Victor, </seg>when <seg xml:id="C15_app630-f1831">falsehood can </seg>look so like the truth, who can assure <seg xml:id="C15_app632-f1831">themselves </seg>of certain happiness? I feel as if I were walking on the edge of <seg xml:id="C15_app636-f1831">a precipice, </seg>towards which thousands are <seg xml:id="C15_app638-f1831">crowding, </seg>and endeavouring to plunge me into the <seg xml:id="C15_app640-f1831">abyss. </seg>William and Justine were <seg xml:id="C15_app642-f1831">assassinated, </seg>and the murderer <seg xml:id="C15_app644-f1831">escapes; </seg>he walks <seg xml:id="C15_app646-f1831">about </seg>the world <seg xml:id="C15_app648-f1831">free, </seg>and perhaps respected. But even if I were <seg xml:id="C15_app656-f1831">condemned </seg>to suffer on the scaffold <seg xml:id="C15_app658-f1831">for </seg>the same <seg xml:id="C15_app660-f1831">crimes, </seg>I would not change places with such a <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app664-f1831__Pt1">wretch.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app664-f1831__Pt2">I </seg>listened to this discourse with the extremest <seg xml:id="C15_app668-f1831">agony. I, </seg>not <seg xml:id="C15_app670-f1831">in deed, </seg>but <seg xml:id="C15_app672-f1831">in </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app673-f1831">effect, </seg>was the true <seg xml:id="C15_app675-f1831">murderer. </seg>Elizabeth read my anguish in my countenance, and kindly taking my <seg xml:id="C15_app677-f1831">hand, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app678-f1831">said, “My </seg>dearest <seg xml:id="C15_app680-f1831">friend, </seg>you must calm <seg xml:id="C15_app684-f1831">yourself. </seg>These events have <seg xml:id="C15_app686-f1831">affected me, God </seg>knows how <seg xml:id="C15_app688-f1831">deeply; </seg>but I am not so wretched as you are. There is an expression of <seg xml:id="C15_app694-f1831">despair, </seg>and sometimes of <seg xml:id="C15_app696-f1831">revenge, </seg>in your <seg xml:id="C15_app698-f1831">countenance, </seg>that makes me <seg xml:id="C15_app702-f1831">tremble. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app703-f1831">Dear Victor, banish these dark passions. Remember the friends around you, <pb n="78" xml:id="F1831_v_094"/>who centre all their hopes in you. Have we lost the power of rendering you happy? Ah! while we love—while </seg>we <seg xml:id="C15_app711-f1831">are true to each other, here </seg>in <seg xml:id="C15_app715-f1831">this land of peace and beauty, your </seg>native <seg xml:id="C15_app717-f1831">country, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app718-f1831">we may reap every tranquil blessing,—what </seg>can <seg xml:id="C15_app722-f1831">disturb our </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app723-f1831__Pt1">peace?”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p10">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app723-f1831__Pt2">And could not such words from her whom I fondly prized before every other gift of fortune, suffice to </seg>chase away the fiend that lurked in my <seg xml:id="C15_app741-f1831">heart? Even as she spoke I drew near to her, as if </seg>in <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app747-f1831__Pt1">terror; lest at that very moment the destroyer had been near to rob me of her. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p11">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app747-f1831__Pt2">Thus not the tenderness of friendship, nor </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app759-f1831">beauty </seg>of <seg xml:id="C15_app763-f1831">earth, nor of heaven, could redeem my soul </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app766-f1831">from </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app767-f1831">woe: the very accents of love were ineffectual. I was encompassed </seg>by <seg xml:id="C15_app772-f1831">a cloud which no beneficial influence could penetrate. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C15_app774-f1831">wounded deer dragging its fainting limbs to some untrodden brake, there </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app782-f1831">to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app783-f1831">gaze upon </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app785-f1831">arrow which had pierced it, and to die—was </seg>but <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app790-f1831__Pt1">a type of me.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p12">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app790-f1831__Pt2">Sometimes I could cope with the sullen despair that overwhelmed me: but sometimes </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app797-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app798-f1831">whirlwind passions </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app799-f1831">of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app800-f1831">my soul drove me </seg>to <seg xml:id="C15_app806-f1831">seek, by bodily exercise </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app808-f1831">by change of place, some relief </seg>from <seg xml:id="C15_app810-f1831">my intolerable sensations. It was during an access of </seg>this <seg xml:id="C15_app813-f1831">kind that I suddenly left my home, and bending my steps towards </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app817-f1831">near Alpine valleys, sought in the magnificence, </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app823-f1831">eternity </seg>of <seg xml:id="C15_app825-f1831">such scenes, to forget myself </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app829-f1831">my ephemeral, because human, sorrows. My wanderings were directed towards the valley of Chamounix. I </seg>had <seg xml:id="C15_app840-f1831">visited it frequently during </seg>my <seg xml:id="C15_app846-f1831">boyhood. Six years had passed since then: </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app849-f1831">
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p12_hi1">I</hi> 
               </seg>was <seg xml:id="C15_app851-f1831">a wreck—but nought had changed </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app852-f1831">in </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app853-f1831__Pt1">those savage and enduring scenes.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p13">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app853-f1831__Pt2">I performed </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app855-f1831">first part of my journey on horseback. I afterwards hired a mule, as </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app858-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app859-f1831">more sure-footed, and least liable to receive injury on these rugged roads. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C15_app863-f1831">weather was fine: it was about the middle of </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app867-f1831">month of August, nearly two months after the death of Justine; </seg>that <seg xml:id="C15_app873-f1831">miserable epoch from </seg>which <seg xml:id="C15_app876-f1831">I dated all my woe. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C15_app880-f1831">weight upon my spirit was sensibly lightened as I plunged yet deeper in </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app889-f1831">ravine of Arve. The </seg>immense mountains <seg xml:id="C15_app894-f1831">and precipices </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app895-f1831">that overhung me </seg>on <seg xml:id="C15_app897-f1831">every </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app898-f1831">side—the </seg>sound of <seg xml:id="C15_app901-f1831">the </seg>river <seg xml:id="C15_app903-f1831">raging among </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app904-f1831">the </seg>rocks, and the dashing <seg xml:id="C15_app906-f1831">of the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app907-f1831">
               <pb n="79" xml:id="F1831_v_095"/>waterfalls around, spoke </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app908-f1831">of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app909-f1831">a power mighty as Omnipotence—and I ceased to fear, or to bend before any being less almighty than that which had created </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app916-f1831">ruled the elements, here displayed in their most terrific guise. Still, </seg>as <seg xml:id="C15_app918-f1831">I </seg>ascended <seg xml:id="C15_app922-f1831">higher, </seg>the valley assumed a more <seg xml:id="C15_app926-f1831">magnificent </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app928-f1831">astonishing character. </seg>Ruined castles <seg xml:id="C15_app930-f1831">hanging </seg>on the precipices <seg xml:id="C15_app932-f1831">of </seg>piny mountains; the impetuous Arve, and cottages every here and there peeping <seg xml:id="C15_app938-f1831">forth </seg>from among the trees, formed a scene of singular <seg xml:id="C15_app942-f1831">beauty. </seg>But it was <seg xml:id="C15_app944-f1831">augmented and </seg>rendered sublime by the mighty <seg xml:id="C15_app946-f1831">Alps, </seg>whose white and shining <seg xml:id="C15_app948-f1831">pyramids </seg>and domes towered above <seg xml:id="C15_app950-f1831">all, as belonging to </seg>another <seg xml:id="C15_app952-f1831">earth, the </seg>habitations of another race of <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app956-f1831__Pt1">beings.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p14">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app956-f1831__Pt2">I </seg>passed the bridge of <seg xml:id="C15_app958-f1831">Pélissier, </seg>where the <seg xml:id="C15_app960-f1831">ravine, </seg>which the river <seg xml:id="C15_app964-f1831">forms, </seg>opened before <seg xml:id="C15_app966-f1831">me, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app968-f1831">I </seg>began to ascend the mountain <seg xml:id="C15_app971-f1831">that overhangs it. </seg>Soon after <seg xml:id="C15_app973-f1831">I </seg>entered the valley of Chamounix. This valley is more wonderful and <seg xml:id="C15_app978-f1831">sublime, </seg>but not so <seg xml:id="C15_app980-f1831">beautiful and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app981-f1831">picturesque, </seg>as that of <seg xml:id="C15_app984-f1831">Servox, </seg>through which <seg xml:id="C15_app986-f1831">I </seg>had just passed. The high and snowy mountains <seg xml:id="C15_app991-f1831">were </seg>its <seg xml:id="C15_app993-f1831">immediate boundaries; </seg>but <seg xml:id="C15_app995-f1831">I </seg>saw no more ruined castles <seg xml:id="C15_app998-f1831">and </seg>fertile fields. Immense glaciers approached the <seg xml:id="C15_app1002-f1831">road; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1003-f1831">I </seg>heard the rumbling thunder of the falling <seg xml:id="C15_app1007-f1831">avalanche, </seg>and marked the smoke of its <seg xml:id="C15_app1011-f1831">passage. Mont </seg>Blanc, the <seg xml:id="C15_app1013-f1831">supreme </seg>and magnificent Mont <seg xml:id="C15_app1015-f1831">Blanc, </seg>raised itself from the surrounding <seg xml:id="C15_app1019-f1831">
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p14_hi1">aiguilles</hi>, </seg>and its tremendous <seg xml:id="C15_app1021-f1831">
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p14_hi2">dôme</hi> 
               </seg>overlooked the <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app1023-f1831__Pt1">valley.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p15">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app1023-f1831__Pt2">A tingling long-lost sense of pleasure often came across me </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1024-f1831">during </seg>this <seg xml:id="C15_app1026-f1831">journey. Some turn in the road, some new object suddenly perceived </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app1030-f1831">recognised, reminded me of days gone by, and were associated with </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app1034-f1831">light-hearted gaiety </seg>of <seg xml:id="C15_app1036-f1831">boyhood. </seg>The <seg xml:id="C15_app1038-f1831">very winds whispered in soothing accents, and maternal nature bade me weep no more. Then again the kindly influence ceased </seg>to <seg xml:id="C15_app1045-f1831">act—I found myself fettered again to grief, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app1048-f1831">indulging </seg>in <seg xml:id="C15_app1050-f1831">all </seg>the misery of reflection. <seg xml:id="C15_app1052-f1831">Then </seg>I spurred on my <seg xml:id="C15_app1060-f1831">animal, striving so to </seg>forget the world, <seg xml:id="C15_app1066-f1831">my fears, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1067-f1831">and, </seg>more than <seg xml:id="C15_app1069-f1831">all, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1070-f1831">myself—or, in </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1071-f1831">a </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1072-f1831">more desperate fashion, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C15_app1074-f1831">alighted, </seg>and threw myself on the <seg xml:id="C15_app1078-f1831">grass, </seg>weighed down by horror and <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app1082-f1831__Pt1">despair.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter9_div4_div9_p16">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app1082-f1831__Pt2">At length </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C15_app1085-f1831">I </seg>arrived at <seg xml:id="C15_app1087-f1831">the village of Chamounix. Exhaustion succeeded to </seg>the <seg xml:id="C15_app1098-f1831">extreme fatigue both of body </seg>and <seg xml:id="C15_app1104-f1831">
               <pb n="80" xml:id="F1831_v_096"/>of mind which I had endured. </seg>For <seg xml:id="C15_app1111-f1831">a short space of time </seg>I remained at the <seg xml:id="C15_app1123-f1831">window, </seg>watching the pallid <seg xml:id="C15_app1125-f1831">lightnings </seg>that played above Mont <seg xml:id="C15_app1129-f1831">Blanc, </seg>and listening to the rushing of the <seg xml:id="C15_app1133-f1831">Arve, </seg>which <seg xml:id="C15_app1135-f1831">pursued its noisy way beneath. The same lulling sounds acted as a lullaby to my too keen sensations: when I placed my head upon </seg>my <seg part="I" xml:id="C15_app1139-f1831__Pt1">pillow, sleep crept over me; I felt it as it came, and blest the giver of oblivion. </seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C15_app1139-f1831__Pt2">
            <milestone n="9" type="end" unit="chapter"/> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>