<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C28</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app1-f1831__Pt1">
            <milestone n="22" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <pb n="165" xml:id="F1831_v_181"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_head1">CHAPTER XXII.</head>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app1-f1831__Pt2">T<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p1_hi1">HE</hi> voyage came </seg>to <seg xml:id="C28_app4-f1831">an end. We landed, and proceeded </seg>to <seg xml:id="C28_app6-f1831">Paris. I soon found that I had overtaxed my strength, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C28_app12-f1831">that I must repose before </seg>I <seg xml:id="C28_app17-f1831">could continue my journey. My father’s care and attentions were indefatigable; but he did not know the origin of my sufferings, and sought erroneous methods </seg>to <seg xml:id="C28_app24-f1831">remedy the incurable ill. He wished me to seek amusement </seg>in <seg xml:id="C28_app26-f1831">society. </seg>I <seg xml:id="C28_app29-f1831">abhorred the face of man. Oh, not abhorred! they were my brethren, </seg>my <seg xml:id="C28_app31-f1831">fellow beings, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app33-f1831">and </seg>I <seg xml:id="C28_app35-f1831">felt attracted even to the most repulsive among them, as to creatures of an angelic nature </seg>and <seg xml:id="C28_app46-f1831">celestial mechanism. But I felt that I had no right to share their intercourse. I had unchained an enemy among them, whose joy it was to shed their blood, and to revel </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app63-f1831">in </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app64-f1831">their groans. How they would, each and all, abhor me, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app68-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app69-f1831">hunt me from </seg>the <seg xml:id="C28_app72-f1831">world, did they know my unhallowed acts, </seg>and <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app78-f1831__Pt1">the crimes which had their source in me!</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app78-f1831__Pt2">My father yielded at length to </seg>my <seg xml:id="C28_app83-f1831">desire to avoid society, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C28_app85-f1831">strove by various arguments to banish my </seg>despair. Sometimes he thought that I felt deeply the degradation of being obliged to answer a charge of <seg xml:id="C28_app93-f1831">murder, </seg>and he endeavoured to <seg xml:id="C28_app97-f1831">prove </seg>to me the futility of <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app101-f1831__Pt1">pride.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app101-f1831__Pt2">“Alas! </seg>my <seg xml:id="C28_app103-f1831">father,” </seg>said I, <seg xml:id="C28_app105-f1831">“how </seg>little do you know <seg xml:id="C28_app109-f1831">me. </seg>Human beings, their feelings and <seg xml:id="C28_app113-f1831">passions, </seg>would indeed be <seg xml:id="C28_app115-f1831">degraded </seg>if such a wretch as I felt pride. <seg xml:id="C28_app118-f1831">Justine, </seg>poor unhappy <seg xml:id="C28_app120-f1831">Justine, </seg>was as innocent as <seg xml:id="C28_app124-f1831">I, </seg>and she suffered the same <seg xml:id="C28_app126-f1831">charge; </seg>she died for <seg xml:id="C28_app128-f1831">it; </seg>and I am the cause of <seg xml:id="C28_app132-f1831">this—I </seg>murdered her. <seg xml:id="C28_app134-f1831">William, Justine, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app136-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app137-f1831">Henry—they </seg>all died by my <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app139-f1831__Pt1">hands.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app139-f1831__Pt2">My </seg>father had <seg xml:id="C28_app141-f1831">often, </seg>during my <seg xml:id="C28_app143-f1831">imprisonment, </seg>heard me make the same <seg xml:id="C28_app147-f1831">assertion; </seg>when <seg xml:id="C28_app149-f1831">I thus </seg>accused myself, he sometimes seemed to desire an <seg xml:id="C28_app151-f1831">explanation, </seg>and at others he appeared to consider it as <seg xml:id="C28_app155-f1831">the offspring of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app156-f1831">delirium, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C28_app158-f1831">that, </seg>during my <seg xml:id="C28_app160-f1831">illness, </seg>some idea of this kind had presented itself to my <seg xml:id="C28_app166-f1831">imagination, </seg>the <seg xml:id="C28_app168-f1831">remembrance </seg>of which I preserved in my convalescence. <seg xml:id="C28_app170-f1831">I </seg>avoided <seg xml:id="C28_app172-f1831">explanation, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app173-f1831">
               <pb n="166" xml:id="F1831_v_182"/>and </seg>maintained a continual silence concerning the wretch I had created. I had a <seg xml:id="C28_app177-f1831">persuasion </seg>that I should be supposed <seg xml:id="C28_app180-f1831">mad; </seg>and this <seg xml:id="C28_app182-f1831">in itself would </seg>for ever <seg xml:id="C28_app184-f1831">have </seg>chained <seg xml:id="C28_app186-f1831">my tongue. But, besides, I could not bring myself to disclose a secret which would fill my hearer with consternation, and make fear and unnatural horror the inmates of his breast. I checked, therefore, </seg>my <seg xml:id="C28_app188-f1831">impatient thirst for sympathy, and was silent </seg>when I would have given the world to have confided the fatal <seg xml:id="C28_app196-f1831">secret. </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app197-f1831__Pt1">Yet still words like those I have recorded, would burst uncontrollably from me. I could offer no explanation of them; but their truth in part relieved the burden of my mysterious woe.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app197-f1831__Pt2">Upon </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app198-f1831">this occasion </seg>my father <seg xml:id="C28_app200-f1831">said, </seg>with an expression of unbounded <seg xml:id="C28_app204-f1831">wonder, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app205-f1831">“My dearest Victor, what infatuation is this? </seg>My dear son, I entreat you <seg xml:id="C28_app211-f1831">never </seg>to make <seg xml:id="C28_app213-f1831">such </seg>an assertion <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app215-f1831__Pt1">again.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app215-f1831__Pt2">“I </seg>am not <seg xml:id="C28_app217-f1831">mad,” </seg>I cried <seg xml:id="C28_app219-f1831">energetically; “the </seg>sun and the <seg xml:id="C28_app221-f1831">heavens, </seg>who have viewed my <seg xml:id="C28_app223-f1831">operations, </seg>can bear witness of my truth. I <seg xml:id="C28_app227-f1831">am </seg>the assassin of those most innocent <seg xml:id="C28_app231-f1831">victims; </seg>they died by my machinations. A thousand times would I have shed my own <seg xml:id="C28_app239-f1831">blood, </seg>drop by <seg xml:id="C28_app243-f1831">drop, </seg>to have saved their <seg xml:id="C28_app245-f1831">lives; </seg>but I could not, my father, indeed I could not sacrifice the whole human <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app247-f1831__Pt1">race.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app247-f1831__Pt2">The </seg>conclusion of this speech <seg xml:id="C28_app251-f1831">convinced </seg>my father that my ideas were <seg xml:id="C28_app255-f1831">deranged, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C28_app257-f1831">he instantly changed </seg>the subject of our <seg xml:id="C28_app259-f1831">conversation, and </seg>endeavoured to alter the course of my thoughts. He wished as much as possible to obliterate the memory of the scenes <seg xml:id="C28_app265-f1831">that had taken place </seg>in <seg xml:id="C28_app267-f1831">Ireland, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C28_app268-f1831">and </seg>never alluded to <seg xml:id="C28_app272-f1831">them, </seg>or suffered me to speak of my <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app276-f1831__Pt1">misfortunes.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app276-f1831__Pt2">As </seg>time passed away I became more <seg xml:id="C28_app280-f1831">calm: </seg>misery had her dwelling in my <seg xml:id="C28_app282-f1831">heart, </seg>but I no longer talked in the same incoherent manner of my own crimes; sufficient for me was the consciousness of them. By the utmost <seg xml:id="C28_app290-f1831">self-violence, </seg>I curbed the imperious voice of <seg xml:id="C28_app294-f1831">wretchedness, </seg>which <seg xml:id="C28_app296-f1831">sometimes </seg>desired to declare itself to the whole <seg xml:id="C28_app302-f1831">world; </seg>and my manners were calmer and more composed than they had ever been since my journey to the <seg xml:id="C28_app309-f1831">sea </seg>of <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app311-f1831__Pt1">ice.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter22_div4_div22_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app311-f1831__Pt2">A few days before we left Paris on our way </seg>to <seg xml:id="C28_app318-f1831">Switzerland, </seg>I received the following letter from <seg part="I" xml:id="C28_app329-f1831__Pt1">Elizabeth:—</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C28_app329-f1831__Pt2"> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>