<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1818v1.ch5</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1213</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 5</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Lackington, Hughes, Harding, Mavor, &amp; Jones</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1818</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">The First Edition</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1818 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 5</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p> CLERVAL then put the
              following letter into my hands.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"To V. FRANKENSTEIN.</p>
               <p>"MY DEAR COUSIN,</p>
               <p>"I cannot describe to you the uneasiness we have
              all felt concerning your health. We cannot help
              imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the
              extent of your disorder: for it is now several months
              since we have seen your hand-writing; and all this
              time you have been obliged to dictate your letters to
              Henry. Surely, Victor, you must have been exceedingly
              ill; and this makes us all very wretched, as much so
              nearly as after the death of your dear mother. My
              uncle was almost persuaded that you were indeed
              dangerously ill, and could hardly be restrained from
              undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. Clerval always
              writes that you are getting better; I eagerly hope
              that you will confirm
              this intelligence soon in your own hand-writing;
              for indeed, indeed, Victor, we are all very miserable
              on this account. Relieve us from this fear, and we
              shall be the happiest creatures in the world.
              
              Your father's health is now so vigorous, that he
              appears ten years younger since last winter. Ernest
              also is so much improved, that you would hardly know
              him: he is now nearly sixteen, and has lost that
              sickly appearance which he had some years ago; he is
              grown quite robust and active.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"My uncle and I
              conversed a long time last night about what
              profession Ernest should follow. His constant illness
              when young has deprived him of the habits of
              application; and now that he enjoys good health, he
              is continually in the open air, climbing the hills,
              or rowing on the lake. I therefore proposed that he
              should be a farmer; which you know, Cousin, is a
              favourite scheme of mine. A farmer's is a very
              healthy happy life; and the least hurtful, or rather
              the most beneficial profession of any. My uncle had
              an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that
              through
              his interest he might become a judge. But,
              besides that he is not at all fitted for such an
              occupation, it is certainly more
              creditable to cultivate the earth for the
              sustenance of man, than to be the confidant, and
              sometimes the accomplice, of his vices; which is the
              profession of a lawyer. I said, that the employments
              of a prosperous farmer, if they were not a more
              honourable, they were at least a happier species of
              occupation than that of a judge, whose misfortune it
              was always to
              meddle with the dark side of human nature. My
              uncle smiled, and said, that I ought to be an
              advocate myself, which put an end to the conversation
              on that subject.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"And now I must tell
              you a story that will please, and perhaps amuse you.
              Do you not remember Justine Moritz? Probably you do
              not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few
              words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with
              four children, of whom Justine was the third. This
              girl had always been the favourite of her father;
              but, through a strange perversity, her
              mother could not endure her, and, after the death
              of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed
              this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age,
              prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at her
              house. The republican
              institutions of our country have produced simpler
              and happier manners than those which prevail in the
              great
              monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less
              distinction between the several classes of its
              inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so
              poor nor so despised, their manners are more refined
              and moral. A
              servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a
              servant in France and England. Justine, thus
              received in our family, learned the duties of a
              servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country,
              does not include the idea of ignorance, and a
              sacrifice of the dignity of a human being.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"After what I have
              said, I dare say you well remember the heroine of my
              little tale: for Justine was a great favourite of
              your's; and I recollect you once remarked, that if
              you were in an ill humour, one glance from Justine
              could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto
              gives concerning the beauty of Angelica—she
              looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived
              a great attachment for her, by which she
              was induced to give her an education superior to
              that which she had at first intended. This benefit
              was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful
              little creature in the world: I do not mean that she
              made any professions, I never heard one pass her
              lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost
              adored her protectress. Although her disposition was
              gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid
              the greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt.
              She thought her the model of all excellence, and
              endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners,
              so that even
              now she often reminds me of her.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"When my dearest aunt
              died, everyone was too much occupied in their own
              grief to notice poor Justine, who had attended her
              during her illness with the most anxious affection.
              Poor Justine
              was very ill; but other trials were reserved for
              her.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"One by one, her
              brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the
              exception of her neglected daughter, was left
              childless. The conscience of the woman was
              troubled; she began to think that the deaths of her
              favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise her
              partiality. She was a Roman
              Catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed
              the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few
              months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine
              was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl!
              she wept when she quitted our house: she was much
              altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given
              softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which
              had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her
              residence at her mother's house of a nature to
              restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very
              vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged
              Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener
              accused her of having caused the deaths of her
              brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length
              threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first
              increased her irritability, but she is now at peace
              forever. She
              died on the first approach of cold weather, at
              the beginning of this last winter. Justine has
              returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly.
              She is very clever and gentle, and extremely pretty;
              as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions
              continually remind me of my dear aunt.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I must say also a few
              words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling
              William.
              I wish you could see him; he is very tall of his age,
              with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and
              curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples
              appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He
              has already had one or two little wives, but
              Louisa
              Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of
              five years of age.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Now, dear Victor, I
              dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip
              concerning the good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss
              Mansfield has already received the congratulatory
              visits on her approaching marriage with a young
              Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister,
              Manon, married M. Duvillard,
              the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite
              schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several
              misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from
              Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and
              is reported to be on the point of marrying a very
              lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a
              widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very
              much admired, and a favourite with every body.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I have written myself
              into good spirits, dear cousin; yet I cannot conclude
              without again anxiously inquiring concerning your
              health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill, write
              yourself, and make your father and all of us happy;
              or -- I cannot bear to think of the other side of the
              question; my tears already flow. Adieu, my dearest
              cousin.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"ELIZABETH
              LAVENZA.</p>
               <p>"Geneva, March 18th, 17--."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Dear, dear Elizabeth!"
              I exclaimed when I had read her letter, "I will write
              instantly, and relieve them from the anxiety they
              must feel." I wrote, and this exertion greatly
              fatigued me; but my convalescence had commenced, and
              proceeded regularly. In another fortnight I was able
              to leave my chamber.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>One of my first duties
              on my recovery was to introduce Clerval to the
              several professors of the university. In doing this,
              I underwent a kind of rough usage, ill befitting the
              wounds that my mind had sustained. Ever since the
              fatal night, the end of my labours, and the beginning
              of my misfortunes, I had conceived a violent
              antipathy even to the name of natural
              philosophy. When I was otherwise quite restored
              to health, the sight of a chemical instrument would
              renew all the agony of my nervous symptoms. Henry saw
              this, and had removed all my apparatus from my view.
              He had also changed my apartment; for he perceived
              that I had acquired a dislike for the room which had
              previously been my laboratory. But these cares of
              Clerval were made of no avail when I visited the
              professors. M. Waldman inflicted torture when he
              praised, with kindness and warmth, the astonishing
              progress I had made in the sciences. He soon
              perceived that I disliked the subject; but, not
              guessing the real cause, he attributed my feelings to
              modesty, and changed the subject from my improvement
              to the science itself, with a desire, as I evidently
              saw, of drawing me out. What could I do? He meant to
              please, and he tormented me. I felt as if he had
              placed carefully, one by one, in my view those
              instruments which were to be afterwards used in
              putting me to a slow and cruel death. I writhed under
              his words, yet dared not exhibit the pain I felt.
              Clerval, whose eyes and feelings were always quick in
              discerning the sensations of others, declined the
              subject, alleging, in excuse, his total ignorance;
              and the conversation took a more general turn. I
              thanked my friend from my heart, but I
              did not speak. I saw plainly that he was
              surprised, but he never attempted to draw my secret
              from me; and although I
              loved him with a mixture of affection and reverence
              that knew no bounds, yet I could never persuade
              myself to confide to him that event which was so
              often present to my recollection, but which I feared
              the detail to another would only impress more
              deeply.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>M. Krempe was not
              equally docile; and in my condition at that time, of
              almost insupportable sensitiveness, his harsh blunt
              encomiums gave me even more pain than the benevolent
              approbation of M. Waldman. "D--n the fellow!" cried
              he; "why, M. Clerval, I assure you he has outstript
              us all. Aye, stare if you please; but it is
              nevertheless true. A youngster who, but a few years
              ago, believed Cornelius Agrippa as firmly as the
              gospel, has now set himself at the head of the
              university; and if he is not soon pulled down, we
              shall all be out of countenance.—Aye, aye,"
              continued he, observing my face expressive of
              suffering, "M. Frankenstein is modest; an excellent
              quality in a young man. Young men should be diffident
              of themselves, you know, M. Clerval; I was myself
              when young; but that wears out in a very short
              time."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>M. Krempe had now
              commenced an eulogy on himself, which happily turned
              the conversation from a subject that was so annoying
              to me.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Clerval was no natural
              philosopher. His imagination was too vivid for the
              minutiae of science. Languages
              were his principal study; and he sought, but
              acquiring their elements, to open a field for
              self-instruction on his return to Geneva. Persian,
              Arabic, and Hebrew, gained his attention, after he
              had made himself perfectly master of Greek and Latin.
              For my own part, idleness had ever been irksome to
              me, and now that I wished to fly from reflection, and
              hated my former studies, I felt great relief in being
              the fellow-pupil with my friend, and found not only
              instruction but consolation in the works of the
              orientalists. Their melancholy is soothing, and their
              joy elevating to a degree I never experienced in
              studying the authors of any other country. When you
              read their writings, life appears to consist in a
              warm sun
              and garden of roses, in the
              smiles and frowns of a fair enemy, and the fire
              that consumes your own heart. How different from the
              manly
              and heroical poetry of Greece and Rome.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Summer passed away in
              these occupations, and my return to Geneva was fixed
              for the latter end of autumn; but being delayed by
              several accidents, winter and snow arrived, the roads
              were deemed impassable,
              and my journey was retarded until the ensuing spring.
              I felt this delay very bitterly; for I longed to see
              my native town, and my beloved friends. My return had
              only been delayed so long from an unwillingness
              to leave Clerval in a strange place, before he
              had become acquainted with any of its inhabitants.
              The winter, however, was spent cheerfully; and
              although the spring was uncommonly late, when it
              came, its beauty compensated for its
              dilatoriness.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The month of May had
              already commenced, and I expected the letter daily
              which was to fix the date of my departure, when Henry
              proposed a pedestrian tour in the environs of
              Ingolstadt that I might bid a personal farewell to
              the country I had so long inhabited. I acceded with
              pleasure to this proposition: I was fond of exercise,
              and Clerval had always been my favourite companion in
              the rambles of this nature that I had taken among the
              scenes of my native country.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>We passed a fortnight
              in these perambulations; my health and spirits had
              long been restored, and they gained additional
              strength from the salubrious air I breathed, the
              natural incidents of our progress, and the
              conversation of my friend. Study had before secluded
              me from the intercourse of my fellow-creatures, and
              rendered
              me unsocial; but Clerval called forth the better
              feelings of my heart; he again taught me to love the
              aspect of nature, and the cheerful faces of children.
              Excellent
              friend! how sincerely did you love me, and
              endeavour to elevate my mind, until it was on a level
              with your own. A selfish pursuit had cramped and
              narrowed me, until your gentleness
              and affection warmed and opened my senses; I became
              the same happy creature who, a few years ago, loving
              and beloved by all, had no sorrow or care. When
              happy, inanimate nature had the power of bestowing on
              me the most delightful sensations. A serene sky and
              verdant fields filled me with ecstasy. The present
              season was indeed divine; the flowers of spring
              bloomed in the hedges, while those of summer were
              already in bud: I was undisturbed by thoughts which
              during the preceding year had pressed upon me,
              notwithstanding my endeavours to throw them off, with
              an invincible burden.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Henry rejoiced in my
              gaiety, and sincerely sympathized in my feelings: he
              exerted himself to amuse me, while he expressed the
              sensations that filled his soul. The resources of his
              mind on this occasion were truly astonishing: his
              conversation was full of imagination;
              and very often, in imitation of the Persian and
              Arabic writers, he invented tales of wonderful fancy
              and passion. At other times he repeated my favourite
              poems, or drew me out into arguments, which he
              supported with great ingenuity.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>We returned to our
              college on a Sunday afternoon: the peasants were
              dancing, and every one we met appeared gay and happy.
              My own spirits were high, and I bounded along with
              feelings of unbridled
              joy and hilarity.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 4 | Chapter
          6 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>