<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1831v1.let2</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1239</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Letter II</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>
                        <name>Henry Colburn</name> and <name>Richard Bentley</name>
                     </publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1831</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">Rev., Corr. [2nd ed.]</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="ser">Bentley's Standard Novels series</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="no">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1831 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Letter II</p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>To Mrs. SAVILLE, England.</p>
         <p>Archangel, 28th March, 17--.</p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p> How slowly the time
                passes here, encompassed as I am by frost and snow!
                yet a second step is taken towards my enterprise. I
                have hired a vessel, and am occupied in collecting
                my sailors; those whom I have already engaged,
                appear to be men on
                whom I can depend, and are certainly possessed
                of dauntless
                courage.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>But I have one want which I have never yet been
              able to satisfy; and the absence of the object of
              which I now feel as a most severe evil. I
              have no friend, Margaret: when I am glowing with
              the enthusiasm
              of success, there will be none to participate my
              joy; if I am assailed by disappointment, no one will
              endeavour to sustain me in dejection. I shall commit
              my thoughts to paper, it is true; but that is a poor
              medium for the communication
              of feeling. I desire the company of a man who could
              sympathize with me; whose eyes would reply to mine.
              You may deem me romantic,
              my dear sister, but I bitterly feel the want of a
              friend. I have no one near me, gentle yet courageous,
              possessed of a cultivated as well as of a capacious
              mind, whose tastes are like my own, to approve or
              amend my plans. How would such a friend repair the
              faults of your poor brother! I am
              too ardent in execution, and too impatient of
              difficulties. But it is a still greater evil to me
              that I am self-educated:
              for the first fourteen years of my life I ran
              
              wild on a common, and read nothing but our uncle
              Thomas's books of voyages. At that age I became
              acquainted with the celebrated poets of our own
              country; but it was only when it had ceased to be in
              my power to derive its most important benefits from
              such a conviction, that I perceived the necessity of
              becoming acquainted
              with more languages than that of my native
              country. Now I am twenty-eight,
              and am in reality more illiterate than many
              schoolboys of fifteen. It is true that I have thought
              more, and that my day
              dreams are more extended and magnificent; but
              they want (as the painters call it) keeping
              ; and I greatly need a friend who would have sense
              enough not to despise me as romantic, and affection
              enough for me to endeavour to regulate
              my mind.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Well, these are useless
              complaints; I shall certainly find no friend on the
              wide
              ocean, nor even here in Archangel, among
              merchants and seamen. Yet some feelings, unallied to
              the dross of human nature, beat even in these rugged
              bosoms. My lieutenant, for instance, is a man of
              wonderful courage
              and enterprise;
              he is madly desirous of glory:
              or rather, to word my phrase more characteristically,
              of advancement
              in his profession. He is an Englishman, and in
              the midst of national and professional prejudices,
              unsoftened by cultivation, retains some of the
              noblest endowments of humanity. I first became
              acquainted with him on board a whale vessel: finding
              that he was unemployed in this city, I easily engaged
              him to assist in my enterprise.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The master is a person of an excellent
              disposition, and is remarkable in the ship for his
              gentleness
              and the mildness of his discipline. This
              circumstance, added to his well known integrity and
              dauntless courage, made me very desirous to engage
              him. A youth passed in solitude, my best years spent
              under your
              gentle and feminine fosterage, has so refined the
              groundwork of my character, that I cannot overcome an
              intense distaste to the
              usual brutality exercised on board ship: I have
              never believed it to be necessary; and when I heard
              of a mariner equally noted for his kindliness of
              heart, and the respect and obedience paid to him by
              his crew, I felt myself peculiarly fortunate in being
              able to secure his services. I heard of him first in
              rather a romantic manner, from a lady who owes to him
              the happiness of her life. This, briefly, is his
              story. Some years ago he loved a young Russian lady,
              of moderate fortune; and having amassed a
              considerable sum in prize-money,
              the father of the girl consented to the match. He saw
              his mistress once before the destined ceremony; but
              she was bathed in tears, and, throwing herself at his
              feet, entreated him to spare her, confessing at the
              same time that she loved another, but that he was
              poor, and that her father would never consent to the
              union. My generous friend reassured the suppliant,
              and on being informed of the name of her lover,
              instantly abandoned his pursuit. He had already
              bought a farm with his money, on which he had
              designed to pass the remainder of his life; but he
              bestowed the whole on his rival, together with the
              remains of his prize-money to purchase stock, and
              then himself solicited the young woman's father to
              consent to her marriage with her lover. But the old
              man decidedly refused, thinking himself bound in
              honour to my friend; who, when he found the father
              inexorable, quitted his country, nor returned until
              he heard that his former mistress was married
              according to her inclinations. "What
              a noble fellow!" you will exclaim. He is so; but
              then he is wholly uneducated: he is as silent
              as a Turk, and a kind of ignorant carelessness
              attends him, which, while it renders his conduct the
              more astonishing, detracts from the interest and
              sympathy which otherwise he would command.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Yet do not suppose, because I complain a little,
              or because I can conceive a consolation for my toils
              which I may never know, that I am wavering in my
              resolutions. Those are as fixed
              as fate; and my voyage is only now delayed until
              the weather shall permit my embarkation. The winter
              has been dreadfully severe; but the spring promises
              well, and it is considered as a remarkably early
              season; so that, perhaps, I may sail sooner than I
              expected. I shall do nothing rashly; you know me
              sufficiently to confide in my prudence and
              considerateness whenever the safety
              of others is committed to my care.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I cannot describe to
              you my sensations on the near prospect of my
              undertaking. It is impossible to communicate to you a
              conception of the trembling sensation, half
              pleasurable and half fearful, with which I am
              preparing to depart. I am going to unexplored
              regions, to "the
              land of mist and snow;" but I shall kill no
              albatross, therefore do not be alarmed for my safety,
              or if I should come back to you as worn and woful as
              the "Ancient Mariner?" You will smile at my allusion;
              but I will disclose a secret. I have often attributed
              my attachment to, my passionate enthusiasm for, the
              dangerous mysteries of the ocean, to that production
              of the most imaginative of modern poets. There is
              something at work in my soul, which I do not
              understand. I am practically
              industrious—pains-taking;—a workman to
              execute with perseverance and labour:—but
              besides this, there is a love for the marvellous, a
              belief in the marvellous, intertwined in all my
              projects, which hurries me out of the common pathways
              of men, even to the wild sea and unvisited regions I
              am about to explore. But to return to dearer
              considerations.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Shall I meet you again, after having traversed
              immense seas, and returned by the
              most southern cape of Africa or America? I dare
              not expect such success, yet I cannot bear to look on
              the reverse of the picture. Continue for the present
              to write to me by every opportunity: I may receive
              your letters on some occasions when I need them most
              to support my spirits. I love you very tenderly.
              Remember me with affection, should you never hear
              from me again.</p>Your affectionate brother,

              <p>ROBERT
              WALTON.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Letter I | Letter
          III &gt;</p>
         <p> How slowly the time
                passes here, encompassed as I am by frost and snow!
                yet a second step is taken towards my enterprise. I
                have hired a vessel, and am occupied in collecting
                my sailors; those whom I have already engaged,
                appear to be men on
                whom I can depend, and are certainly possessed
                of dauntless
                courage.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>