<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1818v3.ch5</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1231</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 5</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Lackington, Hughes, Harding, Mavor, &amp; Jones</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1818</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">The First Edition</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1818 EDITION : VOL. III</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 5</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p> WE had resolved not to go to London, but
              to cross the country to Portsmouth,
              and thence to embark for Havre.
              I preferred this plan principally because I dreaded
              to see again those places in which I had enjoyed a
              few moments of tranquillity with my beloved Clerval.
              I thought with horror of seeing again those persons
              whom we had been accustomed to visit together, and
              who might make inquiries
              concerning an event, the very remembrance of
              which made me again feel the pang I endured when I
              gazed on his lifeless form in the inn at ----.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As for my father, his
              desires and exertions were bounded to the again
              seeing me restored to health and peace of mind. His
              tenderness and attentions were unremitting; my grief
              and gloom was obstinate, but he would not despair.
              Sometimes he thought that I felt deeply the
              degradation of being obliged to answer a charge of
              murder, and he endeavoured to prove to me the
              futility of pride.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Alas! my father," said
              I, "how
              little do you know me. Human beings, their
              feelings and passions, would indeed be degraded if
              such a wretch as I felt pride. Justine, poor unhappy
              Justine, was as innocent as I, and she suffered the
              same charge; she died for it; and I am the cause of
              this—I murdered her. William, Justine, and
              Henry—they
              all died by my hands."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>My father had often,
              during my imprisonment, heard me make the same
              assertion; when I thus accused myself, he sometimes
              seemed to desire an explanation, and at others he
              appeared to consider it as caused by delirium, and
              that, during my illness, some idea of this kind had
              presented itself to my imagination, the remembrance
              of which I preserved in my convalescence. I avoided
              explanation, and maintained a continual silence
              concerning the wretch I had created. I had a feeling
              that I should
              be supposed mad, and this for ever chained my
              tongue, when I would have given the world to have
              confided the fatal secret. Yet still words like those
              I have recorded would burst uncontrollably from me. I
              could offer no explanation of them; but their truth
              in part relieved the burden of my mysterious woe.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Upon this occasion my father said, with
              an expression of unbounded wonder, "What do you mean,
              Victor? are you mad? My dear son, I entreat you never
              to make such an assertion again."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I am
              not mad," I cried energetically; "the sun and the
              heavens, who have viewed my operations, can bear
              witness of my truth. I am the assassin of those most
              innocent victims; they died by my machinations. A
              thousand times would I have shed my own blood, drop
              by drop, to have saved their lives; but I could not,
              my father, indeed I
              could not sacrifice the whole human race."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The conclusion of this
              speech convinced my father that my ideas were
              deranged, and he instantly changed the subject of our
              conversation and endeavoured to alter the course of
              my thoughts. He wished as much as possible to
              obliterate the memory of the scenes that had taken
              place in Ireland, and never alluded to them, or
              suffered me to speak of my misfortunes.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As time passed away I
              became more calm: misery had her dwelling in my
              heart, but I no longer talked in the same incoherent
              manner of my own crimes; sufficient
              for me was the consciousness of them. By the
              utmost self-violence, I
              curbed the imperious voice of wretchedness, which
              sometimes desired to declare itself to the whole
              world; and my manners were calmer and more composed
              than they had ever been since my journey to the sea
              of ice.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> We arrived at Havre on the 8th of
              May, and instantly proceeded to Paris, where my
              father had some business which detained us a few
              weeks. In this city, I received the following letter
              from Elizabeth:—</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"To VICTOR
              FRANKENSTEIN.</p>
               <p>"MY DEAREST FRIEND,</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It gave me the greatest pleasure to receive a
              letter from my uncle dated at Paris; you are no
              longer at a formidable distance, and I may hope to
              see you in less than a fortnight. My poor cousin, how
              much you must have suffered! I expect to see you
              looking even more ill than when you quitted Geneva.
              This winter has been passed most miserably, tortured
              as I have been by anxious suspense; yet I hope to see
              peace in your countenance, and to find that your
              heart is not totally devoid of comfort and
              tranquillity.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Yet I fear that the
              same feelings now exist that made you so miserable
              a
              year ago, even perhaps augmented by time. I would
              not disturb you at this period when so many
              misfortunes weigh upon you; but a conversation that I
              had with my uncle previous to his departure renders
              some explanation necessary before we meet.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Explanation! you may
              possibly say; what can Elizabeth have to explain? If
              you really say this, my questions are answered, and I
              have no more to do than to sign myself your
              affectionate cousin. But you are distant from me, and
              it is possible that you may dread,
              and yet be pleased with this explanation; and, in
              a probability of this being the case, I dare not any
              longer postpone writing what, during your absence, I
              have often wished to express to you, but have never
              had the courage to begin.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> "You well know, Victor, that our union
              had been the
              favourite plan of your parents ever since our
              infancy. We were told this when young, and taught to
              look forward to it as an event that would certainly
              take place. We were affectionate playfellows during
              childhood, and, I believe, dear and valued friends to
              one another as we grew older. But as brother and
              sister often entertain a lively affection towards
              each other, without desiring a more intimate union,
              may not such also be our case? Tell me, dearest
              Victor. Answer me, I conjure you, by our mutual
              happiness, with simple truth—Do
              you not love another?</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"You have travelled;
              you have spent several years of your life at
              Ingolstadt; and I confess to you, my friend, that
              when I saw you last
              autumn so unhappy, flying
              to solitude, from the society of every creature,
              I could not help supposing that you might regret our
              connection, and believe yourself bound in honour to
              fulfill the wishes of your parents, although they
              opposed themselves to your inclinations. But this is
              false reasoning. I confess to you, my cousin, that I
              love you, and that in my airy dreams of futurity you
              have been my constant friend and companion. But it is
              your happiness I desire as well as my own, when I
              declare to you, that our marriage would render me
              eternally miserable, unless it were the dictate of
              your
              own free choice. Even now I weep to think, that,
              borne down as you are by the cruellest misfortunes,
              you may stifle, by the word honour, all hope
              of that love and happiness which would alone restore
              you to yourself. I, who have so disinterested an
              affection for you, may increase your miseries
              ten-fold by being an obstacle to your wishes. Ah,
              Victor, be assured that your cousin and playmate has
              too sincere a love for you not to be made miserable
              by this supposition. Be happy, my friend; and if you
              obey me in this one request, remain satisfied that
              nothing on earth will have the power to interrupt my
              tranquillity.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Do not let this letter
              disturb you; do not answer to-morrow, or the next
              day, or even until you come, if it will give you
              pain. My uncle will send me news of your health; and
              if I see but one smile on your lips when we meet,
              occasioned by this or any other exertion of mine, I
              shall need no other happiness.</p>
               <p>"ELIZABETH LAVENZA.</p>
               <p>"Geneva, May 18th, 17—."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> This letter revived in my memory what I
              had before forgotten, the threat of the
              fiend—"I will be with you on your
              wedding-night!" Such was my sentence,
              and on that night would the dæmon employ every
              art to destroy me, and tear me from the glimpse of
              happiness which promised partly to console my
              sufferings. On that night he had determined to
              consummate his crimes by my death. Well, be it so;
              a
              deadly struggle would then assuredly take place,
              in which if he was victorious, I should be at peace,
              and his power over me be at an end. If he were
              vanquished, I should be a free man. Alas! what
              freedom? such as the
              peasant enjoys when his family have been
              massacred before his eyes, his cottage burnt, his
              lands laid waste, and he is turned adrift, homeless,
              pennyless, and alone, but free. Such would be my
              liberty, except that in my Elizabeth I possessed a
              treasure; alas! balanced by those horrors of remorse
              and guilt, which would pursue me until death.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Sweet and beloved
              Elizabeth! I read and re-read her letter, and some
              softened feelings stole into my heart, and dared to
              whisper paradisaical dreams of love and joy; but
              the
              apple was already eaten, and the angel's arm
              bared to drive me from all hope. Yet I would die to
              make her happy. If the monster executed his threat,
              death was inevitable; yet, again, I considered
              whether my marriage would hasten my fate. My
              destruction might indeed arrive a few months sooner;
              but if my torturer should suspect that I postponed
              it, influenced by his menaces, he would surely find
              other, and perhaps more dreadful means of revenge. He
              had vowed to be with me on my wedding-night,
              yet he did not consider that threat as binding him to
              peace in the mean time; for, as if to shew me that he
              was not yet satiated with blood, he had murdered
              Clerval immediately after the enunciation of his
              threats. I resolved, therefore, that if my immediate
              union with my cousin would conduce either to her's or
              my father's happiness, my adversary's designs against
              my life should not retard it a single hour.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> In this state of mind I wrote to
              Elizabeth. My
              letter was calm and affectionate. "I fear, my
              beloved girl," I said, "little happiness remains for
              us on earth; yet all that I may one day enjoy is
              concentered in you. Chase away your idle fears; to
              you alone do I consecrate my life, and my endeavours
              for contentment. I have one secret, Elizabeth, a
              dreadful one; when revealed to you, it will chill
              your frame with horror, and then, far from being
              surprised at my misery, you will only wonder that I
              survive what I have endured. I will confide this tale
              of misery and terror to you the day after our
              marriage shall take place; for, my sweet cousin,
              there must be perfect confidence between us. But
              until then, I conjure you, do not mention or allude
              to it. This I most earnestly entreat, and I know you
              will comply."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In about a week after
              the arrival of Elizabeth's letter, we returned to
              Geneva. My cousin welcomed me with warm affection;
              yet tears were in her eyes, as she beheld my
              emaciated frame and feverish cheeks. I saw a change
              in her also. She
              was thinner, and had lost much of that heavenly
              vivacity that had before charmed me; but her
              gentleness, and soft looks of compassion, made her a
              more fit companion for one blasted
              and miserable as I was.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The tranquillity which
              I now enjoyed did not endure. Memory brought madness
              with it; and when I thought of what had passed,
              a
              real insanity possessed me; sometimes I was
              furious, and burnt with rage; sometimes low and
              despondent. I neither spoke or looked, but sat
              motionless, bewildered by the multitude of miseries
              that overcame me.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Elizabeth alone had the
              power to draw me from these fits; her gentle voice
              would soothe me when transported by passion, and
              inspire me with human feelings when sunk in torpor.
              She wept with me, and for me. When reason returned,
              she would remonstrate, and endeavour to inspire me
              with resignation. Ah! it is well for the unfortunate
              to be resigned, but for
              the guilty there is no peace. The agonies of
              remorse poison the luxury there is otherwise
              sometimes found in indulging the excess of grief.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Soon after my arrival my father spoke of
              my immediate marriage with my cousin. I remained
              silent.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Have you, then, some
              other attachment?"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"None on earth. I love
              Elizabeth, and look forward to our union with
              delight. Let the day therefore be fixed; and on it I
              will consecrate myself, in life or death, to the
              happiness of my cousin."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"My dear Victor, do not
              speak thus. Heavy misfortunes have befallen us; but
              let us only cling closer to what remains, and
              transfer our love for those whom we have lost to
              those who yet live. Our
              circle will be small, but bound close by the ties
              of affection and mutual misfortune. And when time
              shall have softened your despair, new
              and dear objects of care will be born to replace
              those of whom we have been so cruelly deprived."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Such were the
              lessons of my father. But to me the remembrance
              of the threat returned: nor can you wonder, that,
              omnipotent as the fiend had yet been in his deeds of
              blood, I should almost regard him as invincible; and
              that when he had pronounced the words, "I shall be
              with you on your wedding-night," I should regard
              the
              threatened fate as unavoidable. But death was no
              evil to me, if the loss of Elizabeth were balanced
              with it; and I therefore, with a contented and even
              cheerful countenance, agreed with my father, that if
              my cousin would consent, the ceremony should take
              place in ten days, and thus put, as I imagined, the
              seal to my fate.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Great God! if for one
              instant I had thought what might be the hellish
              intention of my fiendish adversary, I would rather
              have banished myself for ever from my native country,
              and wandered
              a friendless outcast over the earth, than have
              consented to this miserable marriage. But, as if
              possessed of magic powers, the monster had blinded me
              to his real intentions; and when I thought that I had
              prepared only my own death, I hastened that of a far
              dearer victim.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> As the period fixed for our marriage
              drew nearer, whether from cowardice or a prophetic
              feeling, I felt my heart sink within me. But I
              concealed my feelings by an appearance of
              hilarity, that brought smiles and joy to the
              countenance of my father, but hardly deceived the
              ever-watchful and nicer
              eye of Elizabeth. She looked forward to our union
              with placid contentment, not unmingled with a little
              fear, which past misfortunes had impressed, that what
              now appeared certain and tangible happiness, might
              soon dissipate into an airy dream, and leave no trace
              but deep and everlasting regret.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Preparations were made
              for the event; congratulatory visits were received;
              and all wore a smiling appearance. I shut up, as well
              as I could, in my own heart the anxiety that preyed
              there, and entered with seeming earnestness into the
              plans
              of my father, although they might only serve as
              the decorations of my tragedy. A house was purchased
              for us near Cologny,
              by which we should enjoy the pleasures of the
              country, and yet be so near Geneva as to see my
              father every day; who would still reside within the
              walls, for the benefit of Ernest,
              that he might follow his studies at the schools.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In the mean time I took
              every precaution to defend my person, in case the
              fiend should openly attack me. I carried pistols and
              a dagger constantly about me, and was ever on the
              watch to prevent artifice; and by these means gained
              a greater degree of tranquillity. Indeed, as the
              period approached, the
              threat appeared more as a delusion, not to be
              regarded as worthy to disturb my peace, while the
              happiness I hoped for in my marriage wore a greater
              appearance of certainty, as the day fixed for its
              solemnization drew nearer, and I heard it continually
              spoken of as an occurrence which no accident could
              possibly prevent.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Elizabeth seemed happy; my tranquil
              demeanour contributed greatly to calm her mind. But
              on the day that was to fulfill
              my wishes and my destiny, she was melancholy, and
              a presentiment of evil pervaded her; and perhaps also
              she thought of the dreadful secret, which I had
              promised to reveal to her on the following day. My
              father was in the mean time overjoyed, and, in the
              bustle of preparation, only observed in the
              melancholy of his niece the diffidence of a
              bride.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>After the ceremony was
              performed, a large party assembled at my father's;
              but it was agreed that Elizabeth and I should pass
              the afternoon and night at Evian,
              and return to Cologny the next morning. As the day
              was fair, and the wind favourable, we resolved to go
              by water.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Those were the last
              moments of my life during which I enjoyed the feeling
              of happiness. We passed rapidly along: the sun was
              hot, but we were sheltered from its rays by a kind of
              canopy, while we enjoyed the beauty of the scene,
              sometimes on one side of the lake, where we saw
              Mont
              Salêve, the pleasant banks of
              Montalêgre, and at a distance, surmounting all,
              the beautiful Mont Blânc, and the assemblage of
              snowy mountains that in vain endeavour to emulate
              her; sometimes coasting the opposite banks, we saw
              the mighty Jura
              opposing its dark side to the ambition that would
              quit its native country, and an almost insurmountable
              barrier to the invader who should wish to enslave
              it.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I took the hand of
              Elizabeth: "You are sorrowful, my love. Ah! if you
              knew what I have suffered, and what I may yet endure,
              you would endeavour to let me taste the quiet, and
              freedom from despair, that this one day at least
              permits me to enjoy."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> "Be happy, my dear Victor," replied
              Elizabeth; "there is, I hope, nothing to distress
              you; and be assured that if a lively joy is not
              painted in my face, my heart is contented. Something
              whispers to me not to depend too much on the prospect
              that is opened before us; but I will not listen to
              such a sinister voice. Observe how fast we move
              along, and how the clouds which sometimes obscure,
              and sometimes rise above the dome of Mont
              Blânc, render this scene of beauty still more
              interesting. Look also at the innumerable fish that
              are swimming in the clear waters, where we can
              distinguish every pebble that lies at the bottom.
              What a divine day! how
              happy and serene all nature appears!"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Thus Elizabeth
              endeavoured to divert her thoughts and mine from all
              reflection upon melancholy subjects. But her temper
              was fluctuating; joy for a few instants shone in her
              eyes, but it continually gave place to distraction
              and reverie.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The sun sunk lower in
              the heavens; we passed the river Drance, and observed
              its path through the chasms of the higher, and the
              glens of the lower hills. The Alps here come closer
              to the lake, and we approached the amphitheatre of
              mountains which forms its eastern boundary. The spire
              of Evian shone under the woods that surrounded it,
              and the range of mountain above mountain by which it
              was overhung.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The wind, which had
              hitherto carried us along with amazing rapidity, sunk
              at sunset to a light breeze; the soft air just
              ruffled the water, and caused a pleasant motion among
              the trees as we approached the shore, from which it
              wafted the most delightful scent
              of flowers and hay. The sun sunk beneath the
              horizon as we landed; and as I touched the shore, I
              felt those cares and fears revive, which soon were to
              clasp me, and cling to me for ever.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 4 | Chapter
          6 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>