<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>Frankenstein the particulars of his formation <lb/>but on this point he was impenetrable. Are you <lb/>mad, my friend, said he, or whither does your <lb/>senseless curiosity lead you –Would you also <lb/>create for yourself &amp; for the world a
        dæmonical <lb/>enemy or to what do your questions <lb/>tend. Peace, peace; learn my miseries &amp; <lb/>do not seek to encrease your own.</p><p> <lb/>Frankenstein discovered that I detail <lb/>ed or made notes concerning his history he <lb/>asked to see them &amp; himself corrected <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>and augmented them <lb/>in many places but principally in  <lb/>giving the life &amp; spirit of the  conver <lb/>sations he held with his enemies–Since <lb/>you have made an account <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>said he I would <lb/>not that a mutilated one should go down to <lb/>posterity. </p><p> <lb/>Thus have ten days passed away <lb/>while I have listened to the strangest <lb/>tale that ever imagination formed. <lb/>My thoughts &amp; every feeling of my soul <lb/>have been drunk up by the interrest <lb/>for my guest <metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0169.01">^</metamark> I wish to soothe him <lb/>yet can I counsel one so infinitely miserable. <lb/> <lb/>so destitute of every hope of consolation to <lb/>live Oh no – the only joy he can now  know <lb/>will bewhen he composes his shattered <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>feelings to <lb/>peace &amp; death — Yet  he enjoys, <lb/>one comfort, the offspring of solitude <lb/>&amp; delirium — he  believed that when <lb/>in dreams he holds converse with his friends,  <lb/>&amp; derives from <lb/>that communion <lb/>consolation for <lb/>his miseries or excitement to <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>his vengeance</p></ab>