<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>hension of the murderer<unclear>.</unclear></p><p> <lb/>The magistrate listened  to me with
      at- <lb/>tention &amp; kindness – Be assured, sir, said he no
      pains <lb/>or exertions on my part  have been
      or <lb/>shall be spared to discover the villain</p><p> <lb/>I thank you, I replied, listen therefore
      to <lb/> <lb/>the deposition I have to make.  It is a indeed a <lb/>tale so  strange that I fear you
      would <lb/>not credit it were there not somthing in <lb/>truth which however wonderful forces <lb/>conviction. The story is too connected to be mis <lb/>taken for a dream &amp; I have no motive <lb/>for falsehood. My manner as I said this <lb/> was impressive but calm; I had
      formed <lb/>in my own heart the resolution to pursue <lb/>my destroyer to death &amp; this purpose quieted <lb/>my agony &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>provisionally reconciled me to life. I now <lb/>related my history briefly but with firmness <lb/>&amp; precision – marking dates with accuracy <lb/>and never deviating into invective or <lb/>exclamation. The magistrate appeared at <lb/>first perfectly incredulous but as I con <lb/>tinued he became  more attentive &amp; <lb/>interrested –I saw him sometimes shudder <lb/>with horror, at others a lively surprise <lb/>unmingled with disbelief was painted <lb/>on his countenance. When I had concluded <lb/>my  narration I said.</p><p> <lb/>This is the being whom I accuse <lb/>and for whose detection &amp; punishment <lb/>I call upon you to exert your whole
      power <lb/>It is your duty as a magist<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>rate and <lb/>I believe &amp; hope your feelings as a man <lb/>do not revolt from the execution <lb/>of those functions on this occasion.—</p><p> <lb/>This address caused a considerable</p></ab>