<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>the murderer of my brother. No sooner <lb/>did that idea cross my imagination than <lb/>I became convinced <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of its truth — my teeth chattered <lb/>and I was forced to lean against  a  <lb/>tree for support — The figure quickly passed <lb/>me and I lost it in the gloom. He <lb/> <lb/>therefore was the murderer! 
       <lb/> <lb/>Nothingin human <lb/>shape could <lb/>have destroyed <lb/>that fair <lb/>child. <damage agent="ink">He</damage> <lb/>was the <lb/>murderer! <lb/>I could not <lb/>doubt it. <lb/>The mere presence <lb/>of the idea <lb/>was an ir <lb/>-resistible <lb/>proof of the <lb/>fact — I thought
      of pur <lb/>sueing the devil, but <metamark function="insert">^</metamark> it would have been in vain for another <lb/>flash discovered him to me  <lb/>hanging
        among the rocks of the nearly perpendicular <lb/>ascent of the Mont-Salêve; he soon reached <lb/>the summit and dissapeared.</p><p> <lb/>I remained motionless the thunder <lb/>ceased but the rain still continued &amp; <lb/>the scene was inveloped in an<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>impenetrable dark- <lb/>ness. I revolved in my mind  <lb/> <lb/>I resolved in my mind the events which I  had, <lb/>untill now, sought to forget. <metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c56-0083.08">^</metamark> The appearance <lb/>of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the work of my own hands, alive at my bed side –  &amp; its
      departure. <lb/> two years <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>had now nearly elapsed since the <lb/>night  on which he first received <lb/>life, and was this his first crime – Alas! <lb/>I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>had turned loose in the world a depraved <lb/>wretch whose delight was in  <lb/>murder &amp; wretchedness; for had he <lb/>not murdered my brother?</p><p> <lb/>No one can conceive of the anguish I <lb/>suffered during the remainder of the</p></ab>