<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>and honor can never willingly continue to en <lb/>dure their present hardships.</p><p> <lb/><date>September 7<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi></date> <lb/>The die is cast. I have consented to return if we <lb/>are not destroyed. Thus are my hopes blasted– <lb/>by cowardice and indecision – I come back <lb/>ignorant &amp; dissa<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>ppointed –It requires  <lb/>more philosophy <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>than I possess to bear this injustice <lb/>with patience –</p><p> <lb/><date>September 12<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi></date> <lb/>It is past. I am returning to Archangel. I have <lb/>lost my hopes of utility &amp; glory –I have lost <lb/>my friend. But  I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>will endeavour <lb/>to detail the bitter circumstances to you, <lb/>my dear sister – And while I am wafted <lb/>towards England &amp; towards you I will not <lb/>despair. </p><p> <lb/>September 9<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi> The ice began to move <lb/>and roarings like thunder was heard <lb/>at a distance as the islands split <lb/>&amp; cracked in every direction. We were <lb/>in the most eminent peril – But as we <lb/>could only remain passive my chief at <lb/>tention was  occupied by my unfor <lb/>tunate guest whose illness encreased to <lb/>such a degree that  he was entirely <lb/>confined to his bed. The ice cracked be <lb/>hind us and was driven with force <lb/>towards the north – a breeze sprung <lb/>from that quarter –<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>andon the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the passage to <lb/>wards the south became free  <lb/>When the sailors saw this &amp; that their <lb/>return towards their native country <lb/>was apparently assured a shout of <lb/>tumutuous joy broke from them</p></ab>