<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/><head>Chap. 15</head> <lb/>We were not allowed to converse for any length <lb/>of time for the precarious state of my health rendered <lb/>every precaution <metamark function="insert">^</metamark> necessary that could ensure tranquillity.
        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.. Kirwin came in &amp; <lb/>insisted that my <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>strength should not be exhausted <lb/> by too much exertion. But <lb/>the appearance of my father was to me like <lb/>that of my good angel, and I gradually recovered my <lb/>health. As my sickness <unclear unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> quitted me I
      was absorbed <lb/>by a <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>gloomy &amp; black melancholy that nothing could dissipate– <lb/>The image of Clerval was for ever before me <lb/> <lb/>ghastly &amp; murdered – More than once the agitation <lb/>into which these reflections threw me into made my <lb/>friends dread a dangerous relapse</p><p> <lb/>Alas! Why did they pre<retrace hand="#pbs" cause="unclear">s</retrace>erve
      so miserable <lb/>and detested a life? It was surely that I <lb/>might fulfil my destiny which is drawing <lb/>to a close— Soon Oh very soon will death <lb/>extinguish these throbbings <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>releive me from this mighty weight <lb/>of anguish that bears me to the  <lb/>dust and in executing the award of jus <lb/>tice I shall also  sink to rest.
      Then <lb/>the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>appearance of death was distant although <lb/>the wish was ever present to my thoughts <lb/>&amp; I often sat for hours motionless &amp; speech <lb/>less wishing for some mighty revolution <lb/>that might bury me &amp; my destroyer in <lb/>its <unclear unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> ruins.</p><p> <lb/>The season of the assizes approached– <lb/>I had already been three months in prison <lb/>&amp;  although I was still weak &amp;
         <lb/>in continual danger of a relapse I was <lb/>obliged to travel nearly a hundred miles to <lb/>the county town where the court was held. <lb/>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Kirwin charged himself with every</p></ab>