<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/><head>Chap. 14<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">th</hi></hi></head> <lb/> <lb/>I was soon  introduced into the
      presence of the <lb/>Magistrate; an old benevolent man with <lb/>calm &amp; mild manners. He looked upon me <lb/>however with some degree of severity, and then <lb/>turning towards my conductors  he  asked who <lb/> appeared as wit- <lb/>nesses on this occasion. about half a dozen <lb/>men came forward and one being selected <lb/>by the magistrate <retrace cause="unclear">he</retrace> deposed that he had been <lb/>out fishing the night before with his son &amp; <lb/>his brother-in-law, Daniel Nugent, when <lb/>about nine o clock they observed a strong <lb/>northerly blast rising &amp; they accordingly put <lb/>in for port. It was a very dark night as <lb/>the moon had not yet risen; They did not <lb/>land at the harbour but, as they had been <lb/>accustomed, at a creek about two miles <lb/>below. He went first carrying a part <lb/>of the fishing tackle &amp; his companions <lb/>followed him at some distance. As he <lb/>was walking along the sands he struck his foot <lb/>against somthing &amp; fell all his length on <lb/>the ground; his comrades came up to assist <lb/>him &amp; by the light of their lantern they <lb/>discovered that he had fallen on the <lb/>body of a man who was to all appearance <lb/>dead.</p><p> <lb/>Their first supposition was that <lb/>it was the corpse of some person who had been <lb/>drowned &amp; thrown on shore by the waves, <lb/>But upon examination they found that <lb/>the clothes were not wet &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>even that the body <lb/>was not yet cold. They instantly carried <lb/>it to the cottage of an old woman <lb/>near the spot &amp; endeavoured <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>but in vain to restore it to life </p></ab>