<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>and when I m<damage type="inkblot">os</damage>t murmured would suddenly <lb/>extricate me from my seemingly insur <lb/>mountable difficulties— Sometimes when <lb/>nature overcome by hunger sunk under <lb/>the exhaustion a repast was prepared for <lb/>me in the desart that restored &amp; inspirited <lb/>me– The fare indeed was coarse such as the <lb/>peasants of the country ate but I <lb/>may not doubt that it was set there <lb/>by the spirits I had invoked to aid me. Often <lb/><damage type="inkblot">wh</damage>en all was dry  the
      heavens cloudless <lb/>&amp; I was parched with thirst – a slight <lb/>cloud would bedim the sky – shed the few <lb/>drops that revived me, &amp; vanish.</p><p> <lb/><space unit="chars" extent="5"/>I followed when I could the courses <lb/>of rivers but the dæmon generally avoided <lb/>these as it was here that the population <lb/>of the country chiefly collected– In other <lb/>places human beings were seldom <lb/>seen &amp; I generally subsisted <metamark>^</metamark>on the wild <lb/><add source="#c57-0160.01">animals</add> that crossed my path – I had money <lb/>with me &amp; gained the friendship of the <lb/>villagers by distributing it or bringing with <lb/>me some <metamark>^</metamark>food that I had killed <lb/>which after taking a small part I al <lb/>ways presented to those who had provided <lb/>with fire &amp; utensils.<metamark>^</metamark>for cooking My life as it passed <lb/>thus was indeed hateful to me &amp; it was <lb/>during sleep alone that I could taste <lb/>joy – Oh blessed sleep! often when most <lb/>miserable I sunk to repose &amp; my dreams <lb/> lulled <metamark>^</metamark>me even to rapture – The spirit <lb/>that guarded me had surely provided <lb/>these moments or rather hours of happi <lb/>ness that I might retain strength to</p></ab>