<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>The first nations whose names  are on
      record are Chaldea <lb/>and  India. Tradition has preserved wonderful accounts
      of their <lb/>progress in astronomical science. To them we owe the Zodiac <lb/>and many observations on the motions of the heavenly bodies  <lb/>which argue a much more accurate knowledge of that art <lb/>than any succeeding country could boast  uptil the time of Galileo <lb/>and Newton. But their wisdom passed away <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>from the earth leaving  faint <lb/>traces  among the Eyptians a race of men
         whose <lb/>minds <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>bear a considerable affinity with those of the <lb/>Chinese. Both these people arrived at a certain point in <lb/>refinement and knowledge and remained fixed: Superstiti <lb/>on and slavery clouded their perceptions and a hatred of <lb/>innovation, the never-failing attendant on a mind <lb/>which has learnt every thing from imitation and no- <lb/>thing from itself, was the natural consequence of the  <lb/>arbitrary  government they obeyed.
      Their history both on ac- <lb/>count of its antiquity and the genius of the nation presents <lb/>little more than a list of  names. Pride and a love of
      Con <lb/>quest was the distinguishing characteristic of their kinds <lb/>kings and  their magnificance <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>was displayed either by <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a bloody <lb/>and useless  warfare on the liberties of
      their neighbours <lb/>or by the  oppression and  destruction of their <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>own <lb/>subjects employed in the building of those famous pyra <lb/>mids, which,  being scarcely more than
      shapless masses <lb/>of brick <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>or stone, seem fitted to endure till the earth <lb/>itself shall  be no longer.</p><p> <lb/> The oppression of
      their own sovereigns fitted <lb/>the necks of theEgyptians for the yoke of a foreign prince <lb/>after a few generations they were subdued and remained for <lb/>ages swallowed up in the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>great Persian monarchy till after the <lb/>death of Alexander when they again
      became <lb/>anindependant nation till the overpowering <lb/>force of the Roman Empire reduced <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>them once more to the <lb/>condition of a Province. <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/><metamark function="insert"/><metamark function="insert"/><metamark function="insert"/> <lb/><damage/></p></ab>