<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/> <lb/> of my promise burst upon me; <lb/>I shudered to think that future ages might <lb/>curse me as their pest whose <restore type="smear_strikethrough"/> <lb/>had not hesitated to buy its own peace at <lb/>the price perhaps of the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>existence of whole human <lb/>race. I trembled, and my heart failed  <lb/>within me, when on looking up I saw <lb/>by the light of the moon, the dæmon at the  <lb/>casement. <lb/>A ghastly grin 
      wrinkled <lb/>lips, as he gazed on me where I sat. Yes, he had <lb/>followed me in my travels; he had loitered <lb/>in forests, hid himself in caves or taken <lb/>refuge in wide &amp; desart heaths &amp; he <lb/>now came to view my progress &amp; claim <lb/> <lb/>the fulfill <lb/>ment of  <lb/><metamark function="separate">_________</metamark>my promise; as I looked on him his countenance <lb/> <lb/>appeared to express the utmost extent
      of malice <lb/>&amp; treachery. I thought with a sensation <lb/>of  madness on my promise of crea <lb/>ting another like to him &amp; trembling <lb/>with passion  tore to pieces the thing <lb/>on which I was engaged – The wretch <lb/>saw me destroy the creature on whose <lb/>future existence he depended for <lb/>happiness and with a howl of devi <lb/>lish despair <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>&amp; revenge withdrew.</p><p> <lb/>I left the room &amp; locking the door <lb/>made a vow in my own heart never <lb/>to resume my labou<retrace cause="unclear">rs</retrace>; &amp; then with trem <lb/>bling steps I sought my own appartment <lb/>I  was alone.  None were near me to <lb/>dissipate the gloom and relieve me <lb/>from the most terrible reveries. Several <lb/>hours passed and I remained near my <lb/>window gazing on the sea. It was almost <lb/>motionless for the winds were hushed &amp;</p></ab>