<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>injury I would bestow every benefit upon him
      with <lb/>tears of gratitude at his acceptance. But <lb/>that cannot be; the human senses are  <lb/>insurmountable barriers to our union. <lb/>But mine shall not the submission of abject <lb/>slavery. I will revenge my injuries  if I <lb/>cannot inspire love I will cause fear <lb/>and chiefly towards you my arch-enemy because <lb/>my creator;  do I swear inextinguishable <lb/>hatred– I will work &amp; destroy nor finish <lb/>untill I desolate your heart so that you <lb/>curse the hour of your birth." A fiend <lb/>-ish rage animated him as he said <lb/>this; his face was wrinkled into contortions <lb/>too horrible for human eyes to behold; <lb/>but presently he calmed himself, &amp; <lb/>proceeded.</p><p> <lb/>I intended to reason. This passion <lb/>is detrimental to me, for you do not <lb/>reflect that you are the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>sole cause <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of its excesses.<unclear>.</unclear> If <lb/>any being felt emotions of benevolence <lb/>towards me I should return then an <lb/>hundred &amp; a hundred fold; for that <lb/>one creature's sake I would make peace <lb/>with the whole kind– But I now indulge <lb/>in dreams <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of bliss that cannot be realized. What <lb/>I ask of you is reasonable and moderate. <lb/>I demand a creature of another sex but <lb/>as hideous as myself. The gratification is <lb/>small but it is all that I can receive <lb/>and it shall content me. It is true we <lb/>shall be monsters cut off from all <lb/>the world but on that account we <lb/>shall be more attached to one another <lb/>Our lives will not be happy but they <lb/>will be harmless &amp; free from the
      misery <lb/>which I now feel. Oh! my creator make</p></ab>