<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>, which past misfortunes had impressed, <lb/>that what now appeared certain &amp; tangible <lb/>happiness might soon dissipate into an <lb/>airy dream &amp; leave no trace but deep &amp; ever <lb/>lasting regret.</p><p> <lb/>Preparations were made for the event. <lb/>Congratulatory visits <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>were received and all wore a <lb/>smiling appearance –I shut up  as well <lb/>as I could, in my own heart the anxiety that <lb/>preyed there and entered with seeming ear <lb/>nestness into the plans of my father although <lb/>they might only serve as the decorations of <lb/>my tragedy. A house was purchased for us <lb/>near Coligny by which we should enjoy <lb/>the pleasures of the country and yet be so <lb/>near Geneva as to see my father every <lb/>day– who would still reside within the <lb/>walls for the benefit of Ernest, that he <lb/>might follow his studies at the universi <lb/>ty.</p><p> <lb/>In the mean time I took every precau <lb/>tion to defend my person in case the <lb/>fiend should atack we— I carried <lb/>pistols &amp; a dagger constantly about <lb/>me and was ever on the watch to <lb/>prevent artifice &amp; by these means gain <lb/>ed a great<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>degree of tranquillity– And indeed as the <lb/>period approached the threat appeared <lb/>more as <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a delusion not to be regarded as <lb/>worthy to disturb my peace while the <lb/>happiness I hoped for in my marriage <lb/>wore an appearance of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>greater certainty <lb/>as <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the period of its solemnization<metamark function="insert">^</metamark> drew near and I heard it <lb/>spoken of every day as an occurence which <lb/>no  accident could <lb/> <lb/>possibly prevent.</p></ab>