<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>It was a lovely sight even to me poor <lb/> wretch who had never beheld
      aught <lb/>beautiful before. the silver hairs &amp; <lb/>benevolent countenance <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of  aged 
          cottager won my reverence <lb/>while <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the gentle manners of the girl enticed <lb/>my love. He played a sweet mournful <lb/>air which I percieved drew tears from <lb/>the eyes of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>his  amiable companion <lb/> <lb/>of which the old man took <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>no notice  it untill <lb/>she sobbed audibly – He  then
      pronounced <lb/>a few sounds and the poor creature leaving <lb/>her work knelt at his feet he rasied her <lb/>and smiled with such  kindness &amp; <lb/>love that I felt <retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">sensations of a peculiar &amp;
        overpowering</retrace> <lb/> <lb/>nature they were amixture<retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">of pain &amp; pleasure; such  as I had never experienced</retrace> <lb/><retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">either from</retrace><retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">hunger or cold</retrace>, <retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">or warmth or food and I</retrace> <lb/>from my stationwithdrew <lb/><retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">unable to</retrace> <lb/><retrace hand="#mws" cause="fix">bear</retrace>these <lb/>emotions</p><p> <lb/>Soon after this the young man returned <lb/>bearing on his sholders a  load of
      wood <lb/>the girl met him at the door helped <lb/>to relieve him of his burden and  <lb/>taking some of it into the  cottage <lb/>placed it on the fire;  then she
      and the <lb/>youth went apart into a nook of the cottage <lb/>and he shewed her a large loaf and a piece <lb/>of cheese.—She seemed pleased and
      went <lb/>into the garden for soome roots &amp; plants <lb/>which she placed in water and then upon <lb/>the fire–. She afterwards continued her work  <lb/>whilst <lb/>the young man went into the 
      garden <lb/>and appeared busily employed in digging &amp; pul</p></ab>