<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>death of William, the execution of Justine <lb/>the murder of Clerval &amp; now of my wife – even <lb/> <lb/>at that moment I knew not that my  only <lb/>remaining friends were safe from the malignity <lb/>of the fiend – my father even now might be <lb/>writhing under his grasp &amp; Ernest might be <lb/>dead at his feet – This reflection made me <lb/>shudder and recalled me to action. 
      I <lb/>started up &amp; resolved to return to Geneva <lb/>with all possible speed. There were no horses <lb/>to be procured and I must return by the <lb/>lake but the wind was unfavourable <lb/>and the rain fell in torrents. It was however <lb/>hardly yet morning and I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>might reasonably hope to arrive <lb/> by night –I hired a number
      of <lb/>men to row and took an oar myself for <lb/>I had always <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>experienced relief <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>from mental  torment in bodily exercise. <lb/>But the overflowing misery I now felt <lb/>&amp; the excess of agitation that I endured <lb/>rendered me incapable of any exertion–I <lb/>threw down the oar &amp; leaning my head <lb/>upon my hands gave way to every <lb/>gloomy idea that arose—If I looked up <lb/>I saw the scenes which were familiar <lb/>to me in my happier time and which I had <lb/>contemplated but the day <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>before in the compa <lb/>ny of her who was <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>now but a shadow &amp; a <lb/>recollection – tears streamed from my <lb/>eyes – I looked on the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>lake the <lb/>rain had ceased for a moment &amp; I  <lb/>saw the <damage type="inkblot">f</damage>ish play in the waters as I <lb/>had done  but  a few <lb/>hours before – they had then been observed by <lb/>Elizabeth. Nothing is so painful to the human <lb/>mind as great &amp; sudden change – The sun</p></ab>