<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>neck &amp; screamed aloud with agony &amp; terror. <lb/>Fortunately as I spoke my native tongue <lb/>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Kirwin alone understood <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>me. But my gestures <lb/>and bitter cries were sufficient, to affright <lb/>the other witnesses.</p><p> <lb/>Why did I not die? More miserable <lb/>than man ever was before why did I <lb/>not sink into rest &amp; forgetfullness? Death <lb/>snatches away many blooming chil<damage type="inkblot">dre</damage>n the <lb/> only hopes of their doating  parents; <lb/>How many brides &amp; youthful lovers have <lb/>been one day in the bloom of health &amp; <lb/>hope &amp; the next a prey for worms &amp; the <lb/>decay of the tomb! Of what materials was I <lb/>made  that I could thus resist so many <lb/>shocks which like the turning of the wheel <lb/> <lb/>continually renewed the torture.</p><p> <lb/>But I was doomed to live &amp; in two <lb/>months found myself <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>as awaking from a <lb/>dream, in a prison, stretched on a wretched <lb/>bed surrounded by gailors–turnkeys, bolts <lb/>&amp; all the miserable apparatus of a dungeon <lb/>It was morning I remember when I th<retrace cause="unclear">u</retrace>s awoke <lb/><damage type="inkblot">I h</damage>ad forgotten <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the particulars of what had happened &amp; only <lb/>felt as if some great misery had over <lb/>come me. But when I looked around <lb/>and saw the barred windows, &amp; the <lb/>squalidness of the room in which I was, <lb/>all flashed across my memory –&amp; I <lb/>groaned bitterly. This sound disturbed an <lb/>old woman who was sleeping in a <lb/>chair beside me. She was a hired nurse, <lb/>the wife of one of the turnkeys &amp; her <lb/>countenance expressed all those bad qua <lb/><space/>lities which <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>often characterize </p></ab>