<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>thize with him I had no right to refuse him <lb/>the small portion of happiness that I had it <lb/>in my power to bestow. You swear, I said, to <lb/>be harmless but have you not already shown <lb/>a degree of malise that would reasonably <lb/>make me distrust you? May not even this <lb/>be a feint that will encrease your triumph <lb/>by affording a wider scope to your revenge.</p><p> <lb/>How is this, cried he; I thought I had moved <lb/>your compassion, and yet you still refuse to <lb/> <lb/>bestow on  me the only benefit that can soften
      my <lb/>heart and render me harmless. If I <lb/>have no ties &amp; no affections hatred &amp; vice <lb/>must be my portion. The love of another <lb/>will destroy the cause of my crimes &amp; I shall <lb/>become a thing of whose existence every <lb/>one will be ignorant. My vices are <lb/> the children of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a forced solitude that I <lb/>abhor and my virtues will necessarily arise <lb/>when  I shall receive the sympathy of an equal. <lb/>I shall feel the affections <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of a living being &amp; <lb/>become linked to the chain of existence <lb/>&amp; events from which I am now excluded</p><p> <lb/>I paused some time <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>to reflect on all <lb/>he had related and the various arguments <lb/> <lb/>which  he had employed. I thought of  <lb/> the promise of virtues which he <lb/>had displayed on the opening of his exis <lb/> <lb/>tence; and the subsequent blight of all <lb/>kindly feelings by the detestation &amp; horror inspired by <lb/>protectors had manifested towards <lb/>him. His power &amp; threats were not <lb/>ommitted in my calculations; a crea <lb/>ture who could exist among the ice caves <lb/>of the glaciers &amp; hide himself from per <lb/>suit in the ridges inaccessible precepieces was</p></ab>