<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/><head>Chapter 13<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">rd</hi></hi></head></p><p> <lb/>I started forward &amp; exclaimed—Villain, before <lb/>you sign my death-warrant, be sure that <lb/>you are yourself safe. I would have seized <lb/>him but he eluded me and quitting the house <lb/>with precipitation in a few moments I saw him <lb/>in his boat which shot across the waters with <lb/>an arrowy swiftness &amp; was soon lost amidst the <lb/>waves.</p><p> <lb/>All was again silent; but his words rung in <lb/>my ears; I burnt with rage to pursue the <lb/>murderer of my peace &amp; precipitate him into <lb/>the ocean. I walked up &amp; down my room hastily <lb/>&amp; perturbed, my imagination conjured before <lb/>me a thousand images  to torment &amp; sting <lb/>me – Why  had I not followed him &amp; closed
      with <lb/>him in mortal strife–? But I had suffered <lb/>him to depart and he had directed his course <lb/>towards the main land; I shuddered to sup- <lb/>pose who might be the next victim sacri <lb/>ficed to his insatiate revenge – And then <lb/>again I thought of his words – "<hi rend="underline">I will be with</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">you on your marriage night</hi> That then <lb/>was the period fixed for the fulfillment <lb/>of my destiny – In that <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>hour I should die and at <lb/>once satisfy and extinguish his malic<retrace cause="unclear">e</retrace>.  <lb/> The prospect did <lb/>not not move me to fear yet when I thought <lb/>of my beloved Elizabeth; of her tears &amp; endless <lb/>sorrow when she should find her lover <lb/>so barbarously snatched from her –tears <lb/>the first I had shed for many months, stream <lb/>ed from my eyes &amp; I resolved not to fall before <lb/>my enemy without a bitter struggle.</p><p> <lb/>The night passed away &amp; the sun rose <lb/>from the ocean – My feelings became calmer <lb/>if it may be called calmness when the <lb/>violence of rage sinks into the depths of</p></ab>