<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>porary fit of despair – he had escaped me and I <lb/>must now commence a destructive &amp; almost <lb/>endless journey across the mountainous ices <lb/>of the occean – amidst cold that few of the <lb/>inhabitants could long endure &amp;  <lb/> <lb/>whih,  I the native of a genial &amp; su<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>nny climate <lb/> <lb/>could not hope to survive. Yet at the idea that the <lb/>fiend should  live &amp; be triumphant my <lb/>rage and vengeance returned &amp; like a <lb/>mighty tide overwhelmed every other fee- <lb/>ling. After  a slight repose during <lb/>which the spirits of the dead hovered round <lb/>me &amp; instigated me to toil &amp; revenge I <lb/>prepared for my journey.</p><p> <lb/>I exchanged my land sledge for <lb/>one fashioned for the ruggedness of the <lb/> <lb/>frozen ocean and purchasing a plentiful stock <lb/>of provisions I departed from land. How <lb/>many days have passed since then I know <lb/>not but I have endured misery which <lb/>nothing but the eternal sentiment  <lb/> <lb/>of a just revenge burning within my heart could have enabled <lb/>me to support. Immense &amp; rugged moun <lb/>tains of ice often  <lb/>barred up my passage and I often heard <lb/>the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>earthquake &amp; the thunder of the ground sea which threatened my <lb/>destruction but again a frost came  <lb/> <lb/>&amp; made the <lb/>paths of the <lb/>sea, secure. <lb/> – By the <lb/>quantity of provision <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>which I have consumed I should guess <lb/>that I had passed three weeks in this <lb/>journey – And despondency &amp; grief– often wrung bitter <lb/>drops from my eyes — Despair indeed had <lb/>almost secured her prey &amp; I should soon <lb/>have sunk under this misery– When once</p></ab>