<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>my letters with feverish impatience; If they <lb/>were delayed I was miserable &amp; overcome <lb/>by a thousand fears; &amp; when they arrived <lb/>and I saw the superscription of Elizabeth <lb/>or my father I hardly dared to read &amp; ascer  <lb/>tain my fate. Sometimes I thought that the <lb/>fiend followed me &amp; might remind me <lb/>by murdering my companion; When these <lb/>thoughts<metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0098.01">^</metamark> I would not quit Henry for a <lb/>moment but followed him as his shadow <lb/>to protect him from <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the fancied rage <lb/>of his destroyer. I felt as if I had commit <lb/>ted some great crime the conscious <lb/>ness of which haunted me. I was guiltless <lb/>but I had <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>indeed drawn down a horrible curse <lb/>upon<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>my head as mortal as that of
        crime <lb/>.</p><p> <lb/>I visited Edinburgh with languid <lb/>eyes &amp; mind &amp; yet that city might have <lb/>interrested the most unfortunate being. <lb/>Clerval did not like it so well as <lb/>Oxford for the antiquity of thelatter city was <lb/>pleasing to him. But the beauty &amp; regu <lb/>larity of the new town <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of Edinburgh delighted him; its <lb/>environs are also the most beautiful <lb/>in the world; Arthur's seat, St Bernards <lb/>Well &amp; the Pentland hills– But I was im <lb/>patient to arrive at the termination <lb/>of my journey.  We left Edinburgh in <lb/>a week passing through Cooper, St Andrews <lb/>&amp; Along the the banks of the Tay to Perth <lb/>Where our friend expected us; But I was <lb/>not in the mood to laugh &amp; talk with  <lb/>Strangers or enter into their feelings or plans</p></ab>