<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>"in her hiding places. They ascend into <lb/>"the heavens;– they have discoverd
      how <lb/>"the blood circulates, and the nature <lb/>"of the air we breathe.  They have <lb/>"acquired new and almost unlimi <lb/>ted powers;– They can command the <lb/>"thunders of heaven, mimick the <lb/>"earthquake, and even mock the <lb/>"invisible world with its own <lb/>"shadows."</p><p> <lb/>I departed highly pleased with <lb/>the professor and his lecture &amp; <lb/>paid him a visit the same evening. <lb/>His manners in private were even <lb/>more mild <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>&amp; attractive than in public. For <lb/>there was a certain dignity in his <lb/>manner during his lectures which <lb/>was replaced by the greatest  <lb/>affability and kindness in his own <lb/>house. He heard my little narration <lb/>concerning my studies with attention <lb/>smiled at the names of Cornelius <lb/>Agrippa and Paracelsus<metamark>X</metamark> but
      without <lb/>the contempt that Mr Krempe had <lb/>expressed to them. <metamark function="insert">^</metamark> <lb/><retrace cause="fix" hand="#mws" spanTo="#c56-0028.04"/><metamark function="displacement">^</metamark> <lb/>He said that <lb/>these were <lb/>men to whose <lb/>indefatigable zeal <lb/>modernnatural <lb/><retrace cause="fix" hand="#mws" spanTo="#c56-0028.05"/>philosophers were <lb/>indebted for most <lb/>of the foundations <lb/>of their knowledge <lb/> <lb/><retrace cause="fix" hand="#mws">They</retrace><metamark function="insert">^</metamark>had<retrace cause="fix" hand="#mws" spanTo="#c56-0028.06"/>left to <lb/>us, as an easier <lb/>task to give new <lb/>names, &amp; arrange <lb/>in conected classi <lb/>fications the <lb/>facts which they <lb/>to a great degree <lb/>had been the <lb/>instruments of <lb/>bringing to light. <lb/>The labours of <lb/>men of genius <lb/>however erroneously <lb/>directed scarce <lb/>ly ever failed. that <lb/>his lecture had removed my prejudice <lb/>against modern chemists and I request- <lb/>ed at the same time his advice <lb/>concerning the books I ought to procure</p></ab>