<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>The mames of <damage type="tear"/> a Simiramis, sovereigns of Babylon
      are <lb/>preserved by that bloody hallo with glory and victory always decora<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>its worshippers; but the effects of their conquest were but mom<damage type="tear"/>e <lb/>tary and gave way before the rapid advances of Cyrus whose <lb/>warfare conducted on principles of utility and benevolence <lb/><unclear unit="chars" extent="4"/>red through the lapse of many ages</p><p> <lb/>The memory of Cyrus is contemplated with peculiar <lb/>complacency by  most historians. His
      humanity and love <lb/>of justice distinguishes him those other conquerors to whom <lb/>ambition <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>is the ruling motive. Cyrus was educated in the <lb/>strictest simplicity, 
      early enured to fatigue and taught <lb/>after the manners of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>his age, to consider glory as the great &amp; <lb/>desirable bourne towards which every virtuous man ought <lb/>to direct his exertions But the natural  mildness of
      his <lb/>disposition let him the rather to seek for honour in the <damage type="tear"/> <lb/>don than in the punishment of his enemies; and his <damage type="tear"/> <lb/>often appeared to the fallen nation rather in the light of <damage type="tear"/> <lb/>blessing than a curse. Innumerable anecdotes are <damage type="tear"/> <lb/>of his virtue and wisdom by Xenephon but this history, <damage type="tear"/> <lb/>tunately must be regarded as a romance rather than the real <lb/>biography of the man: for although tradition might probably <lb/>preserve several  of the private actions of
      so <lb/>celebrated a prince. Yet the minuteness &amp; regularity of detail <lb/> which embellishes the
      narratives of the Cyropedia must <lb/>be solely attributed to the invention of its author and there <lb/>are no rational grounds by which we can regulate the ex <lb/>tent of credit due to the historian of  Cyrus. The
      anecdotes <lb/>however that are perserved of him chiefly relate to the generous <lb/>pardon of his prisoners of war, a mode of proceeding that <lb/>wonderfully facillitated his conquests so that he was still young <lb/>when he became possessed of the Babylonish Empire. From <lb/>this time he was principally occupied in the cares of govern <lb/>ment which he established on a very arbitrary 
      footing <lb/>leaving to his sucessors a despotic authority over a people <lb/><damage type="tear"/> whose courage was destroyed by slavery and</p></ab>