<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/> <lb/>Whence <lb/>did I come? <lb/>What was <lb/>my destination? these questions continually recurred but I <lb/>was unable to solve them</p><p> <lb/>The volume of Plutarchs lives which I <lb/>possessed contained the histories of the first <lb/>founders of the ancient republics– This book <lb/>had a far different effect upon me from <lb/> the letters of Werter. I learned <lb/>from  Werter's  imaginations despondency &amp; gloom; but Plutarch <lb/>taught me high thoughts—he elevated me above <lb/> the wretched sphere of my own reflections <lb/>to admire &amp; love the heroes of past ages.  <lb/>Many things I read surpassed my unterstanding <lb/>and <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>experience I had a very  confused know <lb/>ledge of kingdoms &amp; wide extents of country <lb/>mighty rivers and boundless seas. But I <lb/>was perfectly unacquainted with towns &amp; <lb/>large assemblages of men. The cottageof my protectors <restore type="smear_strikethrough"/> <lb/>the  only school inwhich I had studied human <lb/>nature — But this book <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>developed new &amp; mightier scenes of action <lb/> I read of men concerned in public <lb/>affairs governing  or masser <lb/>cring their speceis. I felt the greatest ardour <lb/>for virtue rise within me and abhor <lb/>rence for vice  as far
      as I understood  the <lb/>signification of those terms relative as they <lb/>were , as I applied them, to pleasure <lb/>and pain <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>alone.. Induced by these feelings  <lb/>I was of course led to admire peacable <lb/>lawgivers Numa, Solon &amp; Lycurgus more than <lb/>Romulus and Theseus. The patriarchal lives <lb/>of my protectors  caused <lb/>these impressions <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>to take a firm hold on my mind — perhaps if my first  <lb/> <lb/>introduction to  <lb/> <lb/>humanity  had been <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>made by a young soldier burning</p></ab>