<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>my speculations &amp; hopes are as nothing and like the <lb/>Archangel who aspired to omnipotence I am  <lb/>chained in an eternal hell. My imagination <lb/>was vivid yet my  powers of application were in- <lb/>tense – by the union of these qualities I 
      conceived <lb/>the idea and executed the  creation of
      a man– <lb/>Even now I cannot recollect without passion <lb/>my reveries while the work was incomplete –I <lb/>trod heaven in my thoughts – now exulting <lb/>in my powers – now  burning with
      the idea <lb/>of their consequences. From my infancy I was <lb/>imbued with high hopes and a lofty ambition <lb/>but how am I sunk – Oh my friend – if you had <lb/>known me as I once was  you would <lb/>not recognize me  in this <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>state of 
          degradation Despon <lb/>dancy rarely visited my heart a high destiny <lb/>seemed to bear me on, untill I fell oh, never <lb/>never <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>again to rise" .</p><p> <lb/>Must I lose this <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>admirable being? I have <lb/>longed for a friend, I have sought one who
      would sympathize <lb/>with &amp; love me. Behold on these desart seas <lb/>I have found such an one – but I fear I have gained him <lb/>but to know his value &amp; lose him –I would <lb/>reconcile him with life but he repulses the <lb/>thought. "I thank you," Walton," he said,  <lb/> for your kind intentions towards so <lb/>miserable a wretch – but when you speak <lb/>of new ties andfresh affections think you that any <lb/>can replace those which are gone? Can any man <lb/>be to me as Clerval was or any woman ano <lb/>ther Elizabeth. Even where the affections are <lb/>not strongly moved by any superior excel <lb/>lence the companions of our childhood al</p></ab>