<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>I was perfectly tranquil as to the consequences of the <lb/>affair.</p><p> <lb/>I entered the room where the corpse lay <lb/>&amp; was led up to the coffin. How can I describle<unclear>?</unclear> <lb/>my sensation. I feel yet parched with horror <lb/>nor can I ever reflect on that ter<retrace cause="unclear">r</retrace>ible <lb/>moment without shuddering &amp; agony that <lb/><damage type="inkblot">fa</damage>intly reminds of the anguish of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the recogni <lb/>tion. The trial, the presence of the <lb/>magistrate &amp; witnesses passed like a <lb/>dream from my memory when I saw <lb/>the lifeless form of Henry Cl<metamark>^</metamark>erval <lb/>stretched before me – I gasped for breath <lb/>&amp; throwing myself on the body I exclaim <lb/>ed. And have my murderous machi <lb/>nations deprived you  also my <lb/>dearest Henry of life— Two  <lb/>I have already destroyed; other victims <lb/>await their destinny – But you, Cl<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>erval, <lb/>my frend, my benefactor!—</p><p> <lb/>The human frame could no longer <lb/>support the <damage type="inkblot">ag</damage>onizing suffering that I <lb/>endured &amp; I was <damage type="inkblot">ca</damage>rried out <damage type="inkblot">of
        t</damage>he room <lb/>in strong convulsions.</p><p> <lb/>A fever succeeded to this. I lay for two <lb/>months on the point of death. My ravings, <lb/>as I afterwards heard were frightful. I called <lb/>myself the murderer of William  <lb/>,  of Justine &amp;
      of  Cl<metamark place="sublinear">^</metamark>erval. Sometimes <lb/>I entreated my attendants to assist me in <lb/>the destruction of the fiend by whom <lb/>I was tormented – and at others I felt the <lb/> <lb/>fingers  of the mosnster already grasping my</p></ab>