<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/><head>Chap. 18</head></p><p> <lb/><metamark function="insert">^</metamark>my present situation was <lb/>one in which all  <lb/>volun- <lb/>-tary <lb/>thought <lb/>was <lb/>swallowed <lb/>up and <lb/>lost. – I was hurried away by fury – Revenge alone <lb/>endowed me with strength, &amp; composure – It <lb/>modelled my feelings &amp; allowed me to be
      calculating <lb/>and calm at periods when otherwise delirium or death <lb/>would have been my portion. My first resolution was <lb/>to quit Geneva for ever.– My country which when <lb/>I was happy &amp; beloved was dear me <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>now in my adversity became hateful <lb/>I provided myself with a small sum of money <lb/> <lb/>together <lb/>with a few jewels which had belonged to my mother <lb/>&amp;  departed</p><p> <lb/>And now my wanderings began which are to <lb/>cease but with life – I have traversed a vast <lb/>portion of the earth and have endured all the hardships <lb/>which travellers in desarts &amp; barbarous countries <lb/>are wont to meet – How I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>have lived I hardly know <lb/> many times have I  stretched my failing limbs on the sandy plain <lb/>exhausted &amp; far from succour, &amp; prayed for <lb/>death – But revenge kept me alive – I dared <lb/>not die &amp; leave my adversary in being.—</p><p> <lb/>When I quitted Geneva my first  labour <lb/>was to gain some <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>clue by which I might trace <lb/>the steps <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of my fiendish enemy. But my plan was unsettled and I <lb/>wandered many hours around the confines <lb/>of the town uncertain what path I should pursue <lb/>As night approached I found myself at the <lb/>entrance of the cemetary<unclear reason="illegible">,</unclear> where William, Eliza <lb/>beth and my father reposed – I entered it &amp; <lb/>approached the  tomb which marked
      their <lb/>graves. Every thing was silent except the <lb/>leaves of the trees which were gentlyagitated by the <lb/>breeze — The night was nearly dark and the <lb/>scene would have been even to an unin <lb/>terested observeraffecting and solemn–the <lb/>spirits of the departed seemed to flit around and <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>to cast a <lb/> <lb/>shadow <lb/>which <lb/>was felt but seen notaround the head of the mourner.
        </p></ab>