<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>Septemb<damage type="inkblot">er</damage> 6<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> <lb/>A scene has just passed of such uncommon inter <lb/>rest that although it is highly probable that <lb/>the papers may never reach you, my dear <lb/>Margeret, yet I cannot forbear recording it. <lb/>We are still surrounded by <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>mountains of ice still in im <lb/>minent danger of being crushed in their
        conflict.— The cold is excessive &amp; <lb/> <lb/>many of my unfortunate comrades have already <lb/>found a grave admidst this scene of <lb/>desolation. Frankenstein has declined daily <lb/> in health a feverish fire still glim <lb/>mers in his eyes but he is ex<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>hausted &amp; <lb/>when suddenly rouzed to any exertion he <lb/>speedily sinks again into apparent lifelessness.</p><p> <lb/>I mentioned my last letter the fears <lb/>I had of mutiny. This morning as I sat <lb/>watching the wan countenance of my friend his <lb/>eyes half closed and his limbs hanging list <lb/>lessly I was rouzed by half a dozen of the <lb/>sailors who desired admission into the ca <lb/>bin they entered &amp; their leader adressed <lb/>me. He told me that he &amp; his compani <lb/>ons had been chosen by the other sailors <lb/>to come in deputation to me to make <lb/>a demand which in justice I could not <lb/>refuse. We were immured by ice &amp; <lb/>would probably never escape but they <lb/>feared that if, as was possible the ice <lb/>should be dissipated and a free passage <lb/>opened I should be rash enough to conti <lb/>nue my voyage &amp; lead them to fresh <lb/>dang<damage type="inkblot">e</damage>rs after they might happily have sur <lb/>mounted this. They desired therefore that <lb/>I should make a solemn promise  <lb/> if the vess<damage type="inkblot">e</damage>l s<damage type="inkblot">houl</damage>d be freed, <metamark>^</metamark>that I</p></ab>