<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>We had arrived in Englan <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>at the beginning <lb/>of October and it was now february; we according <lb/>ly determined to commence our journey <lb/>towards the north at  at the expiration of <lb/>another month. In this expedition we did <lb/>not intend to follow the great road to Edinburgh <lb/>But to visit Windsor, Oxford, Matlock &amp; the <lb/>Cumberland lakes resolving to arrive at the <lb/>completion of this tour about the end of <lb/>July. I packed my chemical instruments <lb/>&amp; the materials which I had collected resolv- <lb/>ing to finish my labours in some obscure <lb/>nook in the country.</p><p> <lb/>We quitted London on the 27 of <lb/>March and remain<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>ed a few days at Windsor <lb/>rambling in its beautiful forest. This was <lb/>a new scene to us mountaineers; The <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>majectic <lb/> oaks the quantity of
      game &amp; the  <lb/> flocks of lovely deer were all novelties <lb/>to us. From thence we proceeded to Oxford. <lb/>We were charmed with the appearance <lb/>of the town. The colledges are antient and <lb/>picturesque, the streets broard &amp; the lands <lb/>cape rendered perfect by the lovely Isis<unclear>.</unclear> <lb/>which  spreads into broard &amp; <lb/>placid expance of water &amp; runs south <lb/>of the town. We had  letters to several <lb/>of the professors who received <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>us with great <lb/>politeness &amp;  cordiality. We found that the <lb/>regulations of this university were much <lb/>improved since the days of Gibbon; But <lb/>there is still  in fashion a great
      deal <lb/>of bigotry &amp; devotion to established rules that <lb/>constrains the mind of the students &amp; leads <lb/>to slavish &amp; narrow principles of action.</p></ab>