<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>effect of these books <unclear reason="illegible">produced</unclear>. They pro <lb/>duced in me an infinity of new images &amp; ideas <lb/>that sometimes raised me to extacy but more <lb/> <lb/>frequently  sunk me to the lowest
      dejection. In the <lb/>Sorrows of Werter besides the interrest of its <lb/>simple and affecting story so many opinions are <lb/>canvassed and so many lights thrown upon what <lb/> had <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>hitherto been <lb/>to me obscure subects that I found <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>in it <lb/>a never end source of speculation. &amp;
        astonishment. The <lb/>gentle and domestic manners it described com <lb/>bined with lofty sentiments, and feelings <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>which had for their object something out of self accor <lb/>ded well with my experience among my pro <lb/>tectors. <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>and with the wants which were for ever alive within my
          own bosom. But I thought Werter himself a more <lb/>divine being than I had ever beheld, or imagined. His cha <lb/>racter contained no pretention but it sunk <lb/>deep –  The disquisitions upon
      death <lb/>and suicide  were calculated to fill me <lb/>with  wonder. – I did not pretend to <lb/>enter into the merits of the case yet I <lb/>inclined towards the opinion of the Hero <lb/>whose extinction I wept without  <lb/>precisely <lb/>
        understanding it. As I read however I <lb/>applied much <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>personally to my<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>own feelings &amp; condition I found my <lb/>self  similar
      yet <lb/><metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0038.07">^</metamark>strangely unlike the beings concerning whom <lb/>I read and to  whose conver <lb/>sation I was a listener – I sympathized <lb/> with &amp; partly understood them<unclear reason="illegible">–</unclear> but <lb/>I was unformed in mind. I was dependant <lb/>on none, &amp; related to none – "The path of my <lb/>departure was free"<unclear reason="illegible">!</unclear> and there was none <lb/>to lament my annihilation – My person <lb/>was hideous and my stature gigantic – What <lb/>did this mean? Who was I? What was I?</p></ab>