<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>tence, but that my vow was heard and I <lb/>was reserved for vengeance – The laughter <lb/>died away <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>when a well known and  <lb/>abhorred voice apparently close to my ear ad <lb/>dressed me in an audible whisper – I am sa <lb/>tisfied,  miserable wretch, you have <lb/>determined to live &amp; I am satisfied – I darted <lb/>towards the place from which the  sound <lb/>proceeded but the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>devil eluded my grasp. <lb/> suddenly the broard disk of the moon <lb/>arose and shone fully upon  <lb/>his ghastly &amp; distorted shape, as he fled
        with <lb/> more than <lb/>mortal speed.</p><p> <lb/>I persued <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>him;– &amp; for many months this <lb/> <lb/>pursuit has been my task. Guided by a slight clue <lb/>I  followed the windings of the Rhone <lb/>but vainly – The mediterranean appeared <lb/>and by a strange chance I saw the fiend <lb/>enter by night &amp; hide himself in a vessel <lb/>bound for the black sea – I followed him  <lb/>I knew the <lb/>vessel in which <lb/>he was concealed <lb/>&amp; he escaped me <lb/>I know not <lb/>how. <lb/> Amidst the wilds of Tartary
      &amp; <lb/>Russia although he still evaded me <lb/>I have ever followed in his track – Some <lb/>times the peasants scared by his horrid <lb/>Apparition informed me of his path <lb/>Sometimes he himself who feared that <lb/>if I lost all trace I should despair &amp; die <lb/>often left some mark to guide me –The <lb/>snows descended on my head &amp; I saw the print <lb/>of his huge step on the white plain –To <lb/>you are fast enterring on life, &amp; care is new to you &amp;<metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0159.08">X</metamark> how can <lb/>you understand what I have felt &amp; still feel. <lb/>Cold, want &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>fatigue were the least pains  <lb/>which I was <lb/>destined to endure; <lb/>I was cursed by some devil &amp; bore about <lb/>with me my eternal Hell – Yet still a <lb/>spirit of good followed &amp; directed my steps</p></ab>