<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/> <lb/></p><p> <lb/>It was evening when I arrived in the outskirts <lb/>of <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>that town and I retired to a hiding place among the <lb/>fields that surround it, to consider in what <lb/>manner I should apply to you. I was oppressed <lb/>by fatigue and hunger and far too unhappy to <lb/>enjoy the gentle breezes of evening or the
      prospect <lb/>of the sun setting behind the stupendous moun <lb/>tains of the Jura. At this time  <lb/>a slight sleep <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>relieved me which was disturbed by the <lb/>approach of a beautiful child who came <lb/>running into the recess I had chosen with <lb/>all the sportiveness of infancy—Suddenly as I <lb/>gazed on him anidea seized me – that <lb/>this little creature was  unpre <lb/>judiced &amp; had lived too short a time to have <lb/>imbibed <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a horror of deformity. If therefore I <lb/>could seize him &amp; educate him as my <lb/>companion &amp; friend, I should not be so <lb/>desolate in this peopled earth.  Urged by this <lb/>impulse I seized on the boy as he passed <lb/>and drew him towards me. As soon as he beheld <lb/>my form he placed his hand before his eyes <lb/>&amp; uttered a shrill scream. I drew his hand <lb/>forcibly from his face &amp; said Child, w<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>hat is <lb/>the meaning of this? I do not intend to hurt <lb/>you— listen to me. He struggled violently <lb/>Let me go he
      cried— Monster — ugly wretch <lb/>You wish to eat me &amp; tear me to pieces you <lb/>are an ogre, – let me go or I will tell my papa. <lb/>Boy said I – You will never see your father <lb/>again –you must come with me. He <lb/>burst into loud cries — hideous monster <lb/>let me go — My papa is a syndic he is <lb/>M. Frankenstien let me go you dare not <lb/>keep me. Frankenstein cried I — You belong then <lb/>to my enemy–To  him towards whom I have</p></ab>