<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>we have yet to wrestle for our lives but many <lb/>hard &amp; miserable hours will you spend <lb/>untill that period arrives"—</p><p> <lb/>Scoffing <unclear reason="case">D</unclear>evils! Again do I vow vengeance <lb/>again do I devote thee miserable fiend to <lb/>torture &amp; death never will I omit my search <lb/>untill he or I, perish. – And then with what <lb/>extacy shall I  join my Elizabeth &amp; <lb/>those who even <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>now prepare for me the <lb/>reward of my tedious &amp; 
      horrible <lb/>pilgrimage</p><p> <lb/>As I pursed <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>still my journey  to the <lb/>northward the snows <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>thickened, &amp; cold encreased  <lb/>in ae degree almost too severe to support. <lb/>The peasantry were shut up in their hovels <lb/>and only a few of the most hardy ventured <lb/>forth to seize the animals whom starvation <lb/>had forced forth to seek for prey. The rivers <lb/>were covered with ice and no fish could <lb/>be procured. The triumph of my enemy <lb/>encreased with the difficulty of my labours <lb/>One  inscription that he left was in <lb/>these words – Prepare – your toils only begin – <lb/><unclear reason="case">W</unclear>rap yourself in furs &amp; provide food for <lb/>we shall soon enter on a journey where <lb/>you sufferings will satisfy my everlasting hatred" My cou <lb/>rage &amp; perseverance were inspired with <lb/>new strength by these difficulties I resolved <lb/>not to fail in my purpose and calling <lb/>heaven to support me I continued with <lb/>unabated fervour to traverse immense <lb/>desarts untill the occean appeared at a <lb/>distance and formed the utmost boundary <lb/>of the horizon –Oh How unlike it was to the <lb/>blue seas of the south Covered with ice it <lb/>was only to be distinguished from land by</p></ab>