<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>with curiosity the press instituted by the author <lb/>of the history <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>of the troubles We re also shewn a room <lb/>which Frier Bacon <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the disoverer of gunpowder had <lb/>inhabited and which, as it was predicted, <lb/>would fall in when a man wiser than <lb/>that philosopher should enter it. A <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a short, round faced prating profes <lb/>sor who accompanied us refused to pass <lb/>the threshold; although we ventured inside <lb/>in perfect . security  <lb/>and probably <lb/>he might <lb/>have done the same</p><p> <lb/>Matlock, which was our next <lb/>place of rest, resembled to agreat degree <lb/>the scenery of Switzerland; But every thing <lb/>is on a lower scale &amp; the green hills <lb/>want the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>crown of distant white alps <lb/>which always attend on the piny  <lb/><restore type="underline" hand="#pbs"/> of our country. We visited <lb/>the wondrous cave &amp; the  little cabinets <lb/>of natural history where the curiosities <lb/>are disposed in the same manner <lb/>as in the collections at Servox &amp; Chamou <lb/>-nix. The latter mame made me tremble <lb/>when pronounced by Henry &amp; I hastened <lb/>to quit Matlock where the scenes were <lb/>thus ascociated.</p><p> <lb/>From Derby, still journeying north- <lb/>ward, we passed two months  <lb/><metamark function="insert">^</metamark>in Cumberland &amp; Westmorland. <lb/>I could now almost fancy myself among <lb/>the Swiss mountains; The little patches of <lb/>snow which yet lingered on the northern <lb/>sides of the mountains – the lakes &amp; the <lb/>dashing of the rocky  streams <lb/>were all  familiar &amp; dear sights <lb/><damage type="inkblot">to</damage> me. Here also we made some aquain</p></ab>