<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/><head>Chap. 10<hi rend="underline">th</hi></head> <lb/>Day after day, week after week passed away on <lb/>my return to Geneva and I had not the <lb/>courage to commence my work. I feared the <lb/>vengeance of the disappointed fiend yet <lb/>I I was unable to overcome my repugnance <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>to the task. <metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0074.01"><hi rend="sup">X</hi>1</metamark> <lb/>My health  which had hitherto declined <lb/>was now much restored, &amp; my spirits when <lb/>unchecked by the memory of my unhappy <lb/>promise, rose proportionably. My father <lb/>saw this with pleasure and he turned his <lb/>thoughts towards the best method of <lb/>eradicating the remains of my melancholy– <lb/>which every now and then would return <lb/>by fits &amp; with a devouring blackness over <lb/>cast the approaching <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>sunshine. At these <lb/>moments I took refuge in the most <lb/>perfect solitude: Alone <lb/>in a little boatI passed whole days
      on <lb/>the lake watching the clouds &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>listening to the rippling <lb/>of the waves, silent &amp; listless. But the fresh <lb/>air and bright sun seldom failed to <lb/>restore me to some degree of compo- <lb/>sure &amp;  on my return I met the <lb/> salutations of my friends with a <lb/>readier smile, &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a more cheerful heart</p><p> <lb/>It was after my return from one <lb/>of these rambles that my father calling <lb/>me aside thus a<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>ddressed me.</p><p> <lb/>I am happy to remark, my dear <lb/>son, that  you have  <lb/>resumed your former pleasures &amp; seem <lb/>to be returning to yourself. And yet <lb/> you are still
      unhappy &amp; still avoid <lb/>our society.  For some time</p></ab>