<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>despair. I left the house, the horrid scene <lb/>of the last nights contention and walked on <lb/>the beach of the sea which I almost regarded <lb/>as an insuperable barrier between me &amp; my <lb/>fellow creatures. Nay a wish that such was <lb/>the fact stole across me; I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>wished that I might pass my <lb/>life on this barren rock wearily it is true <lb/>but uninterrupted by any sudden shock <lb/>of misery –If I returned <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>it was to be  sa <lb/>crificed or to see those I most loved die <lb/>under the grasp of a dæmon whom I <lb/>had myself created. I walked about the <lb/>isle like a restless spectre seperated from <lb/>all it loved &amp; miserable in the seperation <lb/>When it became noon &amp; the sun rose <lb/>higher I lay down  on the grass &amp; was <lb/>overpowered by a deep sleep. I had been <lb/>awake the whole of the preceeding night, <lb/>my nerves were agitated &amp; my eyes inflamed <lb/>with watching &amp; misery. The sleep into which <lb/>I now sunk refreshed me &amp; when I awoke <lb/>I again felt as if I belonged to a race of <lb/>human beings like myself &amp; I began to <lb/>reflect upon what had passed with <lb/>greater composure —Yet still the words of <lb/>the fiend rung in my ears like a death <lb/>knell, they appeared like a dream, yet <lb/>distinct and oppressive as a reality.</p><p> <lb/>The  sun was far
      descended and I still <lb/>sat on the shore satisfying my ap<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>petite <lb/>which was become ravenous with an <lb/>oaten cake when I saw a fishing  boat <lb/>land close to me &amp; one of the men brought <lb/>me a packet; it contained letters from <lb/>Geneva &amp; one from Cl<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>erval entreating me <lb/>to  join him. He said 
      that nearly a</p></ab>