<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>the deep grief  <lb/>which this <lb/>scene had <lb/>at first <lb/>excited felt quickly gave <lb/>way to rage &amp; despair – They were dead and I lived – Their <lb/>murderer also lived &amp; to destroy him I must drag <lb/>out my  weary existence. I knelt on the earth <lb/>and with  quirering lips
      exclaimed – By the <lb/>Sacred earth <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>on which I kneel , by the shades <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>that wander <lb/>near me. By the deep &amp; eternal grief that <lb/>I feel I swear — And by thee oh night and by <lb/>the spirits that preside over thee I swear <lb/>to pursue the dæmon who caused this misery <lb/>untill he or I shall perish in a mortal <lb/>conflict – For this purpose I will preserve <lb/>my life — To execute this <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>dear revenge will I again <lb/>behold the sun &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>tread the green herbage of earth <lb/>which otherwise should vanish from my <lb/>eyes for ever – And I call on you spirits of <lb/>the dead &amp; you wandering ministers of ven <lb/>geance to aid me &amp; conduct me in my <lb/>work. Let the cursed &amp; hellish monster <lb/>drink deep of agony –  Let <lb/>him feel the despair that now torments <lb/>me.</p><p> <lb/>I had begun my adjuration with <lb/>solemnity &amp; an awe that almost assured <lb/>me that the shades of my murdered friends <lb/>heard &amp; approved my devotion – But the <restore type="smear_strikethrough"/> <lb/>possessed me as I concluded it &amp; <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>rage choaked <lb/>my utterance. I was answered through the <lb/>stillness of night by a loud &amp; fiendish laugh– <lb/>It rung my ears long and heavily; the <lb/>mountains re-echoed it and I felt as if <lb/>all Hell surrounded me with mockery <lb/>and laughing—Surely in that moment I <lb/>should have been possessed by frenzy <lb/>and have destroyed  my miserable exis-</p></ab>