<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p><handShift medium="pen" new="#mws"/> <lb/> <lb/></p><p> <lb/>Such was the history of my beloved cotta <lb/>gers. It <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>impressed me deeply, <metamark function="insert">^</metamark> I learned from <metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0037.02">^</metamark> to admire <lb/>their virtues &amp; to deprecate the vices of mankind. <lb/>As yet I looked <lb/>upon crime as a distant evil;  bene <lb/>volence &amp; generosity were ever present <lb/>before me – <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>inciting in me to desire to become an
                    actor in the <lb/>busy scene where so many admirable <lb/>qualities were called forth and displayed. <lb/>But  in giving  an account <lb/>of the progress of my intellect, I must not <lb/>omit a circumstance which
                occurred <lb/> in the beginning of the month <lb/>of August of the same year.</p><p> <lb/>One night during my accustomed <lb/>visit to the neighbouring wood where <lb/>I collected my own food and brought <lb/>home firing for  my protectors, I found <lb/>on the ground a leathern portmanteau <lb/>containing several articles of dress &amp; some <lb/>books. I  eagerly seized the prize
            &amp; <lb/>returned with it to my hovel. The books <lb/>were fortunately written in the language  <lb/>the elements <lb/>of which <lb/>I had learned at the cottage; they consisted <lb/>of "Paradise Lost" — a volume of Plutarchs <lb/>lives and the Sorrows of Werter –  <lb/>I the possessionof these treasures <lb/><metamark function="displacement" xml:id="c57-0037.08">X</metamark> I could  continually study <lb/>and exercise my mind upon <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>thesehistories when my <lb/>friends were employed in their ordinary <lb/>occupations. I can hardly describe to you the</p></ab>