<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>after the poor animals that carried me  had <lb/>with incredible toil gained the summit of an ice <lb/>mountain  they paused to rest and one unable to <lb/>move <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>sinking under the toil died—I  viewed the
      expance <lb/>before, with anguish; when suddenly my eye was <lb/>arrested by a dark speck on <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the dusky plain – I strained my <lb/>sight to discover what  it could be &amp; uttered a wild <lb/>cry of extacy when I distinguished a sledge dogs &amp; <lb/><metamark function="insert">^</metamark>the distorted proportions of a well known form <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>within. Oh  with what <lb/>a burning gush did hope revisit my heart – warm <lb/>tears filled my eyes which I hastily wiped away <lb/>that they might not <metamark function="insert">^</metamark> intercept the view I had of the <lb/>fiend. I followed— but still the dew dimmed my <lb/>sight untill giving way to the emotions that <lb/>oppressed me I wept aloud.</p><p> <lb/>But this was not the time for delay <lb/>I disincumbered the dogs of their dead compa <lb/>nion  gave them a plentiful portion of <lb/>food and after an hours repose which was abso <lb/>lutely necessary &amp; yet which was bitterly irksome <lb/>to me I continued my path — The sledge was <lb/>still visible nor did I again lose sight of it <lb/>except at the moments when for a short time <lb/>some ice rock concealed it <metamark function="insert">^</metamark> with its
          intervening crags. I indeed perceptibly <lb/>gained on the object of my pursuit. And after about  ano <lb/>ther days journey I beheld myself at no <lb/>more than half a 
          mile distant.  <lb/>My heart bounded within me – But <lb/>now when I appeared almost within grasp <lb/>of my enemy my hopes were suddenly extinguished <lb/>and I  lost all trace of him more <lb/>utterly than I had ever done before A ground <lb/>sea was heard – the thunder of its<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>progress as  the wa <lb/>ters rolled &amp; swelled beneath me became every <lb/>moment more ominous &amp; terrific —I pressed
      on <lb/><unclear unit="chars" extent="1"/> but in
        vain – The wind arose the sea roared</p></ab>