<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>and my eyes were shut to the horror of my <lb/>proceedings. But now I went to it in cold <lb/>blood and my heart often sicken<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>ed at the <lb/>work of my hands.</p><p> <lb/>Thus situated; employed in the most <lb/>detestable occupation, in <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a solitude where <lb/>nothing could for an instant call my attention <lb/> from the actual scene
      in which I <lb/>was engaged, my spirits were unequal, I <lb/>became restless &amp; nervous– Every moment I <lb/>feared to meet  my persecutor. Sometimes <lb/>I sat with my eyes fixed on the ground fear- <lb/>ing to raise them lest they should meet <lb/>the object which I so much dreaded to behold I feared <lb/> <lb/>to wander from the sight of my fellow crea <lb/>tures lest when alone  He should come <lb/>to claim his companion.  In the <lb/>mean time I worked on &amp; my  labour <lb/>was already considerably advanced– I looked <lb/>with pleasure towards <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>its completion yet <lb/>freedom from the curse I endured was <lb/>a joy I never dared promise myself— <lb/><note>Finish Chap. 2
        here</note></p><p> <lb/>One evening I sat in my  <lb/>workshop, the sun had set &amp; the moon <lb/>was just rising from the sea — I had not <lb/>light sufficient for my employment and I sat <lb/>idle  in <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a pause of consideration <lb/>of whether I should leave my labour for <lb/>the night or hasten its conclusion by an <lb/>unremitting attention to it. As I sat a train <lb/>of reflection occurred to me which led to me <lb/>consider the effects of what I was now <lb/>doing. <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>three years before I had been engaged <lb/>in the same manner &amp; had created a <lb/>fiend whose unparralelled barbarity had</p></ab>