<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/> <lb/>for happiness; my beloved cousin &amp; the blue lake which had <lb/>been so dear to me, in early childhood, but my <lb/>general <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>state of feeling was <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a torpor in which a prison <lb/>was as welcome a  residence as the
      divi <lb/>nest scene in nature &amp; these fits were seldom <lb/>interrupted but by paroxisms of anguish &amp; <lb/>despair – At these moments I often endeavour <lb/>ed to put an end to the existence I loathed <lb/>&amp; it required unceasing attendance &amp; vigilance <lb/>to restrain me from committing some dreadful <lb/>act of violence. I remember as I quitted the <lb/>prison I heard one of the men say – He may be <lb/>innocent of the murder but he has certainly <lb/>a bad conscience.–</p><p> <lb/>These words struck me; a bad conscience, <lb/>yes surely I had one – William, Justine &amp; Cl<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>erval <lb/>had died <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>through my infernal machinations <lb/> And whose <lb/>death, cried I, is to finish the tragedy — Ah! my <lb/>father do not let us remain in this wretched <lb/>country– Take me where I can forget myself, <lb/>my existence &amp; all the world. My father easily <lb/>acceeded to my desire &amp; after having taken <lb/>leave of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Kirwin we hastened to Dublin. <lb/>I felt as if I was relieved from a heavy weight <lb/>when the packet set sail with a fair wind <lb/>from Ireland and I had quitted for ever the <lb/>country which had been to me the scene <lb/>of so much misery – It was midnight, my <lb/>father slept below in the cabin &amp; I lay on <lb/>the deck looking at the stars &amp; listening to <lb/>the dashing of the waves –I hailed the darkness <lb/>that shut Ireland from my sight &amp; <lb/>my pulse beat with a feverish joy when <lb/>I reflected that I should soon see Geneva <lb/>The passed appeared to me <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>in the light of a fright</p></ab>