<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/><head>Chap  2.</head></p><p> <lb/>London was  our present point <lb/>of rest; we determined to remain several <lb/>months in this wonderful &amp; celebrated city. <lb/>Cl<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>erval desired for the intercourse of <lb/>the men of genius &amp; talent who flou <lb/>rished at that time; but this was, with <lb/>me, a secondary object; I was princi <lb/>pally occupied with the means of obtaining <lb/>the information necessary for the comple <lb/>tion of my promise and quickly availed <lb/>myself of the letters of introduction that <lb/>I had brought with me addressed to <lb/>the <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>most distinguished <lb/>natural philosophers. If this journey had <lb/>taken place during my days of study &amp; <lb/>happiness it would have afforded me <lb/>inexpressible  pleasure. But a <lb/>blight had come over my existence &amp; I only <lb/>visited these people for the sake of the <lb/>information they might give me on <lb/>the subject in which I was so deeply <lb/>interrested. Company was irksome to me; <lb/>when alone I could fill my mind with the <lb/>sights of heaven &amp; earth; the voice of <damage type="tear"/> <lb/> <lb/>Henry soothed me &amp; I could cheat myself into a<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>transitory peace. But busy, uninterresting,<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>joyous faces brought back despair to my<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>heart. I saw an insurmountable barrie<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>placed between me &amp; my fellow men; thi<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>barrier was sealed with the blood of<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>William and Justine, and to reflect on<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>those events filled my soul with anguish<damage type="tear"/> <lb/>But in Clerval I saw the image of my <lb/>former self; he was inquisitive &amp; anxious</p></ab>