<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>are consumed you sit amid the ruins &amp; lament <lb/>their fall. Hypocritical  Fiend! If he whom <lb/>you lament still lived still would you <lb/>persue him with your accursed vengeance. <lb/>It is not pity that you feel – it is sorrow that <lb/>your power of mischief is  anihilated</p><p> <lb/> It is not thus, said
      the dæmon, &amp; <lb/>yet <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>such must be yourimpression since such <lb/>appears to have been the purport of my <lb/>actions. But I do not seek <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>a fellow feeling in <lb/>my misery–I feel it deeply &amp; truly &amp; for sy <lb/>mpathy that I may never find. When <lb/>I first sought it– it was the love of virtue, <lb/>it was  feelings of happiness &amp; content <lb/>that I wished to be participated. But <lb/>now that virtue is to me merely a sha <lb/>dow and happiness &amp; content <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>are turned <lb/>into despair shall I seek for sympathy <lb/>in that. No–I am content to suffer <lb/>alone while I do suffer – And when I <lb/>die I am satisfied that  hatred <lb/>&amp; opprobrium should load my memory. <lb/>Once my fancy was soothed by dreams <lb/>of virtue of fame &amp; of enjoyment. Once <lb/>I hoped to meet with one who pardoning <lb/>my outward form <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>would love me for the <lb/>excellent qualities with which I was so eminently  <lb/>capable <lb/>of bringing <lb/>forth. – I <lb/>was then filled with high thoughts of <lb/>honour &amp; self devotion – But now  <lb/>vice <lb/>has sunk me below the meanest  <lb/>animal– no crimes can equal mine <lb/>&amp; when I call over the frightful cata <lb/>logue I cannot believe that I am he <lb/><damage unit="chars" extent="4" type="inkblot"/>whose thoughts were once filled with</p></ab>