<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><ab xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="surface"><p> <lb/>would instantly direct my course to  <lb/>Archangel.</p><p> <lb/>This speech tro<metamark function="insert">^</metamark>ubled  me. I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>had not despaired <lb/>nor had I yet conceived the idea of returning <lb/>if set free. Yet could I <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>in justice, or even in <lb/>possibility refuse thisdemand. I hesitated be- <lb/>fore I answered when Frankenstein who had <lb/> at first been silent &amp; indeed <lb/> <lb/>appeared hardly to have force enough to attend <lb/>now rouzed himself. His eyes sparkled <lb/>and his cheek flushed was with momentary <lb/>vigour.  Turning to the
      men he <lb/>said; What do you mean? What do <lb/>you demand of your captain? Are <lb/>you then so easily turned from your <lb/>design? Did you ot 
      call this <lb/>a glorious expedition &amp; wherefore was it glorious? <lb/>Not because the way was smooth <lb/>&amp; placid as a southern sea but <lb/>because it was full of dangers &amp; <lb/>terror – because at every new incident <lb/>your fortitude was to be called forth &amp; your <lb/>courage exhibited– Because death &amp; danger <lb/>surrounded you &amp; these you were to <lb/>brave &amp; overcome. For this was it a glori <lb/>ous; for this was it <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>an honorable under <lb/>taking. You were to <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>be hereafter hailed <lb/>as the benefactors of your species – <unclear reason="case">Y</unclear>our names <lb/>adored as the brave men who encoun <lb/>tered death for honor &amp; the benefit of mankind. – And now <lb/>behold with the first imagination of danger –or if <lb/>you will – The first mighty &amp; terrific <lb/>trial  of your courage you <lb/>shrink away &amp; are content to be handed</p></ab>