<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p14"/>I feel pleasure in dwelling on the recollections of childhood, before misfortune had
    tainted my mind, and changed its bright visions of extensive usefulness into gloomy and
    narrow reflections upon self. But, in drawing the picture of my early days, I must not
    omit to record those events which led, by in<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_063" n="051"/>sensible steps to my after tale of misery: for when I would account to myself for the
    birth of that passion, which afterwards ruled my destiny, I find it arise, like a
    mountain river, from ignoble and almost forgotten sources; but, swelling as it
    proceeded, it became the torrent which, in its course, has swept away all my hopes and
    joys.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p14"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p15"/>Natural philosophy is the genius that has regulated my fate; I desire therefore, in
    this narration, to state those facts which led to my predilection for that science. When
    I was thirteen years of age, we all went on a party of pleasure to the baths near
    Thonon: the inclemency of the weather obliged us to remain a day confined to the inn. In
    this house I chanced to find a volume of the works of Cornelius Agrippa. I opened it
    with apathy; the theory which he attempts to demonstrate, and the <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_064" n="052"/>wonderful facts which he relates, soon changed this
    feeling into enthusiasm. A new light seemed to dawn upon my mind; and, bounding with
    joy, I communicated my discovery to my father. I cannot help remarking here the many
    opportunities instructors possess of directing the attention of their pupils to useful
    knowledge, which they utterly neglect. My father looked carelessly at the title-page of
    my book, and said, “Ah! Cornelius Agrippa! My dear Victor, do not waste your time upon
    this; it is sad trash.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p15"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p16"/>If, instead of this remark, my father had taken the pains to explain to me, that the
    principles of Agrippa had been entirely exploded, and that a modern system of science
    had been introduced, which possessed much greater powers than the ancient, because the
    powers of the latter were chimerical, while <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_065" n="053"/>those
    of the former were real and practical; under such circumstances, I should certainly have
    thrown Agrippa aside, and, with my imagination warmed as it was, should probably have
    applied myself to the more rational theory of chemistry which has resulted from modern
    discoveries. It is even possible, that the train of my ideas would never have received
    the fatal impulse that led to my ruin. But the cursory glance my father had taken of my
    volume by no means assured me that he was acquainted with its contents; and I continued
    to read with the greatest avidity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p16"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p17"/>When I returned home, my first care was to procure the whole works of this author, and
    afterwards of Paracelsus and Albertus Magnus. I read and studied the wild fancies of
    these writers with delight; they appeared to me trea<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_066" n="054"/>sures known to few beside myself; and although I often wished to communicate
    these secret stores of knowledge to my father, yet his indefinite censure of my
    favourite Agrippa always withheld me. I disclosed my discoveries to Elizabeth,
    therefore, under a promise of strict secrecy; but she did not interest herself in the
    subject, and I was left by her to pursue my studies alone.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p17"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p18"/>It may appear very strange, that a disciple of Albertus Magnus should arise in the
    eighteenth century; but our family was not scientifical, and I had not attended any of
    the lectures given at the schools of Geneva. My dreams were therefore undisturbed by
    reality; and I entered with the greatest diligence into the search of the philosopher’s
    stone and the elixir of life. But the latter obtained my most undi<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_067" n="055"/>vided attention: wealth was an inferior object; but what glory would
    attend the discovery, if I could banish disease from the human frame, and render man
    invulnerable to any but a violent death!<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p18"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p19"/>Nor were these my only visions. The raising of ghosts or devils was a promise liberally
    accorded by my favourite authors, the fulfilment of which I most eagerly sought; and if
    my incantations were always unsuccessful, I attributed the failure rather to my own
    inexperience and mistake, than to a want of skill or fidelity in my instructors.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p19"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p20"/>The natural phænomena that take place every day before our eyes did not escape my
    examinations. Distillation, and the wonderful effects of steam, processes of which my
    favourite authors were utterly ignorant, excited my astonishment; but my utmost wonder
    was <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_068" n="056"/>engaged by some experiments on an air-pump,
    which I saw employed by a gentleman whom we were in the habit of visiting.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p20"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p21"/>The ignorance of the early philosophers on these and several other points served to
    decrease their credit with me: but I could not entirely throw them aside, before some
    other system should occupy their place in my mind.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p21"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p22"/>When I was about fifteen years old, we had retired to our house near Belrive, when we
    witnessed a most violent and terrible thunder-storm. It advanced from behind the
    mountains of Jura; and the thunder burst at once with frightful loudness from various
    quarters of the heavens. I remained, while the storm lasted, watching its progress with
    curiosity and delight. As I stood at the door, on a sudden I beheld a stream of fire
    issue from an old and beautiful oak, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_069" n="057"/>which stood
    about twenty yards from our house; and so soon as the dazzling light vanished, the oak
    had disappeared, and nothing remained but a blasted stump. When we visited it the next
    morning, we found the tree shattered in a singular manner. It was not splintered by the
    shock, but entirely reduced to thin ribbands of wood. I never beheld any thing so utterly
    destroyed.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p22"/>
</xml>
