<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p6"/>When my father became a husband and a parent, he found his time so occupied by the
    duties of his new situation, that he relinquished many of his public employments, and
    devoted himself to the education of his children. Of these I was the eldest, and the
    destined suc<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_063" n="44"/>cessor to all his labours and utility. No
    creature could have more tender parents than mine. My improvement and health were their
    constant care, especially as I remained for several years their only child. But before I
    continue my narrative, I must record an incident which took place when I was four years
    of age.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p6"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p7"/>My father had a sister, whom he tenderly loved, and who had married early in life an
    Italian gentleman. Soon after her marriage, she had accompanied her husband into his
    native country, and for some years my father had very little communication with her.
    About the time I mentioned she died; and a few months afterwards he received a letter
    from her husband, acquainting him with his intention of marrying an Italian lady, and
    requesting my father to take charge of the in<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_064" n="45"/>fant
    Elizabeth, the only child of his deceased sister. “It is my wish,” he said, "that you
    should consider her as your own daughter, and educate her thus. Her mother's fortune is
    secured to her, the documents of which I will commit to your keeping. Reflect upon this
    proposition; and decide whether you would prefer educating your niece yourself to her
    being brought up by a stepmother.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p7"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p8"/>My father did not hesitate, and immediately went to Italy, that he might accompany the
    little Elizabeth to her future home. I have often heard my mother say, that she was at
    that time the most beautiful child she had ever seen, and showed signs even then of a
    gentle and affectionate disposition. These indications, and a desire to bind as closely
    as possible the ties of domestic love, determined my mother to consider Elizabeth <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_065" n="46"/>as my future wife; a design which she never found reason
    to repent.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p8"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9"/>From this time Elizabeth Lavenza became my playfellow, and, as we grew older, my
    friend. She was docile and good tempered, yet gay and playful as a summer insect.
    Although she was lively and animated, her feelings were strong and deep, and her
    disposition uncommonly affectionate. No one could better enjoy liberty, yet no one could
    submit with more grace than she did to constraint and caprice. Her imagination was
    luxuriant, yet her capability of application was great. Her person was the image of her
    mind; her hazel eyes, although as lively as a bird’s, possessed an attractive softness.
    Her figure was light and airy; and, though capable of enduring great fatigue, she
    appeared the most fragile creature in the world. While I admired her under<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_066" n="47"/>standing and fancy, I loved to tend on her, as I should
    on a favourite animal; and I never saw so much grace both of person and mind united to
    so little pretension.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9"/>
</xml>
