<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C07a"/>
        <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="1"/>
          <head sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_head1"/>CHAPTER I.<head eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_head1"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1"/>I <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1_hi1"/>AM<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1_hi1"/> by birth a Genevese; and my family is one of the most
            distinguished of that republic. My ancestors had been for many years counsellors and
            syndics; and my father had filled several public situations with honour and reputation.
            He was respected by all who knew him for his integrity and indefatigable attention to
            public business. He passed his younger days perpetually occupied by the affairs of his
            country; <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_059" n="40"/>and it was not until the decline of life that
            he thought of marrying, and bestowing on the state sons who might carry his virtues and
            his name down to posterity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p1"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p2"/>As the circumstances of his marriage illustrate his character, I cannot refrain from
            relating them. One of his most intimate friends was a merchant, who, from a flourishing
            state, fell, through numerous mischances, into poverty. This man, whose name was
            Beaufort, was of a proud and unbending disposition, and could not bear to live in
            poverty and oblivion in the same country where he had formerly been distinguished for
            his rank and magnificence. Having paid his debts, therefore, in the most honourable
            manner, he retreated with his daughter to the town of Lucerne, where he lived unknown
            and in wretchedness. My father loved Beaufort with the truest <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_060" n="41"/>friendship, and was deeply grieved by his retreat in these unfortunate
            circumstances. He grieved also for the loss of his society, and resolved to seek him
            out, and endeavour to persuade him to begin the world again through his credit and
            assistance.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p2"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p3"/>Beaufort had taken effectual measures to conceal himself; and it was ten months before
            my father discovered his abode. Overjoyed at this discovery, he hastened to the house,
            which was situated in a mean street, near the Reuss. But when he entered, misery and
            despair alone welcomed him. Beaufort had saved but a very small sum of money from the
            wreck of his fortunes; but it was sufficient to provide him with sustenance for some
            months, and in the mean time he hoped to procure some respectable employment in a
            merchant’s house. The <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_061" n="42"/>interval was consequently spent
            in inaction; his grief only became more deep and rankling, when he had leisure for
            reflection; and at length it took so fast hold of his mind, that at the end of three
            months he lay on a bed of sickness, incapable of any exertion.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p3"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p4"/>His daughter attended him with the greatest tenderness; but she saw with despair that
            their little fund was rapidly decreasing, and that there was no other prospect of
            support. But Caroline Beaufort possessed a mind of an uncommon mould; and her courage
            rose to support her in her adversity. She procured plain work; she plaited straw; and by
            various means contrived to earn a pittance scarcely sufficient to support life.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p4"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p5"/>Several months passed in this manner. Her father grew worse; her time <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_062" n="43"/>was more entirely occupied in attending him; her means
            of subsistence decreased; and in the tenth month her father died in her arms, leaving
            her an orphan and a beggar. This last blow overcame her; and she knelt by Beaufort’s
            coffin, weeping bitterly, when my father entered the chamber. He came like a protecting
            spirit to the poor girl, who committed herself to his care, and after the interment of
            his friend, he conducted her to Geneva, and placed her under the protection of a
            relation. Two years after this event Caroline became his wife.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p5"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p6"/>When my father became a husband and a parent, he found his time so occupied by the
            duties of his new situation, that he relinquished many of his public employments, and
            devoted himself to the education of his children. Of these I was the eldest, and the
            destined suc<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_063" n="44"/>cessor to all his labours and utility. No
            creature could have more tender parents than mine. My improvement and health were their
            constant care, especially as I remained for several years their only child. But before I
            continue my narrative, I must record an incident which took place when I was four years
            of age.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p6"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p7"/>My father had a sister, whom he tenderly loved, and who had married early in life an
            Italian gentleman. Soon after her marriage, she had accompanied her husband into his
            native country, and for some years my father had very little communication with her.
            About the time I mentioned she died; and a few months afterwards he received a letter
            from her husband, acquainting him with his intention of marrying an Italian lady, and
            requesting my father to take charge of the in<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_064" n="45"/>fant
            Elizabeth, the only child of his deceased sister. “It is my wish,” he said, "that you
            should consider her as your own daughter, and educate her thus. Her mother's fortune is
            secured to her, the documents of which I will commit to your keeping. Reflect upon this
            proposition; and decide whether you would prefer educating your niece yourself to her
            being brought up by a stepmother.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p7"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p8"/>My father did not hesitate, and immediately went to Italy, that he might accompany the
            little Elizabeth to her future home. I have often heard my mother say, that she was at
            that time the most beautiful child she had ever seen, and showed signs even then of a
            gentle and affectionate disposition. These indications, and a desire to bind as closely
            as possible the ties of domestic love, determined my mother to consider Elizabeth <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_065" n="46"/>as my future wife; a design which she never found reason
            to repent.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p8"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9"/>From this time Elizabeth Lavenza became my playfellow, and, as we grew older, my
            friend. She was docile and good tempered, yet gay and playful as a summer insect.
            Although she was lively and animated, her feelings were strong and deep, and her
            disposition uncommonly affectionate. No one could better enjoy liberty, yet no one could
            submit with more grace than she did to constraint and caprice. Her imagination was
            luxuriant, yet her capability of application was great. Her person was the image of her
            mind; her hazel eyes, although as lively as a bird’s, possessed an attractive softness.
            Her figure was light and airy; and, though capable of enduring great fatigue, she
            appeared the most fragile creature in the world. While I admired her under<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_066" n="47"/>standing and fancy, I loved to tend on her, as I should
            on a favourite animal; and I never saw so much grace both of person and mind united to
            so little pretension.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p9"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter1_div4_div1_p10"/>Every one adored Elizabeth. If the 
        </xml>
