<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml><anchor type="collate" xml:id="C07e"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p6"/>I feel exquisite pleasure in dwelling on the recollections of childhood, before
    misfortune had tainted my mind, and changed its bright visions of extensive usefulness
    into gloomy and narrow reflections upon self. Besides, in drawing the picture of my
    early days, I also record those events which led, by insensible steps, to my after tale
    of misery: for when I would account to myself for the birth of that passion, which
    afterwards ruled my destiny, I find it arise, like a mountain river, from ignoble and
    almost forgotten sources; but, swelling as it proceeded, it became the torrent which, in
    its course, has swept away all my hopes and joys.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p6"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p7"/>Natural philosophy is the genius that has regulated my fate; I desire, therefore, in
    this narration, to state those facts which led to my predilection for that science. When
    I was thirteen years of age, we all went on a party of pleasure to the baths near
    Thonon: the inclemency of the weather obliged us to remain a day confined to the inn. In
    this house I chanced to find a volume of the works of Cornelius Agrippa. I opened it
    with apathy; the theory which he attempts to demonstrate, and the wonderful facts which
    he relates, soon changed this feeling into enthusiasm. A new light seemed to dawn upon
    my mind; and, bounding with joy, I communicated my discovery to my father. <pb xml:id="F1831_v_042" n="26"/>My father looked carelessly at the titlepage of my book,
    and said, “Ah! Cornelius Agrippa! My dear Victor, do not waste your time upon this; it
    is sad trash.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p7"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p8"/>If, instead of this remark, my father had taken the pains to explain to me, that the
    principles of Agrippa had been entirely exploded, and that a modern system of science
    had been introduced, which possessed much greater powers than the ancient, because the
    powers of the latter were chimerical, while those of the former were real and practical;
    under such circumstances, I should certainly have thrown Agrippa aside, and have
    contented my imagination, warmed as it was, by returning with greater ardour to my
    former studies. It is even possible, that the train of my ideas would never have
    received the fatal impulse that led to my ruin. But the cursory glance my father had
    taken of my volume by no means assured me that he was acquainted with its contents; and
    I continued to read with the greatest avidity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p8"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p9"/>When I returned home, my first care was to procure the whole works of this author, and
    afterwards of Paracelsus and Albertus Magnus. I read and studied the wild fancies of
    these writers with delight; they appeared to me treasures known to few beside myself. I
    have described myself as always having been embued with a fervent longing to penetrate
    the secrets of nature. In spite of the intense labour and wonderful discoveries of
    modern philosophers, I always came from my studies discontented and unsatisfied. Sir
    Isaac Newton is said to have avowed that he felt like a child picking up shells beside
    the great and unexplored ocean of truth. Those of his successors in each branch of
    natural philosophy with whom I was acquainted, appeared even to my boy’s apprehensions,
    as tyros engaged in the same pursuit.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p9"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p10"/>The untaught peasant beheld the elements around him, and was acquainted with their
    practical uses. The most learned philosopher knew little more. He had partially unveiled
    the face of Nature, but her immortal lineaments were still a wonder and a mystery. He
    might dissect, anatomise, and give names; but, not to speak of a final cause, causes in
    their secondary and tertiary grades were <pb xml:id="F1831_v_043" n="27"/>utterly
    unknown to him. I had gazed upon the fortifications and impediments that seemed to keep
    human beings from entering the citadel of nature, and rashly and ignorantly I had
    repined.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p10"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p11"/>But here were books, and here were men who had penetrated deeper and knew more. I took
    their word for all that they averred, and I became their disciple. It may appear strange
    that such should arise in the eighteenth century; but while I followed the routine of
    education in the schools of Geneva, I was, to a great degree, self taught with regard to
    my favourite studies. My father was not scientific, and I was left to struggle with a
    child’s blindness, added to a student’s thirst for knowledge. Under the guidance of my
    new preceptors, I entered with the greatest diligence into the search of the
    philosopher’s stone and the elixir of life; but the latter soon obtained my undivided
    attention. Wealth was an inferior object; but what glory would attend the discovery, if
    I could banish disease from the human frame, and render man invulnerable to any but a
    violent death!<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p11"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p12"/>Nor were these my only visions. The raising of ghosts or devils was a promise liberally
    accorded by my favourite authors, the fulfilment of which I most eagerly sought; and if
    my incantations were always unsuccessful, I attributed the failure rather to my own
    inexperience and mistake, than to a want of skill or fidelity in my instructors. And
    thus for a time I was occupied by exploded systems, mingling, like an unadept, a
    thousand contradictory theories, and floundering desperately in a very slough of
    multifarious knowledge, guided by an ardent imagination and childish reasoning, till an
    accident again changed the current of my ideas.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p12"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p13"/>When I was about fifteen years old we had retired to our house near Belrive, when we
    witnessed a most violent and terrible thunder-storm. It advanced from behind the
    mountains of Jura; and the thunder burst at once with frightful loudness from various
    quarters of the heavens. I remained, while the storm lasted, watching its progress with
    curiosity and delight. As I stood at the door, on a sudden I beheld a stream of fire
    issue from an old and beautiful oak, which stood about twenty yards from our <pb xml:id="F1831_v_044" n="28"/>house; and so soon as the dazzling light vanished, the
    oak had disappeared, and nothing remained but a blasted stump. When we visited it the
    next morning, we found the tree shattered in a singular manner. It was not splintered by
    the shock, but entirely reduced to thin ribands of wood. I never beheld anything so
    utterly destroyed.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p13"/>
</xml>
