<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C20c"/> rank, the
            merchant commanded his daughter to think no more of her <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_099" n="095"/>lover, but to prepare to return with him to her native country. The
            generous nature of Safie was outraged by this command; she attempted to expostulate with
            her father, but he left her angrily, reiterating his tyrannical mandate.<note sID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p16_note1"/>Thomas copy: pencil mark joins paragraphs.<note eID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p16_note1"/> “A few days after, the Turk entered his daughter’s apartment, and told her hastily,
            that he had reason to believe that his residence at Leghorn had been divulged, and that
            he should speedily be delivered up to the French government; he had, consequently, hired
            a vessel to convey him to Constantinople, for which city he should sail in a few hours.
            He intended to leave his daughter under the care of a confidential servant, to follow at
            her leisure with the greater part of his property, which had not yet arrived at
            Leghorn.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p16"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p17"/>“When alone, Safie resolved in her <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_100" n="096"/>own mind the
            plan of conduct that it would become her to pursue in this emergency. A residence in
            Turkey was abhorrent to her; her religion and her feelings were alike adverse to it. By
            some papers of her father’s, which fell into her hands, she heard of the exile of her
            lover, and learnt the name of the spot where he then resided. She hesitated some time,
            but at length she formed her determination. Taking with her some jewels that belonged to
            her, and a small sum of money, she quitted Italy, with an attendant, a native of
            Leghorn, but who understood the common language of Turkey, and departed for Germany.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p17"/>
      <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p18"/>“She arrived in safety at a town about twenty leagues from the cottage of De Lacey,
            when her attendant fell dangerously ill. Safie nursed her with the most devoted
            affection; but the <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_101" n="097"/>poor girl died, and the Arabian
            was left alone, unacquainted with the language of the country, and utterly ignorant of
            the customs of the world. She fell, however, into good hands. The Italian had mentioned
            the name of the spot for which they were bound; and, after her death, the woman of the
            house in which they had lived took care that Safie should arrive in safety at the
            cottage of her lover.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p18"/>
      <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="13"/></xml>
