<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C12</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app1-f1831__Pt1">
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p14">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app1-f1831__Pt2">“Dear, </seg>dear <seg xml:id="C12_app3-f1831">Elizabeth!” </seg>I <seg xml:id="C12_app5-f1831">exclaimed, </seg>when I had read her <seg xml:id="C12_app8-f1831">letter, “I </seg>will write <seg xml:id="C12_app10-f1831">instantly, </seg>and relieve them from the <seg xml:id="C12_app12-f1831">anxiety </seg>they must <seg xml:id="C12_app14-f1831">feel.” </seg>I wrote, and this exertion greatly fatigued me; <seg xml:id="C12_app18-f1831">but </seg>my convalescence <seg xml:id="C12_app20-f1831">had commenced, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C12_app22-f1831">proceeded regularly. In </seg>another fortnight I was able to leave my <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app26-f1831__Pt1">chamber.<pb n="53" xml:id="F1831_v_069"/>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p15">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app26-f1831__Pt2">One </seg>of my first duties on my recovery was to introduce Clerval to the several professors of the university. In doing <seg xml:id="C12_app34-f1831">this, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C12_app36-f1831">underwent </seg>a kind of rough <seg xml:id="C12_app38-f1831">usage, </seg>ill <seg xml:id="C12_app40-f1831">befitting </seg>the wounds that my mind had sustained. Ever since the <seg xml:id="C12_app43-f1831">fatal </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app44-f1831">night, </seg>the end of my <seg xml:id="C12_app46-f1831">labours, </seg>and the beginning of my <seg xml:id="C12_app48-f1831">misfortunes, </seg>I had conceived a violent antipathy even to the name of <seg xml:id="C12_app54-f1831">natural </seg>philosophy. When I was otherwise quite restored to <seg xml:id="C12_app56-f1831">health, </seg>the sight of a chemical instrument <seg xml:id="C12_app58-f1831">would renew </seg>all the agony of my nervous <seg xml:id="C12_app62-f1831">symptoms. </seg>Henry saw <seg xml:id="C12_app64-f1831">this, </seg>and had <seg xml:id="C12_app66-f1831">removed </seg>all my <seg xml:id="C12_app68-f1831">apparatus </seg>from my <seg xml:id="C12_app70-f1831">view. </seg>He had also changed my <seg xml:id="C12_app74-f1831">apartment; </seg>for he perceived that I had <seg xml:id="C12_app78-f1831">acquired a </seg>dislike <seg xml:id="C12_app80-f1831">for </seg>the room which had previously been my <seg xml:id="C12_app84-f1831">laboratory. </seg>But these cares of Clerval were <seg xml:id="C12_app88-f1831">made </seg>of no avail when I visited the professors. M. Waldman inflicted torture when he <seg xml:id="C12_app96-f1831">praised, </seg>with kindness and warmth, the astonishing progress I had made in the sciences. He soon perceived <seg xml:id="C12_app106-f1831">that </seg>I <seg xml:id="C12_app108-f1831">disliked </seg>the <seg xml:id="C12_app110-f1831">subject; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app111-f1831">but </seg>not guessing the real <seg xml:id="C12_app115-f1831">cause, </seg>he attributed <seg xml:id="C12_app117-f1831">my </seg>feelings to <seg xml:id="C12_app119-f1831">modesty, and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app120-f1831">changed </seg>the subject from my <seg xml:id="C12_app124-f1831">improvement, </seg>to the science itself, with a <seg xml:id="C12_app130-f1831">desire, </seg>as I evidently <seg xml:id="C12_app132-f1831">saw, </seg>of drawing me out. What could I do? He meant to <seg xml:id="C12_app140-f1831">please, and </seg>he <seg xml:id="C12_app142-f1831">tormented me. I </seg>felt as if he <seg xml:id="C12_app144-f1831">had placed carefully, </seg>one by <seg xml:id="C12_app146-f1831">one, </seg>in my view those instruments which were to be afterwards used in putting me to a slow and cruel death. I writhed under his words, yet dared not <seg xml:id="C12_app156-f1831">exhibit </seg>the pain I felt. Clerval, whose eyes and feelings were always quick in discerning the sensations of <seg xml:id="C12_app162-f1831">others, </seg>declined the <seg xml:id="C12_app164-f1831">subject, alleging, in excuse, his total ignorance; </seg>and the conversation took a more general turn. I thanked <seg xml:id="C12_app168-f1831">my friend </seg>from my heart, but I did not speak. I saw <seg xml:id="C12_app174-f1831">plainly </seg>that he was surprised, but he never attempted to draw my secret from <seg xml:id="C12_app180-f1831">me; </seg>and although I loved him with a mixture of <seg xml:id="C12_app184-f1831">affection </seg>and reverence that knew <seg xml:id="C12_app186-f1831">no </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app188-f1831">bounds, </seg>yet I could never persuade <seg xml:id="C12_app193-f1831">myself </seg>to confide to him that event which was so often present to my <seg xml:id="C12_app197-f1831">recollection, </seg>but which I feared the detail to another would only impress more <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app201-f1831__Pt1">deeply.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p16">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app201-f1831__Pt2">M. </seg>Krempe was not equally <seg xml:id="C12_app203-f1831">docile; and </seg>in my <seg xml:id="C12_app205-f1831">condition at that time, </seg>of almost insupportable <seg xml:id="C12_app209-f1831">sensitiveness, </seg>his harsh blunt <seg xml:id="C12_app213-f1831">encomiums </seg>gave me even more pain than the <seg xml:id="C12_app219-f1831">bene<pb n="54" xml:id="F1831_v_070"/>volent </seg>approbation of M. <seg xml:id="C12_app222-f1831">Waldman. “D—n the fellow!” </seg>cried <seg xml:id="C12_app224-f1831">he; “why, </seg>M. <seg xml:id="C12_app226-f1831">Clerval, I assure </seg>you he has outstript <seg xml:id="C12_app230-f1831">us all. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app231-f1831">Ay, </seg>stare if you <seg xml:id="C12_app233-f1831">please; </seg>but <seg xml:id="C12_app235-f1831">it </seg>is <seg xml:id="C12_app237-f1831">nevertheless </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app238-f1831">true. </seg>A youngster <seg xml:id="C12_app240-f1831">who, </seg>but <seg xml:id="C12_app242-f1831">a few </seg>years <seg xml:id="C12_app244-f1831">ago, </seg>believed <seg xml:id="C12_app246-f1831">in </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app247-f1831">Cornelius </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app248-f1831">Agrippa </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app249-f1831">as </seg>firmly as <seg xml:id="C12_app251-f1831">in </seg>the <seg xml:id="C12_app253-f1831">gospel, </seg>has <seg xml:id="C12_app255-f1831">now </seg>set himself at the head of <seg xml:id="C12_app257-f1831">the university; </seg>and if he is not soon <seg xml:id="C12_app259-f1831">pulled down, </seg>we shall all be out <seg xml:id="C12_app261-f1831">of </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app262-f1831">countenance.—Ay, ay,” </seg>continued <seg xml:id="C12_app265-f1831">he, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app266-f1831">observing </seg>my <seg xml:id="C12_app268-f1831">face expressive </seg>of <seg xml:id="C12_app270-f1831">suffering, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app271-f1831">“M. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app272-f1831">Frankenstein </seg>is <seg xml:id="C12_app274-f1831">modest; </seg>an excellent quality in <seg xml:id="C12_app276-f1831">a </seg>young <seg xml:id="C12_app278-f1831">man. </seg>Young men should be <seg xml:id="C12_app280-f1831">diffident </seg>of <seg xml:id="C12_app282-f1831">themselves, </seg>you <seg xml:id="C12_app284-f1831">know, M. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app285-f1831">Clerval: </seg>I was myself when <seg xml:id="C12_app287-f1831">young; </seg>but <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app289-f1831__Pt1">that wears out in a very short time.”</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p17">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app289-f1831__Pt2">M. </seg>Krempe had now commenced <seg xml:id="C12_app291-f1831">an </seg>eulogy on <seg xml:id="C12_app293-f1831">himself, which </seg>happily turned the conversation from <seg xml:id="C12_app297-f1831">a </seg>subject that was so <seg xml:id="C12_app299-f1831">annoying </seg>to <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app301-f1831__Pt1">me.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p18">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app301-f1831__Pt2">Clerval </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app302-f1831">had never sympathised in my tastes for </seg>natural <seg xml:id="C12_app304-f1831">science; and </seg>his <seg xml:id="C12_app307-f1831">literary pursuits differed wholly from those which had occupied me. He came to </seg>the <seg xml:id="C12_app309-f1831">university with the design of making himself complete master of the oriental languages, as thus he should </seg>open a field <seg xml:id="C12_app318-f1831">for the plan of life he had marked out </seg>for <seg xml:id="C12_app320-f1831">himself. Resolved to pursue no inglorious career, he turned his eyes toward the East, as affording scope for </seg>his <seg xml:id="C12_app323-f1831">spirit of enterprise. The </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app325-f1831">Persian, Arabic, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C12_app327-f1831">Sanscrit languages engaged </seg>his <seg xml:id="C12_app330-f1831">attention, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app331-f1831">and I was easily induced to enter on </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app335-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app336-f1831">same studies. </seg>Idleness had ever been irksome to <seg xml:id="C12_app343-f1831">me, </seg>and now that I <seg xml:id="C12_app347-f1831">wished to </seg>fly from <seg xml:id="C12_app349-f1831">reflection, </seg>and hated my <seg xml:id="C12_app351-f1831">former </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app352-f1831">studies, </seg>I <seg xml:id="C12_app354-f1831">felt </seg>great relief in being the <seg xml:id="C12_app356-f1831">fellow-pupil with </seg>my <seg xml:id="C12_app358-f1831">friend, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C12_app360-f1831">found </seg>not <seg xml:id="C12_app362-f1831">only instruction </seg>but consolation in the works of the orientalists. <seg xml:id="C12_app366-f1831">I did not, like him, attempt a critical knowledge of their dialects, for I did not contemplate making any other use of them than temporary amusement. I read merely to understand their meaning, and they well repaid my labours. </seg>Their melancholy is <seg xml:id="C12_app368-f1831">soothing, </seg>and their joy <seg xml:id="C12_app372-f1831">elevating, </seg>to a degree I never experienced in <seg xml:id="C12_app376-f1831">studying the </seg>authors <seg xml:id="C12_app378-f1831">of any </seg>other <seg xml:id="C12_app380-f1831">country. </seg>When you <seg xml:id="C12_app382-f1831">read </seg>their <seg xml:id="C12_app384-f1831">writings, </seg>life appears to consist in a warm sun and <seg xml:id="C12_app390-f1831">a </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app391-f1831">garden </seg>of <seg xml:id="C12_app393-f1831">roses,—in </seg>the smiles <seg xml:id="C12_app395-f1831">and frowns </seg>of a fair <seg xml:id="C12_app397-f1831">enemy, </seg>and the fire that consumes your own <seg xml:id="C12_app401-f1831">heart. </seg>How different from the manly <seg xml:id="C12_app403-f1831">and heroical poetry </seg>of Greece and <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app405-f1831__Pt1">Rome!<pb n="55" xml:id="F1831_v_071"/>
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p19">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app405-f1831__Pt2">Summer </seg>passed away in these <seg xml:id="C12_app407-f1831">occupations, and </seg>my return to Geneva was fixed for the latter end of <seg xml:id="C12_app411-f1831">autumn; </seg>but being delayed by several <seg xml:id="C12_app413-f1831">accidents, </seg>winter and snow arrived, the roads were deemed <seg xml:id="C12_app419-f1831">impassable, </seg>and my <seg xml:id="C12_app421-f1831">journey </seg>was <seg xml:id="C12_app423-f1831">retarded until </seg>the ensuing spring. <seg xml:id="C12_app425-f1831">I </seg>felt this delay very <seg xml:id="C12_app429-f1831">bitterly; </seg>for I <seg xml:id="C12_app431-f1831">longed </seg>to see my native <seg xml:id="C12_app435-f1831">town </seg>and my beloved <seg xml:id="C12_app437-f1831">friends. </seg>My return had only been delayed so <seg xml:id="C12_app441-f1831">long, </seg>from an unwillingness to leave Clerval in a strange <seg xml:id="C12_app445-f1831">place, </seg>before he had become acquainted with <seg xml:id="C12_app449-f1831">any of </seg>its inhabitants. The <seg xml:id="C12_app451-f1831">winter, however, </seg>was <seg xml:id="C12_app453-f1831">spent cheerfully; </seg>and although the spring was uncommonly <seg xml:id="C12_app457-f1831">late, </seg>when it <seg xml:id="C12_app461-f1831">came </seg>its beauty compensated <seg xml:id="C12_app463-f1831">for </seg>its <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app465-f1831__Pt1">dilatoriness.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p20">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app465-f1831__Pt2">The </seg>month of May <seg xml:id="C12_app469-f1831">had </seg>already <seg xml:id="C12_app471-f1831">commenced, </seg>and I expected the letter <seg xml:id="C12_app477-f1831">daily which </seg>was to fix the date of my <seg xml:id="C12_app481-f1831">departure, </seg>when Henry proposed a pedestrian tour in <seg xml:id="C12_app485-f1831">the </seg>environs of <seg xml:id="C12_app487-f1831">Ingolstadt, </seg>that I might bid <seg xml:id="C12_app490-f1831">a personal </seg>farewell to the country I had so long <seg xml:id="C12_app494-f1831">inhabited. </seg>I <seg xml:id="C12_app496-f1831">acceded </seg>with pleasure to this <seg xml:id="C12_app500-f1831">proposition: </seg>I was fond of <seg xml:id="C12_app502-f1831">exercise, </seg>and Clerval had always been my favourite companion in <seg xml:id="C12_app506-f1831">the </seg>rambles of this nature that I had <seg xml:id="C12_app510-f1831">taken </seg>among the scenes of my native <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app513-f1831__Pt1">country.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p21">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app513-f1831__Pt2">We </seg>passed a fortnight in these <seg xml:id="C12_app515-f1831">perambulations: </seg>my health and spirits had long been <seg xml:id="C12_app519-f1831">restored, </seg>and they gained <seg xml:id="C12_app521-f1831">additional strength </seg>from the salubrious <seg xml:id="C12_app523-f1831">air </seg>I breathed, the natural incidents of our <seg xml:id="C12_app531-f1831">progress, </seg>and the conversation of my friend. Study had before <seg xml:id="C12_app535-f1831">secluded </seg>me <seg xml:id="C12_app537-f1831">from </seg>the <seg xml:id="C12_app539-f1831">intercourse </seg>of my <seg xml:id="C12_app541-f1831">fellow-creatures, and rendered me unsocial; </seg>but Clerval called forth the better feelings of my <seg xml:id="C12_app545-f1831">heart; </seg>he again taught me to love the aspect of <seg xml:id="C12_app549-f1831">nature, </seg>and the cheerful faces of children. Excellent friend! how sincerely did you love <seg xml:id="C12_app553-f1831">me, </seg>and endeavour to elevate my <seg xml:id="C12_app556-f1831">mind </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app557-f1831">until </seg>it was on a level with your <seg xml:id="C12_app561-f1831">own! </seg>A selfish <seg xml:id="C12_app563-f1831">pursuit </seg>had cramped and narrowed <seg xml:id="C12_app565-f1831">me, until </seg>your <seg xml:id="C12_app567-f1831">gentleness </seg>and affection warmed and opened <seg xml:id="C12_app569-f1831">my senses; </seg>I became the same happy creature <seg xml:id="C12_app573-f1831">who, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C12_app574-f1831">a </seg>few years ago, <seg xml:id="C12_app576-f1831">loved </seg>and beloved by all, had no sorrow or <seg xml:id="C12_app580-f1831">care. </seg>When <seg xml:id="C12_app582-f1831">happy, </seg>inanimate nature had the power of <seg xml:id="C12_app586-f1831">bestowing </seg>on me the most delightful <seg xml:id="C12_app592-f1831">sensations. </seg>A serene sky and <seg xml:id="C12_app596-f1831">verdant </seg>fields filled me with <seg xml:id="C12_app600-f1831">ecstasy. The </seg>present season was indeed <seg xml:id="C12_app602-f1831">divine; </seg>the flowers of spring <seg xml:id="C12_app604-f1831">bloomed </seg>in the <seg xml:id="C12_app606-f1831">hedges, </seg>while <seg xml:id="C12_app608-f1831">those<pb n="56" xml:id="F1831_v_072"/> 
               </seg>of summer were already in <seg xml:id="C12_app610-f1831">bud. </seg>I was <seg xml:id="C12_app614-f1831">undisturbed </seg>by thoughts <seg xml:id="C12_app618-f1831">which </seg>during the <seg xml:id="C12_app620-f1831">preceding </seg>year <seg xml:id="C12_app622-f1831">had </seg>pressed upon <seg xml:id="C12_app624-f1831">me, notwithstanding </seg>my endeavours to throw them <seg xml:id="C12_app626-f1831">off, with </seg>an invincible <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app628-f1831__Pt1">burden.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p22">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app628-f1831__Pt2">Henry </seg>rejoiced in my <seg xml:id="C12_app632-f1831">gaiety, </seg>and sincerely <seg xml:id="C12_app636-f1831">sympathised </seg>in my <seg xml:id="C12_app638-f1831">feelings: </seg>he exerted himself to amuse me, while he expressed the <seg xml:id="C12_app642-f1831">sensations </seg>that filled his <seg xml:id="C12_app646-f1831">soul. </seg>The resources of his mind on this occasion were truly <seg xml:id="C12_app652-f1831">astonishing: </seg>his conversation was full of <seg xml:id="C12_app654-f1831">imagination; </seg>and very often, in imitation <seg xml:id="C12_app656-f1831">of </seg>the <seg xml:id="C12_app658-f1831">Persian and </seg>Arabic writers, he invented tales of <seg xml:id="C12_app662-f1831">wonderful </seg>fancy and <seg xml:id="C12_app664-f1831">passion. </seg>At other times he repeated my favourite <seg xml:id="C12_app668-f1831">poems, </seg>or drew me out into <seg xml:id="C12_app670-f1831">arguments, </seg>which he supported with great <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app674-f1831__Pt1">ingenuity.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p23">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app674-f1831__Pt2">We </seg>returned to our <seg xml:id="C12_app676-f1831">college </seg>on a Sunday <seg xml:id="C12_app678-f1831">afternoon: </seg>the <seg xml:id="C12_app680-f1831">peasants </seg>were <seg xml:id="C12_app682-f1831">dancing, </seg>and every one we met appeared <seg xml:id="C12_app686-f1831">gay </seg>and <seg xml:id="C12_app688-f1831">happy. </seg>My own spirits were <seg xml:id="C12_app692-f1831">high, </seg>and I bounded along with feelings of <seg xml:id="C12_app698-f1831">unbridled </seg>joy and <seg xml:id="C12_app700-f1831">hilarity. </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C12_app701-f1831__Pt1">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C12_app701-f1831__Pt2">
            <milestone n="6" type="end" unit="chapter"/> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>