<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C11</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app1-f1831__Pt1">
            <milestone n="6" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_head1">CHAPTER VI.</head>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app1-f1831__Pt2"> C<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1_hi1">LERVAL</hi> 
               </seg>then put the following letter into <seg xml:id="C11_app5-f1831">my hands. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app6-f1831">It was from </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app7-f1831">my </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app8-f1831__Pt1">own Elizabeth:—</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p2">“My dearest Cousin,</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app8-f1831__Pt2">“You have been ill, very ill, and even </seg>the <seg xml:id="C11_app15-f1831">constant letters of dear kind Henry are not sufficient to reassure me on </seg>your <seg xml:id="C11_app20-f1831">account. You are forbidden to write—to hold a pen; yet one word from you, dear Victor, is necessary to calm our apprehensions. For a long </seg>time <seg xml:id="C11_app30-f1831">I </seg>have <seg xml:id="C11_app33-f1831">thought that each post would bring this line, and my persuasions </seg>have <seg xml:id="C11_app37-f1831">restrained my uncle from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. I have prevented his encountering the inconveniences and perhaps dangers </seg>of <seg xml:id="C11_app50-f1831">so long a journey; yet how often have </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app52-f1831">I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app53-f1831">regretted not being able </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app54-f1831">to </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app55-f1831">perform it myself! I figure to myself that the task of attending on your sick bed has devolved on some mercenary old nurse, who could never guess your wishes, nor minister to them with </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app62-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app63-f1831">care </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app65-f1831">and </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app66-f1831">affection of your poor cousin. Yet that is over now: </seg>Clerval <seg xml:id="C11_app69-f1831">writes </seg>that <seg xml:id="C11_app71-f1831">indeed </seg>you <seg xml:id="C11_app73-f1831">are </seg>getting <seg xml:id="C11_app75-f1831">better. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app76-f1831">I </seg>eagerly hope <seg xml:id="C11_app78-f1831">that </seg>you will confirm <seg xml:id="C11_app82-f1831">this intelligence </seg>soon in your own <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app84-f1831__Pt1">handwriting.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app84-f1831__Pt2">“Get well—and return to us. You will find a happy, cheerful home, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app94-f1831">friends who love you dearly. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app98-f1831">Your father’s </seg>health is <seg xml:id="C11_app102-f1831">vigorous, and he asks but to see you,—but to be assured </seg>that <seg xml:id="C11_app106-f1831">you are well; and not a care will ever cloud his benevolent countenance. How pleased </seg>you would <seg xml:id="C11_app114-f1831">be to remark the improvement of our Ernest! </seg>He is now <seg xml:id="C11_app120-f1831">sixteen, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app122-f1831">full of activity and spirit. </seg>He is <seg xml:id="C11_app131-f1831">desirous to be a true Swiss, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app138-f1831">to enter into foreign service;<pb n="50" xml:id="F1831_v_066"/> but we cannot part with him, at least until </seg>his <seg xml:id="C11_app146-f1831">elder brother return to us. My uncle is not pleased with </seg>the <seg xml:id="C11_app151-f1831">idea </seg>of <seg xml:id="C11_app153-f1831">a military career in a distant country; but Ernest never had your powers of application. </seg>He <seg xml:id="C11_app158-f1831">looks upon study as an odious fetter;—his time </seg>is <seg xml:id="C11_app163-f1831">spent </seg>in the open <seg xml:id="C11_app165-f1831">air, </seg>climbing the <seg xml:id="C11_app167-f1831">hills </seg>or rowing on the lake. <seg xml:id="C11_app171-f1831">I </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app172-f1831">fear </seg>that he <seg xml:id="C11_app177-f1831">will become an idler, unless we yield the point, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app190-f1831">permit him to enter on </seg>the <seg xml:id="C11_app196-f1831">profession </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app197-f1831">which </seg>he <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app215-f1831__Pt1">has selected.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app215-f1831__Pt2">“Little alteration, except </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app230-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app231-f1831">growth </seg>of <seg xml:id="C11_app233-f1831">our dear children, has taken place since you left us. </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app241-f1831">The </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app242-f1831">blue lake, and snow-clad mountains, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app249-f1831">they </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app250-f1831">never change;—and I think our placid home, and our contented hearts are regulated by the same immutable laws. My trifling occupations take up </seg>my <seg xml:id="C11_app260-f1831">time </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app263-f1831">amuse me, and </seg>I <seg xml:id="C11_app266-f1831">am rewarded for any exertions by seeing none but happy, kind faces around me. Since you left us, but one change has taken place in our little household. </seg>Do you remember <seg xml:id="C11_app283-f1831">on what occasion </seg>Justine <seg xml:id="C11_app285-f1831">Moritz entered our family? </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app286-f1831">Probably </seg>you do <seg xml:id="C11_app288-f1831">not; </seg>I will <seg xml:id="C11_app290-f1831">relate </seg>her <seg xml:id="C11_app292-f1831">history, therefore, </seg>in a few words. <seg xml:id="C11_app294-f1831">Madame Moritz, </seg>her <seg xml:id="C11_app296-f1831">mother, </seg>was a widow with four <seg xml:id="C11_app300-f1831">children, </seg>of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her <seg xml:id="C11_app310-f1831">father; but, through a strange perversity, </seg>her mother could <seg xml:id="C11_app314-f1831">not </seg>endure <seg xml:id="C11_app316-f1831">her, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app317-f1831">and, </seg>after the death of M. <seg xml:id="C11_app321-f1831">Moritz, </seg>treated her very ill. My aunt observed <seg xml:id="C11_app325-f1831">this; and, </seg>when Justine was twelve years <seg xml:id="C11_app331-f1831">of age, </seg>prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at <seg xml:id="C11_app337-f1831">our </seg>house. The republican institutions of our <seg xml:id="C11_app341-f1831">country </seg>have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less <seg xml:id="C11_app357-f1831">distinction </seg>between the <seg xml:id="C11_app359-f1831">several </seg>classes <seg xml:id="C11_app361-f1831">of its inhabitants; </seg>and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so <seg xml:id="C11_app363-f1831">despised, their manners </seg>are more refined and moral. A servant <seg xml:id="C11_app365-f1831">in </seg>Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France <seg xml:id="C11_app367-f1831">and England. Justine, </seg>thus <seg xml:id="C11_app369-f1831">received in </seg>our <seg xml:id="C11_app371-f1831">family, learned </seg>the duties of <seg xml:id="C11_app373-f1831">a servant; </seg>a <seg xml:id="C11_app375-f1831">condition which, </seg>in our fortunate <seg xml:id="C11_app377-f1831">country, </seg>does not include <seg xml:id="C11_app379-f1831">the idea of ignorance, and </seg>a <seg xml:id="C11_app381-f1831">sacrifice </seg>of the dignity of a human <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app383-f1831__Pt1">being.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app383-f1831__Pt2">“Justine, </seg>you <seg xml:id="C11_app388-f1831">may remember, </seg>was a great favourite of <seg xml:id="C11_app394-f1831">yours; </seg>and I <seg xml:id="C11_app396-f1831">recollect </seg>you once <seg xml:id="C11_app398-f1831">remarked, </seg>that if you were in an <seg xml:id="C11_app402-f1831">ill-humour, </seg>one glance from <seg xml:id="C11_app405-f1831">Justine </seg>could <seg xml:id="C11_app407-f1831">dissipate<pb n="51" xml:id="F1831_v_067"/> 
               </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app408-f1831">it, for </seg>the same reason that Ariosto <seg xml:id="C11_app412-f1831">gives </seg>concerning the beauty of <seg xml:id="C11_app416-f1831">Angelica—she </seg>looked so <seg xml:id="C11_app418-f1831">frank-hearted </seg>and happy. My aunt <seg xml:id="C11_app420-f1831">conceived a great </seg>attachment for her, by which she <seg xml:id="C11_app422-f1831">was induced to </seg>give her <seg xml:id="C11_app424-f1831">an </seg>education superior to that which she had at first <seg xml:id="C11_app430-f1831">intended. This </seg>benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the <seg xml:id="C11_app438-f1831">world: </seg>I do not mean that she made any <seg xml:id="C11_app442-f1831">professions; </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app443-f1831">I </seg>never heard one pass her <seg xml:id="C11_app447-f1831">lips; </seg>but you could see by her <seg xml:id="C11_app451-f1831">eyes </seg>that she almost adored her protectress. Although <seg xml:id="C11_app457-f1831">her disposition was </seg>gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid <seg xml:id="C11_app461-f1831">the greatest </seg>attention to every gesture of my <seg xml:id="C11_app464-f1831">aunt. </seg>She thought her the <seg xml:id="C11_app466-f1831">model </seg>of <seg xml:id="C11_app468-f1831">all excellence, </seg>and endeavoured to imitate her <seg xml:id="C11_app470-f1831">phraseology </seg>and manners, so that even now she often <seg xml:id="C11_app476-f1831">reminds </seg>me of <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app480-f1831__Pt1">her.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app480-f1831__Pt2">“When </seg>my dearest aunt <seg xml:id="C11_app482-f1831">died, </seg>every one was too much occupied in their own grief to notice poor <seg xml:id="C11_app488-f1831">Justine, </seg>who had attended her during her illness with the <seg xml:id="C11_app492-f1831">most anxious </seg>affection. Poor Justine was very <seg xml:id="C11_app496-f1831">ill; </seg>but other <seg xml:id="C11_app498-f1831">trials </seg>were reserved for <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app500-f1831__Pt1">her.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app500-f1831__Pt2">“One </seg>by <seg xml:id="C11_app502-f1831">one, </seg>her brothers and sister <seg xml:id="C11_app504-f1831">died; </seg>and her <seg xml:id="C11_app506-f1831">mother, </seg>with the exception of her neglected <seg xml:id="C11_app508-f1831">daughter, was </seg>left childless. The conscience of the woman was <seg xml:id="C11_app512-f1831">troubled; </seg>she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a <seg xml:id="C11_app516-f1831">judgment from </seg>heaven to <seg xml:id="C11_app518-f1831">chastise </seg>her <seg xml:id="C11_app520-f1831">partiality. </seg>She was a Roman <seg xml:id="C11_app522-f1831">catholic; </seg>and I believe her confessor <seg xml:id="C11_app526-f1831">confirmed </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app527-f1831">the </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app528-f1831">idea which </seg>she had <seg xml:id="C11_app530-f1831">conceived. </seg>Accordingly, a few months after your departure for <seg xml:id="C11_app532-f1831">Ingolstadt, </seg>Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor <seg xml:id="C11_app536-f1831">girl! </seg>she wept when she quitted our <seg xml:id="C11_app538-f1831">house; </seg>she was much altered since the death of my <seg xml:id="C11_app542-f1831">aunt; </seg>grief had given <seg xml:id="C11_app544-f1831">softness </seg>and a winning mildness to her <seg xml:id="C11_app546-f1831">manners, </seg>which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her <seg xml:id="C11_app554-f1831">mother’s </seg>house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor <seg xml:id="C11_app558-f1831">woman </seg>was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her <seg xml:id="C11_app564-f1831">unkindness, </seg>but much <seg xml:id="C11_app566-f1831">oftener </seg>accused her <seg xml:id="C11_app568-f1831">of </seg>having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at <seg xml:id="C11_app576-f1831">length </seg>threw <seg xml:id="C11_app578-f1831">Madame Moritz </seg>into a decline, which at first <seg xml:id="C11_app582-f1831">increased </seg>her irritability, but she is now at <seg xml:id="C11_app584-f1831">peace </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app585-f1831">forever. </seg>She died on the first approach of cold <seg xml:id="C11_app592-f1831">weather, </seg>at <seg xml:id="C11_app595-f1831">the </seg>beginning of <seg xml:id="C11_app597-f1831">this<pb n="52" xml:id="F1831_v_068"/> 
               </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app598-f1831">last winter. </seg>Justine has returned to <seg xml:id="C11_app602-f1831">us; </seg>and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and <seg xml:id="C11_app608-f1831">gentle, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app610-f1831">extremely pretty; </seg>as I mentioned <seg xml:id="C11_app614-f1831">before, </seg>her <seg xml:id="C11_app616-f1831">mien </seg>and her expressions continually remind me of my dear <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app622-f1831__Pt1">aunt.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app622-f1831__Pt2">“I </seg>must say <seg xml:id="C11_app624-f1831">also </seg>a few words to <seg xml:id="C11_app626-f1831">you, </seg>my dear <seg xml:id="C11_app628-f1831">cousin, </seg>of little darling William. I wish you could see <seg xml:id="C11_app632-f1831">him; </seg>he is very tall of his <seg xml:id="C11_app636-f1831">age, </seg>with sweet laughing blue <seg xml:id="C11_app640-f1831">eyes, </seg>dark <seg xml:id="C11_app642-f1831">eye-lashes, </seg>and curling <seg xml:id="C11_app644-f1831">hair. </seg>When he <seg xml:id="C11_app646-f1831">smiles, </seg>two little dimples appear on <seg xml:id="C11_app650-f1831">each cheek, </seg>which are rosy with <seg xml:id="C11_app654-f1831">health. </seg>He has already had one or two little <seg xml:id="C11_app660-f1831">
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1">wives</hi>, </seg>but Louisa Biron is his <seg xml:id="C11_app664-f1831">favourite, </seg>a pretty little girl of five years <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app668-f1831__Pt1">of age.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app668-f1831__Pt2">“Now, </seg>dear <seg xml:id="C11_app670-f1831">Victor, </seg>I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip <seg xml:id="C11_app676-f1831">concerning the good people of Geneva. </seg>The pretty Miss <seg xml:id="C11_app680-f1831">Mansfield </seg>has already <seg xml:id="C11_app682-f1831">received </seg>the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John <seg xml:id="C11_app689-f1831">Melbourne, </seg>Esq. Her ugly <seg xml:id="C11_app691-f1831">sister, Manon, </seg>married M. <seg xml:id="C11_app693-f1831">Duvillard, </seg>the rich <seg xml:id="C11_app695-f1831">banker, </seg>last autumn. Your favourite <seg xml:id="C11_app699-f1831">schoolfellow, </seg>Louis <seg xml:id="C11_app701-f1831">Manoir, </seg>has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from <seg xml:id="C11_app709-f1831">Geneva. </seg>But he has already recovered his <seg xml:id="C11_app715-f1831">spirits, </seg>and <seg xml:id="C11_app717-f1831">is </seg>reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty <seg xml:id="C11_app723-f1831">Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She </seg>is a <seg xml:id="C11_app725-f1831">widow, </seg>and much older than <seg xml:id="C11_app727-f1831">Manoir; </seg>but she is <seg xml:id="C11_app731-f1831">very </seg>much <seg xml:id="C11_app733-f1831">admired, </seg>and a favourite with <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app737-f1831__Pt1">everybody.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app737-f1831__Pt2">“I </seg>have written myself into <seg xml:id="C11_app740-f1831">better </seg>spirits, dear <seg xml:id="C11_app742-f1831">cousin; </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app743-f1831__Pt1">but my anxiety returns upon me as I conclude. Write, dearest Victor,—one line—one word will be a blessing to us. Ten thousand thanks to Henry for his kindness, his affection, and his many letters: we are sincerely grateful. Adieu! my cousin; take care of yourself; and, I entreat you, write!</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app743-f1831__Pt2">“E<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1">LIZABETH</hi> 
               </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app773-f1831__Pt1">L<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2">AVENZA</hi>.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app773-f1831__Pt2">“Geneva, </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C11_app774-f1831">March 18th, </seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C11_app775-f1831__Pt1">17—.”</seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C11_app775-f1831__Pt2"> 
            </seg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>