<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C24"/>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="17"/>
   <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
   <p>D<hi rend="smallcaps">AY</hi> after day, week after week, passed away on my return to
            Geneva; and I could not collect the courage to recommence my work. I feared the
            vengeance of the disappointed fiend, yet I was unable to overcome my repugnance to the
            task which was enjoined me. I found that I could not compose a female without again
            devoting several months to profound study and labo<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_006" n="002"/>rious disquisition. I had heard of some discoveries having been made by an English
            philosopher, the knowledge of which was material to my success, and I sometimes thought
            of obtaining my father’s consent to visit England for this purpose; but I clung to every
            pretence of delay, and could not resolve to interrupt my returning tranquillity. My
            health, which had hitherto declined, was now much restored; and my spirits, when
            unchecked by the memory of my unhappy promise, rose proportionably. My father saw this
            change with pleasure, and he turned his thoughts towards the best method of eradicating
            the remains of my melancholy, which every now and then would return by fits, and with a
            devouring blackness overcast the approaching sunshine. At these moments I took refuge in
            the most perfect solitude. I passed whole <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_007" n="003"/>days on
            the lake alone in a little boat, watching the clouds, and listening to the rippling of
            the waves, silent and listless. But the fresh air and bright sun seldom failed to
            restore me to some degree of composure; and, on my return, I met the salutations of my
            friends with a readier smile and a more cheerful heart.</p>
   <p>It was after my return from one of these rambles that my father, calling me aside, thus
            addressed me:—</p>
   <p>“I am happy to remark, my dear son, that you have resumed your former pleasures, and
            seem to be returning to yourself. And yet you are still unhappy, and still avoid our
            society. For some time I was lost in conjecture as to the cause of this; but yesterday
            an idea struck me, and if it is well founded, I conjure you to avow it. Reserve on such
            a point would be not only <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_008" n="004"/>useless, but draw down
            treble misery on us all.”</p>
   <p>I trembled violently at this exordium, and my father continued—</p>
   <p>“I confess, my son, that I have always looked forward to your marriage with your cousin
            as the tie of our domestic comfort, and the stay of my declining years. You were
            attached to each other from your earliest infancy; you studied together, and appeared,
            in dispositions and tastes, entirely suited to one another. But so blind is the
            experience of man, that what I conceived to be the best assistants to my plan may have
            entirely destroyed it. You, perhaps, regard her as your sister, without any wish that
            she might become your wife. Nay, you may have met with another whom you may love; and,
            considering yourself as bound in honour to your cousin, this struggle <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_009" n="005"/>may occasion the poignant misery which you appear to
            feel.”</p>
   <p>“My dear father, re-assure yourself. I love my cousin tenderly and sincerely. I never
            saw any woman who excited, as Elizabeth does, my warmest admiration and affection. My
            future hopes and prospects are entirely bound up in the expectation of our union.”</p>
   <p>“The expression of your sentiments on this subject, my dear Victor, gives me more
            pleasure than I have for some time experienced. If you feel thus, we shall assuredly be
            happy, however present events may cast a gloom over us. But it is this gloom, which
            appears to have taken so strong a hold of your mind, that I wish to dissipate. Tell me,
            therefore, whether you object to an immediate solemnization of the marriage. We have
            been unfortunate, and recent events have drawn us from <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_010" n="006"/>that every-day tranquillity befitting my years and infirmities. You are
            younger; yet I do not suppose, possessed as you are of a competent fortune, that an
            early marriage would at all interfere with any future plans of honour and utility that
            you may have formed. Do not suppose, however, that I wish to dictate happiness to you,
            or that a delay on your part would cause me any serious uneasiness. Interpret my words
            with candour, and answer me, I conjure you, with confidence and sincerity.”</p>
   <p>I listened to my father in silence, and remained for some time incapable of offering
            any reply. I revolved rapidly in my mind a multitude of thoughts, and endeavoured to
            arrive at some conclusion. Alas! to me the idea of an immediate union with my cousin was
            one of horror and dismay. I was bound <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_011" n="007"/>by a solemn
            promise, which I had not yet fulfilled, and dared not break; or, if I did, what manifold
            miseries might not impend over me and my devoted family! Could I enter into a festival
            with this deadly weight yet hanging round my neck, and bowing me to the ground. I must
            perform my engagement, and let the monster depart with his mate, <hi rend="underline">before I allowed myself to enjoy the delight of an union from which I expected peace.</hi></p>
   <p>I remembered also the necessity imposed upon me of either journeying to England, or
            entering into a long correspondence with those philosophers of that country, whose
            knowledge and discoveries were of indispensable use to me in my present undertaking. The
            latter method of obtaining the desired intelligence was dilatory and unsatisfactory:
            besides, any variation was <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_012" n="008"/>agreeable to me, and I
            was delighted with the idea of spending a year or two in change of scene and variety of
            occupation, in absence from my family; during which period some event might happen which
            would restore me to them in peace and happiness: my promise might be fulfilled, and the
            monster have departed; or some accident might occur to destroy him, and put an end to my
            slavery for ever.</p>
   <p>These feelings dictated my answer to my father. I expressed a wish to visit England;
            but, concealing the true reasons of this request, I clothed my desires under the guise
            of wishing to travel and see the world before I sat down for life within the walls of my
            native town.</p>
   <p>I urged my entreaty with earnestness, and my father was easily induced to comply; for a
            more indulgent and <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_013" n="009"/>less dictatorial parent did not
            exist upon earth. Our plan was soon arranged. I should travel to Strasburgh, where
            Clerval would join me. Some short time would be spent in the towns of Holland, and our
            principal stay would be in England. We should return by France; and it was agreed that
            the tour should occupy the space of two years.</p>
   <p>My father pleased himself with the reflection, that my union with Elizabeth should take
            place immediately on my return to Geneva. “These two years,” said he, “will pass
            swiftly, and it will be the last delay that will oppose itself to your happiness. <hi rend="underline">And, indeed, I earnestly desire that period to arrive, when we shall all be united, and
            neither hopes or fears arise to disturb our domestic calm.</hi>”</p>
   <p>“I am content,” I replied, “with <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_014" n="010"/>your
            arrangement. By that time we shall both have become wiser, and I hope happier, than we
            at present are.” I sighed; but my father kindly forbore to question me further
            concerning the cause of my dejection. He hoped that new scenes, and the amusement of
            travelling, would restore my tranquillity.</p>
   <p>I now made arrangements for my journey; but one feeling haunted me, which filled me
            with fear and agitation. During my absence I should leave my friends unconscious of the
            existence of their enemy, and unprotected from his attacks, exasperated as he might be
            by my departure. But he had promised to follow me wherever I might go; and would he not
            accompany me to England? This imagination was dreadful in itself, but soothing, inasmuch
            as it supposed the safety of my friends. I was agonized with the idea of the pos<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_015" n="011"/>sibility that the reverse of this might happen. But
            through the whole period during which I was the slave of my creature, I allowed myself
            to be governed by the impulses of the moment; and my present sensations strongly
            intimated that the fiend would follow me, and exempt my family from the danger of his
            machinations.</p>
   <p>It was in the latter end of August that I departed, to pass two years of exile.
            Elizabeth approved of the reasons of my departure, and only regretted that she had not
            the same opportunities of enlarging her experience, and cultivating her understanding.
            She wept, however, as she bade me farewell, and entreated me to return happy and
            tranquil. “We all,” said she, “depend upon you; and if you are miserable, what must be
            our feelings?”</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_016" n="012"/>I threw myself into the carriage that was to
            convey me away, hardly knowing whither I was going, and careless of what was passing
            around. I remembered only, and it was with a bitter anguish that I reflected on it, to
            order that my chemical instruments should be packed to go with me: for I resolved to
            fulfil my promise while abroad, and return, if possible, a free man. Filled with dreary
            imaginations, I passed through many beautiful and majestic scenes; but my eyes were
            fixed and unobserving. I could only think of the bourne of my travels, and the work
            which was to occupy me whilst they endured.</p>
   <p>After some days spent in listless indolence, during which I traversed many leagues, I
            arrived at Strasburgh, where I waited two days for Clerval. He came. Alas, how great was
            the contrast between <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_017" n="013"/>us! He was alive to every new
            scene; joyful when he saw the beauties of the setting sun, and more happy when he beheld
            it rise, and recommence a new day. He pointed out to me the shifting colours of the
            landscape, and the appearances of the sky. “This is what it is to live,” he cried, “now
            I enjoy existence! But you, my dear Frankenstein, wherefore are you desponding and
            sorrowful?” In truth, I was occupied by gloomy thoughts, and neither saw the descent of
            the evening star, nor the golden sun-rise reflected in the Rhine.—And you, my friend,
            would be far more amused with the journal of Clerval, who observed the scenery with an
            eye of feeling and delight, than to listen to my reflections. I, a miserable wretch,
            haunted by a curse that shut up every avenue to enjoyment.</p>
   <p>We had agreed to descend the Rhine <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_018" n="014"/>in a boat from
            Strasburgh to Rotterdam, whence we might take shipping for London. During this voyage,
            we passed by many willowy islands, and saw several beautiful towns. We staid a day at
            Manheim, and, on the fifth from our departure from Strasburgh, arrived at Mayence. The
            course of the Rhine below Mayence becomes much more picturesque. The river descends
            rapidly, and winds between hills, not high, but steep, and of beautiful forms. We saw
            many ruined castles standing on the edges of precipices, surrounded by black woods, high
            and inaccessible. This part of the Rhine, indeed, presents a singularly variegated
            landscape. In one spot you view rugged hills, ruined castles overlooking tremendous
            precipices, with the dark Rhine rushing beneath; and, on the sudden turn of a
            promontory, flourishing vineyards, with <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_019" n="015"/>green
            sloping banks, and a meandering river, and populous towns, occupy the scene.</p>
   <p>We travelled at the time of the vintage, and heard the song of the labourers, as we
            glided down the stream. Even I, depressed in mind <add place="margin">by remor</add>, and my spirits continually agitated
            by gloomy feelings, even I was pleased. I lay at the bottom of the boat, and, as I gazed
            on the cloudless blue sky, I seemed to drink in a tranquillity to which I had long been
            a stranger. And if these were my sensations, who can describe those of Henry? He felt as
            if he had been transported to Fairy-land, and enjoyed a happiness seldom tasted by man.
            “I have seen,” he said, “the most beautiful scenes of my own country; I have visited the
            lakes of Lucerne and Uri, where the snowy mountains descend almost perpendicu<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_020" n="016"/>larly to the water, casting black and impenetrable
            shades, which would cause a gloomy and mournful appearance, were it not for the most
            verdant islands that relieve the eye by their gay appearance; I have seen this lake
            agitated by a tempest, when the wind tore up whirlwinds of water, and gave you an idea
            of what the water-spout must be on the great ocean, and the waves dash with fury the
            base of the mountain, where the priest and his mistress were overwhelmed by an
            avalanche, and where their dying voices are still said to be heard amid the pauses of
            the nightly wind; I have seen the mountains of La Valais, and the Pays de Vaud: but this
            country, Victor, pleases me more than all those wonders. The mountains of Switzerland
            are more majestic and strange; but there is a charm in the banks of this divine river, 
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_021" n="017"/>that I never before saw equalled. Look at that
            castle which overhangs yon precipice; and that also on the island, almost concealed
            amongst the foliage of those lovely trees; and now that group of labourers coming from
            among their vines; and that village half-hid in the recess of the mountain. Oh, surely,
            the spirit that inhabits and guards this place has a soul more in harmony with man, than
            those who pile the glacier, or retire to the inaccessible peaks of the mountains of our
            own country.”</p>
   <p>Clerval! beloved friend! even now it delights me to record your words, and to dwell on
            the praise of which you are so eminently deserving. He was a being formed in the
                <cit>
         <quote>“very poetry of nature.*”</quote>
         <note>* <bibl>Leigh Hunt’s
                  “Rimini.”</bibl>
         </note>
      </cit> His wild and enthusiastic imagination was chastened
            by the sen<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_022" n="018"/>sibility of his heart. His soul
            overflowed with ardent affections, and his friendship was of that devoted and wondrous
            nature that the worldly-minded teach us to look for only in the imagination. But even
            human sympathies were not sufficient to satisfy his eager mind. The scenery of external
            nature, which others regard only with admiration, he loved with ardour:
            <comment text=" RM: text following for poem appears 2 points smaller "/>
            <cit>
         <quote>
            <lg>
               <l>————————————“The sounding cataract</l>
                  <l>Haunted <hi rend="italic">him</hi> like a passion: the tall rock,</l>
                  <l>The mountain, and the deep and gloomy wood,</l>
                  <l>Their colours and their forms, were then to him</l>
                  <l>An appetite; a feeling, and a love,</l>
                  <l>That had no need of a remoter charm,</l>
                  <l>By thought supplied, or any interest</l>
                  <l>Unborrowed from the eye*.”</l>
            </lg>
         </quote>
         <note>* <bibl>Wordsworth’s "Tintern
                  Abbey."</bibl>
         </note>
      </cit>
   </p>
   <p>And where does he now exist? Is this gentle and lovely being lost forever? Has this
            mind so replete with <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_023" n="019"/>ideas, imaginations fanciful
            and magnificent, which formed a world, whose existence depended on the life of its
            creator; has this mind perished? Does it now only exist in my memory? No, it is not
            thus; your form so divinely wrought, and beaming with beauty, has decayed, but your
            spirit still visits and consoles your unhappy friend.</p>
   <p>Pardon this gush of sorrow; these ineffectual words are but a slight tribute to the
            unexampled worth of Henry, but they soothe my heart, overflowing with the anguish which
            his remembrance creates. I will proceed with my tale.</p>
   <p>Beyond Cologne we descended to the plains of Holland; and we resolved to post the
            remainder of our way; for the wind was contrary, and the stream of the river was too
            gentle to aid us.</p>
   <p>Our journey here lost the interest <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_024" n="020"/>arising from
            beautiful scenery; but we arrived in a few days at Rotterdam, whence we proceeded by sea
            to England. It was on a clear morning, in the latter days of December, that I first saw
            the white cliffs of Britain. The banks of the Thames presented a new scene; they were
            flat, but fertile, and almost every town was marked by the remembrance of some story. We
            saw Tilbury Fort, and remembered the Spanish armada; Gravesend, Woolwich, and Greenwich,
            places which I had heard of even in my country.<comment elem="note"
               type="editor"
               resp="rm"
               text="Mary Shelley’s text gives a date DECEMBER that cannot be reconciled with OCTOBER on                 page 24. Text-base from original editors displays SEPTEMBER. Revised to match                 original edition in PDF source."/>
   </p>
   <p>At length we saw the numerous steeples of London, St. Paul’s towering above all, and
            the Tower famed in English history.</p>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="17"/>
</xml>
