<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
      
      <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C29"/>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="1r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0001.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0001">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0001.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#mws"/> 
         <lb/>satisfied that nothing on earth will have the power <lb/>to interrupt my tranquility.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Do not let this letter disturb you; do not <lb/>answer it tomorrow or the next day or even untill <lb/>you come if it will give you pain. My uncle will <lb/>send me news of your health and if I see but <lb/>one smile on your lips when we meet occasioned <lb/>by this or any other <del rend="strikethrough">happ</del> exertion of mine I <lb/>shall need no other happiness; <lb/>E<shi rend="underline">liz<shi rend="double-underline">abeth</shi>
         </shi>
         <shi rend="underline">L<shi rend="double-underline">avenz</shi>
         </shi>a <lb/>Geneva <lb/>
         <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">April</del> May 18<shi rend="underline">
            <shi rend="sup">th</shi>
         </shi>
         <shi rend="underline">17—— </shi>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>This letter revived in my memory what I had <lb/>before forgotten, the <del rend="strikethrough">tr</del> threat of the fiend.– <shi rend="underline">I will b</shi>e <lb/>
         <shi rend="underline">with you on your wedding night!</shi> Such was my</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="1v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0002.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0002">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0002.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>sentence, and on that night would the dæmon employ <lb/>every art to destroy me and tear me from the <lb/>
         <mod>
                <mdel>p</mdel>
                <add>
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
                <add place="superlinear">glimse of</add>
            </mod> happiness which promised <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> partly to <del rend="strikethrough">so</del> console <lb/>my sufferings. On that night he had determined <lb/>to consummate his crimes by my death. Well be it so; <lb/>a deadly strugle would then assuredly take place <lb/>where if he <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">wer</del>
                <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">should be</del>
                <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
                <add place="superlinear">was</add>
            </mod> victorious I should be at <lb/>peace and his power over me be at an end. If  <lb/>he were vanquished I should <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
            <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
         </add>
         <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">be</add> a free man. Alas! <lb/>what freedom; such as the peasant enjoys when <lb/>his family have been massacred before his <lb/>eyes, his cottage burnt, his lands <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">laid</add>
            waste, and he is <lb/>turned adrift homeless pennyless and alone, but  <lb/>free. Such would be my liberty except that in <lb/>my <del rend="strikethrough">libert</del> Elizabeth I possessed a treasure,
            alas! <lb/>balanced by the horrors of remorse and guilt <lb/>which would pursue me untill death.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Sweet and beloved Elizabeth! I read and <w ana="start"/>re-<lb/>read<w ana="end"/> her letter and some softened feelings stole</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="2r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0003.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0003">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0003.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>
         <add hand="#comp">
            <milestone spanTo="#c58-0003.01" unit="tei:note"/>T.K<anchor xml:id="c58-0003.01"/>
         </add>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Soon after my arrival my father spoke <lb/>of my immediate marriage with my cousin. I <lb/>remained silent.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>"Have you then some other attachment?"<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>"None on earth; I love Elizabeth and look <lb/>foward to our union with delight. Let the <lb/>day therefore be fixed and on it I will consecrate <lb/>my<mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <mdel>
               <add place="intralinear">s</add>
            </mdel>
         </mod>
         <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">self in</add>
         </mod> life or death to the happiness of my cousin.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>My dear Victor do not speak thus. Heavy <lb/>misfortunes have befallen us, but let us only cling <lb/>closer to what remains and transfer our love for <lb/>those whom we have lost <del rend="strikethrough">wh</del> to those who yet <lb/>live. Our circle will be small but bound close <lb/>by the ties of affection and mutual misfortune-</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="2v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0004.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0004">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0004.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>and when time shall have softened your despair <lb/>new and dear cares will be <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> born to replace those
      of <lb/>whom we have been so cruelly deprived."<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Such were the lessons of my father; but to <lb/>me the remembrance of the threat returned nor <lb/>can you wonder that omnipotent as the fiend <lb/>had yet been in his deeds of blood I should almost  <lb/>regard him as invincible, and that when <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">he</add> had <lb/>pronounced the words, <shi rend="underline">I <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">will</del> shall be with you</shi> 
         <lb/>
         <shi rend="underline">on your wedding night</shi>, I should regard the  <lb/>threatened fate as unavoidable. But death was  <lb/>no evil to me if the loss of Elizabeth were balanced <lb/>with it and I therefore with a conten<mod>
            <mdel>d</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">t</add>
         </mod>ed and even <lb/>cheerful countenance agreed with my father <lb/>that if my cousin would consent the ceremony <lb/>should take place in ten days; and thus put as I <lb/>imagined the seal to my fate.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Great God! If for one instant I had though<add place="intralinear">t</add> 
         <lb/>what might be the hellish intention of my fiendish</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="3r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0005.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0005">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0005.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>adversary I would rather have banished myself for <lb/>ever from my native country and wandered <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">a</add>
         </mod> 
         <w ana="start"/>friend<lb/>less<w ana="end"/> outcast over the earth than have consented <lb/>to this miserable marriage. But as if possessed <lb/>of magic powers the monster had blinded me to his real <lb/>intentions and when I thought that I prepared only <lb/>my own death I hastened that of a far dearer victim.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>As the <del rend="strikethrough">th</del> period fixed for our
      marriage drew <lb/>nearer <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">wh</del>
         <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">wh</del> whether from cowardice or a prophetic <lb/>feeling, I felt my heart sink within me. But I concealed <lb/>my feelings by <del rend="strikethrough">b</del> an appearance of hilarity that <lb/>brought smiles and joy to the countenance of my <w ana="start"/>fa<lb/>ther<w ana="end"/> but hardly deceived the ever watchful and <lb/> nicer eye of Elizabeth. She looked forward to our <w ana="start"/>u</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="3v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0006.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0006">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0006.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>nion<w ana="end"/> with placid contentment not unmingled <lb/>with a little fear, which past misfortune had <lb/>impressed, that what now appeared certain and <lb/>tangible happiness might soon dissipate into an <lb/>airy dream and leave no trace but deep and <lb/>everlasting regret.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Preparations were made for the event; <w ana="start"/>congratu<lb/>latory<w ana="end"/> were received, and all wore a smiling <w ana="start"/>appear<lb/>ance<w ana="end"/>. I shut up as well as I could in my own heart <lb/>the anxiety that preyed there and entered with <del rend="strikethrough">sen</del> 
         <lb/>seeming earnestness into the plans of my father <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">altho</del> although they might only serve as the <w ana="start"/>decora<lb/>tions<w ana="end"/> of my tragedy. A house was purchased for us <lb/>near Cologny by which we should enjoy the <w ana="start"/>plea<lb/>sures<w ana="end"/> of the country and yet be so near Gene<retrace cause="unclear">v</retrace>a <lb/>as to see my father every day; who would still <lb/>reside within the walls for the benefit of Ernest that <lb/>he might follow his studies at the schools.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>In the mean time I took every precaution</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="4r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0007.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0007">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0007.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>to defend my person in case the fiend should openly <lb/>attack me. I carried pistols and dagger constantly <lb/>about me and was ever on the watch to prevent <lb/>artifice and by these means gain<add place="intralinear">ed</add> a greter degree
      of <lb/>tanquillity. Indeed as the <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> period approached
      the <lb/>threat appeared more as a delusion not <del rend="strikethrough">bo</del> to be <w ana="start"/>re<lb/>garded<w ana="end"/> as worthy to disturb my peace while the <lb/>happiness I hoped for in my marriage wore <lb/>a greater appearance of certainty as the day fixed <lb/>for its solemnization drew nearer and I heard it <lb/>continully spoken of as an occurrence which no <w ana="start"/>ac<lb/>cident<w ana="end"/> could possibly prevent.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Elizabeth seemed happy and this change <lb/>from mirth to content which she saw come over</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="4v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0008.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0008">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0008.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>me. But on the day that was to fulfil my <del rend="strikethrough">wi</del> wishes <lb/>and my destiny she was melancholy and a presentiment <lb/>of evil pervaded her; and perhaps also she thought <lb/>of the dreadful secret which I had promised to <lb/>reveal to her the following day. My father was in the <lb/>mean time overjoyed, and, <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">in</add>
         </mod> the bustle of <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">pe</del> preparation, <lb/>only observed in the melancholy of his niece the <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">a</del> diffidence of a bride.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>After the ceremony was performed a large <lb/>party assembled at my father's; but it was agreed <lb/>that Elizabeth and I should pass the afternoon <lb/>and night at Evian and return to Cologny the <lb/>next morning. <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">As</add> The day was fair and the <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> 
         <lb/>wind <del rend="strikethrough">was</del> favourable we resolved to go by water.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Those were the last moments of my life <w ana="start"/>du<lb/>ring<w ana="end"/> which I enjoyed the felling of happiness. We <lb/>passed rapidly along; the sun was hot but we were <lb/>sheltered <del rend="strikethrough">by</del> from its rays by a kind of canopy while <lb/>we enjoyed the beauty of the scene; sometimes on</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="5r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0009.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0009">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0009.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>one side of the lake where we saw Mont Salêve, <lb/>the pleasant banks of Montalêgre and at a <w ana="start"/>dis<lb/>tance<w ana="end"/> surmounting all the beeautiful Mont <lb/>Blânc and the assemblage of snowy mountains <lb/>that <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">in vain</add>
         </mod> endeavour <del rend="strikethrough">in va</del> to emulate her; som<add place="intralinear">e</add>times <lb/>coasting the opposite banks we saw the mighty Jura <lb/>opposing its dark side to the ambition that would <lb/>quit its native country and an almost <w ana="start"/>insurmount<lb/>able<w ana="end"/> barrier to the invader who should wish to <lb/>enslave it.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I took the hand of Elizabeth<mod>
            <mdel>s</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">:</add>
         </mod> "You are sorrow <lb/>ful, my love<mod>
            <mdel>;</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">.</add>
         </mod> ah! if you knew what I have suffered <lb/>and what I may yet endure you would endeavour <lb/>to let me taste the quiet, and freedom from despair</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="5v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0010.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0010">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0010.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>that this one day at least permits me to enjoy.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Be happy, my dear Victor, replied Elizabeth, there <lb/>is I hope nothing to distress you; and be assured that <lb/>if a lively joy is not painted in my face my heart is <lb/>contented. Something whispers to me not to depend <lb/>too much on the prospect that is opened before us <lb/>but I will not <del rend="strikethrough">lis</del> listen to such a sinister voice. <lb/>Observe how fast we move along, and how the clouds <lb/>which sometimes obscure, and sometimes rise above <lb/>the dome of Mônt Blânc, under this scene of <lb/>beauty still more interesting. Look also at the <lb/>innumerable fish that are <del rend="strikethrough">smi</del> swimming <lb/>in the clear waters where we can distinguish <lb/>every pebble that lies at the bottom. What a divine <lb/>day<mod>
            <mdel>;</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">!</add>
         </mod> how happy and serene all nature appears!<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Thus Elizabeth endeavoured to divert her <lb/>thoughts and mine from all reflection upon <lb/>melancholy subjects. But her temper was <w ana="start"/>fluc<lb/>tuating<w ana="end"/>; joy for a few instants shone in her</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="6r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0011.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0011">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0011.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">ey</del> eyes but it continually gave place to distraction <lb/>and reverie.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>The sun sunk lower in the heavens; we <lb/>passed the river Drance and observed its path <lb/>through the chasms of the higher and the glens <lb/>of the lower hills. The <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">Ap</del> Alps here come closer <lb/>to the lake and we approached the <w ana="start"/>amphi<lb/>
         <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">thre</del>theatre<w ana="end"/> of mountains which forms the <lb/>eastern boundary of the lake. The spire of Evian <lb/>shone <del rend="strikethrough">un<mod>
               <mdel>t</mdel>
               <add place="intralinear">d</add>
            </mod>e</del> under the woods that surrounded <lb/>it and the range of mountain above mountain <lb/>by which it was overhung.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>The wind which had hitherto carried us <w ana="start"/>a<lb/>long<w ana="end"/> with amazing rapidity sunk at sunset to a</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="6v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0012.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0012">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0012.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>light breeze; the light air just ruffled the water <lb/>and caused a pleasant motion among the trees as <lb/>we approached the shore it wafted the most <w ana="start"/>de<lb/>lightful<w ana="end"/> scent of flowers and hay. The sun sunk <w ana="start"/>be<lb/>neath<w ana="end"/> the horizon as we landed, and as I touched <lb/>the shore I felt those cares and fears revive which <lb/>soon were to clasp me and cling to me forever.</zone>
   </surface>


      <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C30"/>     
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="7r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0013.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0013">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0013.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>
         <milestone spanTo="#c58-0013.03" unit="tei:head"/>Chapter VI<anchor xml:id="c58-0013.03"/>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>It was eight o'clock when we landed; we <w ana="start"/>walk<lb/>ed<w ana="end"/> for a short time on the shore enjoying the <lb/>transitory light and then retired to the inn and <w ana="start"/>con<lb/>templated<w ana="end"/> the lovely scene of waters, woods and mountains <lb/>obscured in darkness yet still displaying the<mod>
            <mdel>y</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">ir</add>
         </mod>
         <del rend="strikethrough">
            <add place="superlinear">black</add>
         </del> 
         <lb/>
         <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">lovely</del>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">black <del rend="strikethrough">black</del>
            </add>
         </mod> outlines. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>The wind which had fallen in the <lb/>south now rose with great violence in the west. The <lb/>moon had reached her summit in the heavens and <lb/>was beginning to descend; the clouds swept across <lb/>it swifter than the flight of the vulture and dim <lb/>me<mod>
            <mdel>r</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">d</add>
         </mod> her rays while the lake reflected the scene of the <lb/>busy heavens <del rend="strikethrough">
            <unclear reason="illegible">se</unclear>
         </del>
      rendered still busier <delSpan rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#c58-0013.02"/>made still <lb/>busier<anchor xml:id="c58-0013.02"/> by the restless waves that were beginning to <lb/>rise. Suddenly a heavy storm of rain descended.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I had been calm during the day but so soon as <lb/>night obscured the shapes of objects a thousand<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> 
         <lb/>fears arose in my mind. I was anxious at watchful</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="7v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0014.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0014">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0014.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>while my right hand grasped a pistol which <lb/>was hidden in my bosom; every sound terrified <lb/>me but I <del rend="strikethrough">s</del> resolved that I would sell my life <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">as</del> dearly <del rend="strikethrough">as possible</del> and not relax the impending <lb/>conflict untill my own life, or that of my <w ana="start"/>adversa<lb/>ry<w ana="end"/> were extinguished.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Elizabeth observed my agitation for some <lb/>time in timid and fearful silence; at length she <lb/>said, What is it that agitates you<del rend="strikethrough">
            <unclear>r</unclear>
         </del>, my dear Victor? <lb/>What is it you fear?<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Oh! peace, peace, my love, replied I, this night <lb/>and all will be safe; but this night is dreadful, <lb/>
         <unclear>—</unclear>very dreadful.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I passed an hour in this state of mind when</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="8r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0015.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0015">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0015.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>suddenly I reflected how dreadful the combat which I <lb/>momentarily expected would be to my wife and <w ana="start"/>earnest<lb/>ly<w ana="end"/> entreated her to retire, resolving not to join her <lb/>untill I had obtained some knowledge as to the <lb/>situation of my enemy.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>She left me, and I continued sometime walking <lb/>up and down the passages of the house and <lb/>inspecting every corner that might afford a <w ana="start"/>re<lb/>treat<w ana="end"/> to my adversary. But I discovered no trace <lb/>of him and was beginning to cons<mod>
            <del rend="overwritten">ider</del>
            <add place="intralinear">jecture</add>
         </mod> that some <lb/>fortunate chance had intervened to prevent <lb/>the execution of his menaces; when suddenly I heard <lb/>a shrill and dreadful scream<mod>
            <mdel>i</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">—</add>
            <mdel>I</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">i</add>
         </mod>t came from the <lb/>room into which Elizabeth had retired<mod>
            <add place="intralinear">.</add>
            <mdel>,</mdel>
            <mdel>a</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">A</add>
         </mod>s I heard <lb/>it, the whole truth rushed into my mind, my arms <lb/>dropped, the motion of every muscle and fibre was <lb/>suspended, I could feel the blood trickling in my veins <lb/>and tingling in the extremities of my limbs. This state <lb/>lasted but for an <mod>
            <mdel>o</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">i</add>
         </mod>nstant; the scream was repeated,</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="8v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0016.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0016">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0016.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>and I rushed into the room. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>Gread God! Why did I not <lb/>then expire! Why am I here to relate the dustruction <lb/>of the best hope and the purest creature of earth. <lb/>She was there, lifeless and inanimate<del rend="strikethrough">;</del> thrown across <lb/>the bed, her head hanging down and her pale and <lb/>distorted features half covered by her hair. <w ana="start"/>Every<lb/>where<w ana="end"/> I turn I see the same figure, her bloodless <lb/>arms and relaxed form flung by the murderer on <lb/>its bridal bier. Could I behold this, and live? Alas! <lb/>life is obstinate and clings closest where it is most <lb/>hated. For a moment only did I lo<mod>
            <mdel>o</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">s</add>
         </mod>e recollection; <lb/>I fainted.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>When I recovered, I found myself surrounded by <lb/>the people of the inn; their countenances expressed</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="9r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0017.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0017">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0017.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>a breathless terror but the horror of others <w ana="start"/>appear<lb/>ed<w ana="end"/> only as a mockery, a shadow of the feelings that <w ana="start"/>op<lb/>pressed<w ana="end"/> me. I escaped from them to the room where <lb/>lay the body of Elizabeth, my love, my wife; so lately <lb/>living, so dear, so worthy. She had been moved from <lb/>the posture in which I had first beheld her, <add place="intralinear">and</add> 
         <lb/>now as she lay her head upon her arm, and a <lb/>handkerchief thrown across her face and neck I <lb/>might have supposed her asleep. I rushed towards <lb/>her, and embraced her with ardour but the <del rend="strikethrough">dealthy</del> 
         <lb/>deathly languour of the limbs told me that what <lb/>I now held in my arms had ceased to be the <w ana="start"/>Eliza<lb/>beth<w ana="end"/> whom I had loved and cherished; the <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">
            <milestone spanTo="#c58-0017.01" unit="tei:note"/>[Vol. III-G 121]<anchor xml:id="c58-0017.01"/>
         </add>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>
         <w ana="start"/>murder<lb/>rous<w ana="end"/> mark of the fiend's grasp was on her neck, <lb/>and the breath had ceased to issue from her lips.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>While I still hung over her in the agony of <lb/>despair, I happened to look up. The <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">windows of the</add>
         </mod> room had <lb/>before been darkened, and I felt a kind of panic on <lb/>seeing the pale yellow light of the moon illuminate</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="9v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0018.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0018">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0018.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>the chamber, the shutters had been thrown back; and, <lb/>with a sensation of horror not be described, <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">I</add>
         </mod> saw <del rend="strikethrough">th</del>at <lb/>the open window a figure the most hidious and <lb/>abhorred. A grin was <del rend="strikethrough">was</del> on the face <add place="superlinear">of</add> the monster; <lb/>he seemed to jeer as with his fiendish finger he pointed <lb/>towards the <del rend="strikethrough">window</del> corpse of my wife. I rushed towards <lb/>the window, and, drawing a pistol from <del rend="strikethrough">the window and</del> 
         <lb/>my bosom, shot; but he eluded me, leapt from his <lb/>station, and running with the swiftness of lightning <lb/>plunged into the lake. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
            <metamark>
               <shi rend="sup">X</shi>
            </metamark>
         </add>The report of the pistol brought <lb/>a crowd into the room; I pointed to where he had <lb/>disappeared and we followed the tract with boats; nets <lb/>were cast but in vain. After passing <del rend="strikethrough">in the</del> severa<add place="intralinear">l</add> 
         <lb/>hours we returned hopeless, most of my companions</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="10r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0019.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0019">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0019.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>believing it <mod>
            <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">to</add>
         </mod> have been a form conjured <del rend="strikethrough">my</del> by my <lb/>fancy. After having landed they proceeded to search the <lb/>country, parties going in different directions among <lb/>the woods and vines.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I did not accompany them; I was exhausted, <lb/>a film covered my eyes and my skin was parched with <lb/>the heat of fever. In this state I lay on a bed <lb/>hardly conscious of what had happened; my eyes <lb/>wandered round the room as if to seek somthing <lb/>that I had lost. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>At length I remembered that my father <lb/>would anxiously expect the return of Elizabeth and <lb/>myself, and that I must return alone. This <w ana="start"/>reflec<lb/>tion<w ana="end"/> brought tears into my eyes and I wept for a long <lb/>time; but my thoughts rambled to various subjects, <lb/>reflecting on my misfortunes and their cause I was <lb/>bewildered in a cloud of wonder and horror. The <lb/>death of William, the execution of Justine, the murder <lb/>of Clerval and lastly of my wife; even at that <w ana="start"/>mo<lb/>ment<w ana="end"/> I knew not that my only remaining friends were</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="10v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0020.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0020">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0020.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>safe from the malignity of the <del rend="strikethrough">friend</del> fiend; my
      father <lb/>even now might <mod>
            <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">be</add>
         </mod> writhing under his grasp and <w ana="start"/>Er<lb/>nest<w ana="end"/> might be dead at his feet. This <del rend="strikethrough">p</del> idea made <lb/>me shudder and recalled me to action; I started up <lb/>and resolved to return to Geneva with all possible <lb/>speed.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>There were no horses to be procured and I must <lb/>return by the lake; but the wind was unfavourable <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">amd</del> and the rain fell in torrents. However it was <lb/>hardly morning and I might reasonably hope to arrive <lb/>by night. I hired men to row and took an oar myself <lb/>for I had always experienced relief from mental <w ana="start"/>tor<lb/>ment<w ana="end"/> in bodily exercise. But the overflowing misery <lb/>I now felt and the excess of agitation that I endured</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5396"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="11r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0021.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0021">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0021.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>rendered me incapable of any exertion. I threw <lb/>down the oar and leaning my head upon my hands <lb/>gave way to every gloomy idea that arose. If I <lb/>looked up I saw the scenes which were familiar <lb/>to me in my happier time and which I had <lb/>contemplated but the day before in the company <lb/>of her who was now but a shadow and a recollection. <lb/>Tears streamed from my eyes, the rain had ceased <lb/>for a moment and I saw the fish play in the  <lb/>waters as they had done a few hours before; they <lb/>had then been observed by Elizabeth. Nothing is <lb/>so painful to the human mind as a great and <lb/>sudden change. The sun might shine, or the clouds <lb/>might lour, but nothing could appear to me as it <lb/>had done the day before. A fiend had snatched <lb/>from me every hope of future happiness; no <w ana="start"/>crea<lb/>ture<w ana="end"/> had ever been so miserable as I was. So <w ana="start"/>fright<lb/>ful<w ana="end"/> an event was single in the history of man.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>But why should I <del rend="strikethrough">dewe</del> dwell upon the <w ana="start"/>inci</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="11v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0022.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0022">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0022.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>dents<w ana="end"/> that followed this last overwhelming event. <lb/>Mine has been a tale of horrors, I have <del rend="strikethrough">now</del> reached <lb/>their acme <del rend="strikethrough">me</del> and what I must now relate can <lb/>but be <del rend="strikethrough">de</del> tedious to you<mod>
            <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">.</add>
            <mdel>no</mdel>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">Know</add>
         </mod> that, one by one, my friends <lb/>were snatched away; I was left desolate. <del rend="strikethrough">
            <unclear>ow</unclear>
         </del> My own <lb/>strength is exhausted; and I must tell in few words <lb/>what remains of my hideous narration.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I arrived at Geneva. My father and Ernest <lb/>yet lived; but the former sunk under the tidings <lb/>that I bore. I see him now, excellent and venerable old <lb/>man; his eyes wandered in vacancy for they had lost <lb/>their charm and delight. His neice, his more than <w ana="start"/>daugh<lb/>ter<w ana="end"/> whom he doated <mod>
            <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">on</add>
         </mod> with all the affection that a <lb/>man in the dec<mod>
            <mdel>t</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">l</add>
         </mod>ine of life having few affections clings</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="12r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0023.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0023">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0023.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>more earnestly to those that remain. Cursed, Cursed <lb/>be the fiend that brought <del rend="strikethrough">wretchedn</del> misery <mod>
            <mdel>of</mdel>
            <add place="superlinear">on</add>
         </mod> his <lb/>grey hairs and domed him to waste in wretchedness. <lb/>He could not live under the horrors that were <lb/>accumulated around him; an approplectic fit was <lb/>brought on and in a few days he died in my arms.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>What then became of me? I know not; I <lb/>lost sensation and chains and darkness were the only <lb/>objects that pressed upon me. Sometimes indeed <lb/>I dreamt that I wandered in flowery meadows and <lb/>pleasant vales with the friends of my youth; but I <lb/>awoke and found myself in a dungeon. Melancholy <lb/>followed but by degrees. I gained a clear conception <lb/>of my miseries and situation and was then released <lb/>from my prison. For they had called me mad <lb/>and during many months, as I understood, a <w ana="start"/>solita<lb/>ry<w ana="end"/> cell had been my habitation. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>But liberty had <lb/>been a useless gift to me had I not <delSpan spanTo="#c58-0023.01"/>at the same <lb/>time that<anchor xml:id="c58-0023.01"/> as I awakened to reason at the same</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="12v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0024.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0024">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0024.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>time awakened to revenge. As the memory of past <lb/>misfortunes prest upon me<add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">,</add> I began to <del rend="strikethrough">f</del> reflect <lb/>on their cause; <mod>
            <mdel>T</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">t</add>
         </mod>he monster whom I had created, the <lb/>miserable dæmon whom I had sent <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">abroard</add>
         </mod> in<del rend="strikethrough">to</del> the world <lb/>for my destruction. I was possessed by a madening <lb/>rage when I thought of him and desired and ardently <lb/>
         <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">prazed</del> prayed that I might have him within <lb/>my grasp to wreak a great and signal revenge on <lb/>his cursed head.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Nor did my hate long confine itself to <w ana="start"/>use<lb/>less<w ana="end"/> wishes; I began to reflect on the best means of <w ana="start"/>se<lb/>curing<w ana="end"/> him, and for this purpose about a month after <lb/>my release I repaired to a criminal judge in the town <lb/>and told him that I had an accusation to make; that</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="13r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0025.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0025">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0025.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>I knew the destroyer of my family and that I required <lb/>him to exert his whole authority for the apprehension <lb/>of the murderer. <lb/>
         <add hand="#comp">
            <milestone spanTo="#c58-0025.01" unit="tei:note"/>
            <unclear>KT</unclear>
         </add>
         <anchor xml:id="c58-0025.01"/>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> The magistrate listened to me with attention <lb/>and kindness. Be assured, sir, said he, no pains or <lb/>exertions on my part shall be spared to discover <lb/>the villain.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I thank you, replied I, listen therefore to the <lb/>deposition that I have to make. It is indeed a tale <lb/>so strange that I should fear you would not <lb/>credit it were there not som<add place="intralinear">e</add>thing in truth which
      how <lb/>ever wonderful forces conviction. The story is too <w ana="start"/>con<lb/>nected<w ana="end"/> to be mistaken for a dream and I have no <lb/>motive for falsehood. My manner as I thus addressed <lb/>him was impressive but calm; I had formed in my <lb/>own heart a resolution to pursue my destroyer to death <lb/>and th<mod>
            <mdel>e</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">is</add>
         </mod> purpose quieted my agony and provisonably <lb/>reconciled me to life. I now related my history briefly but <lb/>with firmness and precision, marking the dates</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="13v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0026.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0026">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0026.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>with accu<mod>
            <mdel>s</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">r</add>
         </mod>acy, and never deviating into invective or <lb/>exclamation. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>The magistrate appeared at first <w ana="start"/>per<lb/>fectly<w ana="end"/> incredulous but as I continued he became more <lb/>attentive and interrested; I saw him sometimes <w ana="start"/>shud<lb/>der<w ana="end"/> with horror, at others a lively surprise <w ana="start"/>unmin<lb/>gled<w ana="end"/> with disbelief was painted on his countenance.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>When I had concluded my narration I said:<add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark>――</metamark>
         </add> 
         <lb/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark>―</metamark>
         </add>This is the being
      whom I accuse and for whose <lb/>detection and punishment I call upon you to exert <lb/>your whole power. It is your duty as a magistrate <lb/>and I believe and hope that your feelings as a <lb/>man will not <del rend="strikethrough">revold</del> revolt from the execution of <lb/>those functions on this occasion."<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>This address caused a considerable change in the</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="14r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0027.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0027">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0027.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>phisiognomy of my auditor. He had heard my story with <lb/>that half kind of belief that is given to a tale of <w ana="start"/>spi<lb/>rits<w ana="end"/> and supernatural events; but when he was <lb/>called upon to act officially in consequence the whole <lb/>tide of his incredulity returned. He however answered <lb/>mildly, "I would willingly afford you every aid <del rend="strikethrough">in
      your</del> 
         <lb/>in your persuit; but the creature of whom you <lb/>speak appears to have powers which would put all <lb/>my exertions to defiance<unclear reason="illegible">:</unclear> Who can follow an<del rend="strikethrough">d</del> animal <lb/>which can traverse the sea of ice, and inhabit caves <lb/>and dens where no man would venture to intrude? <lb/>Besides some months have elapsed since the <w ana="start"/>commis<lb/>sion<w ana="end"/> of his crimes and <del rend="strikethrough">k</del> no one can conjecture to <lb/>what place he has wandered or what region he may <lb/>now inhabit."<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>"I do not doubt that he hovers near the spot <lb/>which I inhabit, and if he has indeed taken refuge <lb/>in the Alps he may be hunted like the chamois and <w ana="start"/>des<lb/>troyed<w ana="end"/> as a beast of prey. But I perceive your thoughts</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="14v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0028.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0028">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0028.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>you do not credit my narrative, and do not intend to <lb/>pursue my enemy with the punishment which <lb/>is his desert.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>As I spoke rage sparkled in my eyes; the <w ana="start"/>ma<lb/>gistrate<w ana="end"/> was intimidated; <mod>
            <mdel>Y</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">y</add>
         </mod>ou are mistaken, said <lb/>he, I will exert myself and if it is in my power to <lb/>seize the monster be assured that he shall suffer <lb/>punishment proportionate to his crimes. But I <lb/>fear from what you have yourself described <lb/>to be his properties that this will prove <w ana="start"/>impracti<lb/>cable<w ana="end"/> and that, while every proper measure is <lb/>pursued, you should endeavour to make up your mind <lb/>to a disappointment.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>That cannot be; but all that I can say will be</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="15r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0029.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0029">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0029.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>of little avail; my revenge is of no moment to you, yet <lb/>while I allow it to be a vice I confess that it is the <w ana="start"/>devour<lb/>ing<w ana="end"/> and only passion of my soul. My rage is <w ana="start"/>unspeaka<lb/>ble<w ana="end"/> when I reflect that the murderer whom I have <lb/>turned loose upon society still exists. You refuse <lb/>my just demand; I have but one resource and I <w ana="start"/>de<lb/>vote<w ana="end"/> myself either in <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">my</add>
         </mod>life or death to his <w ana="start"/>destruc<lb/>tion<w ana="end"/>.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I trembled with excess of agitation as I said this; there <lb/>was a frenzy in my manner, and something I doubt not <lb/>of that haughty fierceness which the martys of old are  <lb/>said to have possessed. But to a Genevan magistrate <lb/>whose mind was occupied by far other ideas than those <lb/>of devotion and heroism, this elevation of mind had much the <lb/>appearance of madness. He endeavoured to soothe me as a <lb/>nurse does a child and reverted to my tale as the effects of <w ana="start"/>deli<lb/>rium<w ana="end"/> 
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>"Man, I cried, how ignorant ar<mod>
            <mdel>e</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">t</add>
         </mod> thou in thy pride of <lb/>wisdom. Cease, you know not what it is you say.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I broke from the house <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">ang</del>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^ ^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">angry and</add>
         </mod> disturbed and retired to <lb/>meditate on some other mode of action.</zone>
   </surface>
      

      <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C31"/>  
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="15v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0030.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0030">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0030.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>
         <milestone spanTo="#c58-0030.01" unit="tei:head"/>Chapter <mod>
            <mdel>7</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">VII</add>
         </mod>
         <anchor xml:id="c58-0030.01"/>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>My present situation was one in which all <w ana="start"/>vo<lb/>luntary<w ana="end"/> thought was swallowed up and lost. I was <w ana="start"/>hur<lb/>ried<w ana="end"/> away by fury; revenge alone endowed me with <lb/>strength and composure, it modelled my feelings and <lb/>allowed me to be <del rend="strikethrough">call</del> calculating and calm at
      periods <lb/>when otherwise delirium or death would have <lb/>been my portion. <milestone unit="tei:p"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>My first resolution was to quit <lb/>Geneva for ever; my country, which when I was <lb/>happy and beloved was dear to me, now in my <lb/>adversity became <del rend="strikethrough">hurf</del>
         <del rend="strikethrough">hurtful</del> hateful. I provided <lb/>myself with a sum of money together with a few <lb/>jewels which had belonged to my mother and departed.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">[</metamark>
         </add>And now my wanderings began which are to cease</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="16r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0031.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0031">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0031.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>but with life. I have traversed a vast portion of the <lb/>earth and have endured all the har<add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">d</add>ships
 which <lb/>travellers in desarts and barbarous countries are wont <lb/>to meet. How I have lived I hardly know; Many times have <lb/>I stretched my <del rend="strikethrough">wear</del> failing limbs <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> on the sandy plain <lb/>and prayed for death. But revenge kept me alive; I <lb/>dared not die and leave my adversary in being.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>When I quitted Geneva <del rend="strikethrough">I</del> my first
      labour was <lb/>to gain some clue <del rend="strikethrough">but</del> by which I might trace the <lb/>steps of my fiendish enemy. But my plan was <w ana="start"/>unset<lb/>tled<w ana="end"/> and I wandered many hours around the confines <lb/>of the <del rend="strikethrough">tw</del> town uncertain what path I should pursue. <lb/>As night approached I found myself <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">and</del>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">at</add>
         </mod> the entrance <lb/>of the cemetary<add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">cemetery</add> where William, Elizabeth and my father <lb/>reposed. I entered it and approached the tomb which <lb/>marked their graves. Every thing was silent except the <lb/>leaves of the trees which were gently agitated by the <lb/>breeze; the night was nearly dark and the scene <lb/>would have been solemn and <del rend="strikethrough">in terresting</del> affecting</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="16v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0032.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0032">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0032.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>even to an uninterested observer; the spirits of the <lb/>departed seemed to flit around and to cast a shadow <lb/>which was felt but seen not around the head of <lb/>the mourner.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>The deep grief which this scene had at first <lb/>excited quickly gave way to rage and despair<unclear reason="illegible">.</unclear> They <lb/>were dead and I lived; their murderer also lived and to <lb/>destroy him I must drag out my weary existence. I <lb/>knelt on the earth and with quivering lips exclaimed; <lb/>"By the sacred earth on which I kneel, by the <lb/>shades that wander near me, by the deep and eternal <lb/>grief that I feel, I swear; And by thee, <del rend="strikethrough">oh</del>O Night, and <lb/>by the spirits that preside over thee, I swear to <lb/>pursue the dæmon who caused this misery untill</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="17r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0033.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0033">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0033.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>he or I shall perish in mortal conflict. For this <lb/>purpose I will preserve my life: to ex<del rend="strikethrough">c</del>e<mod>
            <mdel>
               <unclear reason="illegible">t</unclear>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">c</add>
         </mod>ute this <lb/>dear revenge will I again behold the sun and <lb/>tread the green herbage of earth which otherwise <lb/>should vanish from my eyes for ever. And I call <lb/>on you, spirits of the dead; and on you, wandering <lb/>ministers of vengeance, to aid and conduct me in <lb/>my work. Let the cursed and hellish monster drink <lb/>deep of agony; let him feel the despair that now <lb/>torments me!<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I had begun my adjuration with solemnity, <lb/>and an awe that almost assured me that the shades <lb/>of my murdered friends heard and approved my devotion. <lb/>But <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">rage</del>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">the furies</add>
         </mod> possessed me as I concluded, and rage choaked <lb/>my utterance. <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark function="paragraph">
          [</metamark>
         </add>I was answered through the stillness <lb/>of night by a <del rend="strikethrough">lon</del> loud and fiendish laugh. It rung <lb/>on my ears long and heavily; the mountains re-echoed <lb/>it and I felt as if all hell surrounded me with mock <lb/>ery and laughter. Surely in that moment I should</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5316"
            lry="6772"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="17v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0034.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0034">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0034.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>have been possessed by frenzy and have destroyed my <lb/>miserable existence, but that my vow was heard <lb/>and I was reserved for vengeance. The laughter died <lb/>away when a well known and abhorred voice <w ana="start"/>ap<lb/>parently<w ana="end"/> close to my ear, addressed me in an audible <lb/>whisper; "I am satisfied; <del rend="strikethrough">yo</del> miserable wretch, you <lb/>have determined to live and I am satisfied."<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I darted towards the spot from which the <lb/>sound proceeded but the devil eluded my grasp; <w ana="start"/>sud<lb/>denly<w ana="end"/> the broard disk of the moon arose and shone <lb/>full<del rend="strikethrough">y</del> upon his ghastly and distorted shape as he fled <lb/>with more than mortal speed.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I pursued him; and for many months this <lb/>has been my task. Guided by a slight clue I follow</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="18r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0035.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0035">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0035.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>ed the windings of the Rhone but vainly; the blue <lb/>Mediterranean appeared and by a strange chance <lb/>I saw the fiend enter by night and hide himself <lb/>
         <add place="superlinear">in a vessel </add>bound for the black sea and took my passage in <lb/>the same ship but he escaped I know not how;<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">
            <metamark>[</metamark>
         </add>Amidst the wilds of Tartary and Russia although <lb/>he still evaded me I <del rend="strikethrough">e</del> have ever followed in his <lb/>tract. Sometimes the peasants <add place="intralinear">s</add>cared by <add place="intralinear">t</add>his horrid <lb/>appar<add place="intralinear">i</add>tion informed me of his path; sometimes <lb/>he himself, who feared that if I lost all trace I should <lb/>despair and die, often left some mark to guide <lb/>me. The snows descended on my head and I saw the prin<add place="intralinear">t</add> 
         <lb/>of his huge step on the white plain. To you <delSpan rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#c58-0034.01"/>who <lb/>are<anchor xml:id="c58-0034.01"/> first enterring on life <mod>
            <mdel>an</mdel>
            <add place="superlinear">to whom</add>
         </mod> care is new <del rend="strikethrough">new</del>
         <del rend="strikethrough">to you</del> 
         <lb/>and agony unknown; how can you <del rend="strikethrough">de</del> understand what <lb/>I have felt and still feel. Cold, want and fatigue were <lb/>the least pains which I was destined to endure; I was <lb/>cursed by some devil <mod>
            <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">carried</add>
         </mod> about with me my eternal <lb/>hell; yet still a spirit of good followed and directed</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5408"
            lry="6680"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="18v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0036.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0036">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0036.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>my steps and when I most murmured would <w ana="start"/>sud<lb/>denly<w ana="end"/> extricate me from my seemingly <w ana="start"/>insurmounta<lb/>ble<w ana="end"/> difficulties; sometimes when nature over<mod>
            <mdel>s</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">c</add>
         </mod>ome by <lb/>hunger sunk under the exhaustion a repast was <lb/>prepared for me in the desart that restored and <lb/>insprited me. The fare was indeed coarse, such as <lb/>the peasants of the country ate, but I may not doubt <lb/>that it was <del rend="strikethrough">e</del> set there by the <del rend="strikethrough">sprits</del>
         <del rend="strikethrough">th</del> spirits that <lb/>I invoked to aid me. Often when all was dry, the <w ana="start"/>hea<lb/>vens<w ana="end"/> cloudless and I was parched by thirst, a slight <lb/>cloud would bedim the sky, shed the few drops that <lb/>revived me and vanish.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I followed when I could the courses of the <lb/>rivers but the dæmon generally avoided these as it</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="19r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0037.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0037">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0037.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#mws"/> 
         <lb/>was here that the population of the country chiefly <lb/>collected. In other places human beings were seldom seen <lb/>and I generally subsisted on the wild animals that <lb/>crossed my path. I had money with me and gained the <lb/>friendship of the villagers by distributing it or bringing <lb/>with me some food that I had killed which after <lb/>taking a small part I always presented to those <lb/>who had provided me with fire and utensils for <lb/>cooking. <del rend="strikethrough">My</del>
         <del rend="strikethrough">My life as it passed thus</del>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>
         <milestone spanTo="#c58-0037.01" unit="tei:note"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">F.W/</add>
         <anchor xml:id="c58-0037.01"/>My life as it
      passed thus was indeed hateful to <lb/>me and it was during sleep alone that I could <lb/>taste joy. Oh<mod>
            <mdel>,</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">!</add>
         </mod> blessed sleep! often when most <w ana="start"/>mise<lb/>rable<w ana="end"/> I sank to repose and my dreams lulled me even <lb/>to rapture. The spirit that guarded me had provided</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="19v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0038.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0038">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0038.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>these moments or rather hours of happiness that I might <lb/>retain strength to fulfil my pilgrimage. Deprived of <lb/>this respite I should <mod>
            <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">have</add>
         </mod>sunk under my hardships. <w ana="start"/>Du<lb/>ring<w ana="end"/> the day I was sustained and inspirited by the hope <lb/>of night; for in sleep I <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">saw</del>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">saw</add>
         </mod> my friends, my wife and <lb/>my beloved country; again I saw the benevolent <w ana="start"/>coun<lb/>tenance<w ana="end"/> of my father, heard the silver tones of my <lb/>Elizabeth's voice and beheld Clerval enjoying health <lb/>and youth. Often when wearied by a toilsome march <lb/>I persuaded myself that I was dreaming untill night <lb/>should come and that I should then enjoy <del rend="strikethrough">
            <unclear extent="1" unit="chars"/>
         </del> reality in <lb/>the arms of my dearest friends. What agonizing fondness <lb/>did I feel for them, how did I cling to their dear forms <lb/>as sometimes they haunted even my waking hours, <lb/>and persuade myself that they still lived. At such <lb/>moments vengeance that burned within me died <lb/>in my heart and I pursued my path towards the <lb/>destruction of the dæmon more as a task <del rend="strikethrough">enjo</del> 
         <lb/>enjoined by heaven, as the mechanical impulse</zone>
   </surface>
      
      
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="20r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0039.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0039">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0039.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>words. Prepare! Your toils only begin; wrap yourself up <lb/>in furs and provide food for we shall soon enter <lb/>on a journey where your sufferings will satisfy <lb/>my everlasting hatred. <lb/>
         <milestone spanTo="#c58-0039.01" unit="tei:note"/>
         <add hand="#comp" place="intralinear">F.W/</add>
         <anchor xml:id="c58-0039.01"/>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/>My courage and perseverance were invigorated <lb/>by these scoffing words; I resolved not to fail in my <lb/>purpose; and calling on heaven to support me I <lb/>continued with unabated fervour, to traverse <w ana="start"/>im<lb/>mense<w ana="end"/> desarts untill the ocean appeared at a <lb/>distance and formed the utmost boundary of <lb/>the horizon. Oh! how unlike it was to the blue seas <lb/>of the south<mod>
            <add place="intralinear">!</add>
            <mdel>;</mdel>
         </mod> Covered with ice it was only to be <lb/>distinguished from land by its superior wildness and <lb/>ruggedness. The greeks wept <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">for joy</add>
         </mod>when they beheld the</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="20v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0040.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0040">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0040.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>mediterranean from the hills of Asia; and hailed <lb/>with rapture the boundary of their toils. I did not weep, <lb/>but I knelt down and <del rend="strikethrough">thanked my guiding spirit</del> with <lb/>a full heart thanked my guiding spirit for <w ana="start"/>co<del rend="strikethrough">u</del>nduct<lb/>ing<w ana="end"/> me in <del rend="strikethrough">safete</del> safety to the place where I hoped <w ana="start"/>not<lb/>withstanding<w ana="end"/> my adversary's gibe, to meet and <w ana="start"/>grap<lb/>ple<w ana="end"/> with him.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Some weeks before this period I had procured a <lb/>sledge and <del rend="strikethrough">go</del> dogs and thus traversed the snows with <lb/>inconceivable speed. I know not whether the fiend <lb/>possessed the same advantages but I found that as <lb/>before I had daily lost ground in the pursuit I now <lb/>gained on him; so much so that when I first saw <lb/>the ocean he was but one days <del rend="strikethrough">joury</del> journey in <lb/>advance and I hoped to intercept him before <lb/>he should reach the beach. With new courage <w ana="start"/>there<lb/>fore<w ana="end"/> I pressed on and in two days arrived at a <lb/>wretched hamlet on the sea shore. I enquired</zone>
   </surface>

      
      <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C32"/> 
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="21r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0041.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0041">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0041.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>
         <milestone spanTo="#c58-0041.01" unit="tei:head"/>Walton, in continuation<anchor xml:id="c58-0041.01"/> 
         <lb/>August 2<mod>
            <mdel>5</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">6</add>
         </mod>– 17—<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>You have read this strange and terrific story, <w ana="start"/>Mar<lb/>geret<w ana="end"/>, and do you not feel your blood congealed with <lb/>horror like that which even now curdles mine. <w ana="start"/>Some<lb/>times<w ana="end"/> seized with sudden agony he could not continue <lb/>his tale, at others his <mod>
            <mdel>
               <unclear reason="illegible">b</unclear>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">v</add>
         </mod>oice broken yet piercing uttered <lb/>with difficulty the words so replete with agony. His fine <lb/>and lovely eyes were now lighted up with indignation, <lb/>now subdued to downcast sorrow and infinite <w ana="start"/>wretch<lb/>edness<w ana="end"/>. Sometimes he commanded his countenance and <lb/>tones and related the most horrible incidents with a <lb/>tranquil voice suppressing every mark of agitation, <lb/>then like a volcano bursting forth his face would</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="21v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0042.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0042">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0042.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>suddenly change to an expression of the wildest <lb/>rage as he shrieked out <del rend="strikethrough">his</del> imprecations on his <w ana="start"/>per<lb/>secutor<w ana="end"/>.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>His tale is connected and told with an appearance <lb/>of <del rend="strikethrough">truth</del> the simplest truth, yet I own to you that <lb/>the letters of Felix and Safie which he shewed me, <lb/>and the appar<mod>
            <mdel>
               <mdel>t</mdel>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">i</add>
         </mod>tion of the monster seen from our ship <lb/>brought to me a greater conviction of the truth of <lb/>his narrative than his asservations however earnest <lb/>and connected. Such a monster has then really existence; <lb/>I cannot doubt it, yet I am lost in surprise and <lb/>admiration. Sometimes I endeavoured to gain from <w ana="start"/>Fran<lb/>kenstein<w ana="end"/> the particulars of his creature's formation, but  <lb/>on this point he was impenetrable. Are you mad, my <lb/>friend<mod>
            <mdel>,</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">?</add>
         </mod> said he,<del rend="smear">?</del>
         <mod>
            <mdel>O</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">o</add>
         </mod>r whither does your senseless curiosity <lb/>lead you? Would you also create for yourself and the <lb/>world a dæmoni<mod>
            <mdel>le</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">a</add>
         </mod>c<del rend="strikethrough">l</del> enemy? <mod>
            <mdel>o</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">O</add>
         </mod>r to what do your questions <lb/>lend? Peace, peace! learn my miseries and do not seek</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="22r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0043.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0043">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0043.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>to encrease your own.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Frankenstein discovered <mod>
            <mdel>or</mdel>
            <add hand="#comp" place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">that I</add>
         </mod> made notes <w ana="start"/>concern<lb/>ing<w ana="end"/> his history; he asked to see them and then <lb/>himself <del rend="strikethrough">as</del> corrected and augmented them in many <lb/>places, but principally in giving the life and spirit <lb/>to the conversations he held with his enemy. Si<retrace cause="unclear">n</retrace>ce <lb/>you <del rend="strikethrough">y</del> have preserved my narration, said he, I <lb/>would not that a mutilated one should go down <lb/>to posterity.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Thus <del rend="strikethrough">as</del> has a week passed away while I have <lb/>listened to the strangest tale that ever imagination <lb/>formed. My thoughts and every feeling of my soul have <lb/>been drunk up by the interrest for my guest which <lb/>this tale and his own elevated and gentle manners</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="22v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0044.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0044">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0044.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>have created. I wish to soothe him yet can<del rend="strikethrough">not</del>
         <del rend="strikethrough">o</del> I <lb/>counsel one so infinitely miserable, so destitute <lb/>of every hope of consolation to live? Oh, no! The only <lb/>joy that <add hand="#comp" place="superlinear">he</add> can now know will be when he composes <lb/>his <del rend="strikethrough">h</del> shattered feelings to peace and death; Yet he <lb/>enjoys one comfort the offspring of solitude and <w ana="start"/>de<lb/>lirium<w ana="end"/>; he believes that when in dreams he holds <lb/>converse with his friends and derives from that <lb/>communion consolation for his miseries or <w ana="start"/>ex<lb/>citements<w ana="end"/> to his vengeance that they are not the <lb/>creations of his fancy but the real beings who visit <lb/>him from the regions of a remote world. This <lb/>faith gives a solemnity to his reveries that render <lb/>them to me almost as imposing and inter<del rend="strikethrough">r</del>esting <lb/>as truth.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Our conversations are not always confined <lb/>to his own history and misfortunes. On every <lb/>point of general literature he displays <w ana="start"/>unbound<lb/>ed<w ana="end"/> knowledge and a quick and piercing appre-</zone>
   </surface>
      

      <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C33"/> 
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="23r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0045.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0045">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0045.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>You were hereafter to be hailed as the benefactors <lb/>of your species; your names adored as belonging <lb/>to brave men who encountered death for honor, <lb/>and the benefit of mankind. And now behold! <lb/>with the first imagination of danger, or, if you <lb/>will, the first mighty and terrific trial of your <lb/>courage <del rend="strikethrough">you</del> you shrink away and are content <lb/>to be handed down as men who had not strength <lb/>enough to endure cold and peril, and so, poor <lb/>souls, they were chilly and returned to their warm <lb/>firesides. <del rend="strikethrough">Y</del> Why that requires not this
      preparation; <lb/>Ye need not have come thus far and dragged your <lb/>captain to the shame of a defeat <del rend="strikethrough">t</del> merely to <lb/>prove yourselves cowards. Oh! be men, or be more <lb/>than men. Be steady to your purposes, and firm <lb/>as rock; this ice is not made of such stuff as your <lb/>hearts might be; it is mutable, cannot <w ana="start"/>with<lb/>stand<w ana="end"/> you if you say that it shall not. Do <lb/>not return to your families with the stigma</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="23v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0046.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0046">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0046.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>of disgrace marked on your brows. Return as heroes <lb/>who have fought and conquered and who know <lb/>not what it is to turn their backs on the foe.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>He spoke thus with a voice so modulated <lb/>to the different feelings expressed in his speech, <lb/>with an eye so full of lofty design and heroism, <lb/>that can you wonder that these men were <lb/>moved. They looked at one another and were <lb/>unable to reply. I spoke; I told them to retire <lb/>and consider of what had been said. <mod>
            <mdel>t</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">T</add>
         </mod>hat I would <lb/>not lead them further north if they strenuously <lb/>desired the contrary; but that I hoped that <lb/>with reflection their courage would return. <lb/>They retired and I turned towards my friend but</zone>
   </surface>
      
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="24r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0047.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0047">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0047.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main"> 
         <lb/>sideration of these points and the well <w ana="start"/>balanc<lb/>ing<w ana="end"/> of what you may esteem your duties I leave <lb/>to you. My judgement and ideas are already <lb/>disturbed by the near approach of death. I dare <lb/>not ask you to do what I think right for I <lb/>may still be misled by passion.<handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/>
         <milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>That he should live, to be an instrument of <lb/>mischief disturbs me; in other respects this hour <lb/>when I momentarily expect my release is the only <lb/>happy one which I have enjoyed for several <lb/>years. The forms of the beloved dead flit <lb/>before me and I hasten to their arms.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Farewell, Walton. Seek happiness in tranquillity <lb/>and avoid ambition even if it be only the <lb/>apparently innocent one of distinguishing yourself <lb/>in science &amp; discoveries. Yet why do I say this? <lb/>I have myself been blasted in these hopes, <lb/>yet another may succeed.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>His voice became fainter as he spoke; &amp; <lb/>at length exhausted by his effort he sunk <lb/>into silence. About half an hour afterwards <lb/>he attempted again to speak, but was unable</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="24v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0048.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0048">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0048.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>— he pressed my hand feebly and his eyes <lb/>closed forever while the irradiation of a gentle <lb/>smile past away from his lips.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Margaret, what comment can I make on the <lb/>untimely extinction of this glorious sprit? What <lb/>can I say that will make you understand <lb/>the depth of my sorrow? All that I should <w ana="start"/>ex<lb/>press<w ana="end"/> would be inadequate &amp; feeble. My tears <lb/>flow- My life is overshadowed with a cloud <lb/>of dissappointment. But I journey towards <lb/>England, &amp; I may there find consolation.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I am interrupted&#x97; what do these sounds <lb/>portend? It is midnight. The breeze blows <lb/>fairly; &amp; the watch on deck scarcely stir— <lb/>Again there is a sound as of a human voice <lb/>but hoarser- it comes from the cabin where the <lb/>remains of Frankenstein still lie. I must <lb/>arise<del rend="strikethrough">
            <unclear>s</unclear>
         </del> &amp; examine— Good night
      my sister- –<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Great God! What a scene has just taken <lb/>place- I am yet dizzy with the <w ana="start"/>remem<lb/>brance<w ana="end"/> of it. I hardly know whether I <lb/>shall have the power to detail it; yet the</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="25r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0049.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0049">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0049.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>tale which I have recorded would be incomplete <lb/>without this final &amp; wonderful catastrophe.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I entered the cabin where lay the remains <del rend="strikethrough">of my</del> 
         <lb/>of my ill-fated, &amp; admirable friend. Over him <lb/>hung a form which I cannot find words to <lb/>describe gigantic in stature, yet uncouth &amp; <w ana="start"/>distor<lb/>ted<w ana="end"/> in its proportions. As he hung over the <lb/>coffin his face was hid by long locks of ragged <lb/>hair– <del rend="strikethrough">but</del> but one vast hand was
            extended, <lb/>in colour &amp; apparent texture like that of a <lb/>mummy. When he heard the sound of my <lb/>approach; he ceased to utter exclamations of <lb/>grief &amp; horror, &amp; sprung towards the window. <lb/>Never did I behold a vision so horrible as his <lb/>face, of <del rend="strikethrough">h</del> such loathsome yet apalling <w ana="start"/>hideous<lb/>ness<w ana="end"/>. I shut my eyes involuntarily, as <lb/>recollecting what were my duties with respect <lb/>to this destroyer, I called on him to stay. <lb/>He paused – Looking on me with wonder, &amp; <lb/>again turning towards the lifeless form of his <lb/>creator he seemed to forget <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> my presence; <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">whi</del> and every feature &amp; gesture seemed instigated</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="25v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0050.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0050">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0050.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>by the wildest rage of some uncontrolable passion <lb/>— That is also my victim<mod>
            <mdel>,</mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">!</add>
         </mod> he exclaimed In <lb/>his murder<del rend="strikethrough">e</del> my crimes are consummated — the <lb/>miserable series of my being is wound to its close! <lb/>O Frankenstein – generous &amp; self devoted being <lb/>what does it avail that I ask thee now to <lb/>pardon me. Wherefore do I seek to perish <lb/>in thy stead after I have irretrievably <w ana="start"/>des<lb/>troyed<w ana="end"/> thee, by destroying those thou lovedst <lb/>Alas he is cold.. he <mod>
            <del rend="overwritten">
               <del rend="smear">cannot</del>
            </del>
            <add place="intralinear">may not</add>
         </mod> answer me.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>His voice seemed suffocated, &amp; my first <w ana="start"/>im<lb/>pulses<w ana="end"/> which had suggested to me the duty <lb/>of obeying the dying request of my friend, <lb/>in destroying his enemy, now were suspended <lb/>by a mixture of curiosity &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">pity</del> compassion.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I approached this tremendous being– I dared <lb/>no<mod>
            <mdel>
               <unclear reason="illegible">w</unclear>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">t</add>
         </mod> again <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> raise my looks upon his face— <lb/>there was something so scaring &amp; <w ana="start"/>unearth<lb/>ly<w ana="end"/> in his ugliness. I attempted to speak, <lb/>but his presence was as a burthen which <lb/>held me dumb, &amp; the words died on my <lb/>lips—. The monster continued to utter</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="26r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0051.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0051">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0051.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>wild &amp; incoherent reproaches.. At length I gathered <lb/>resolution to speak, in a pause as it were in <lb/>the tempest of his passion — Your repentance is <lb/>now superflous: I said, If you had listened to <lb/>the voice of conscience, &amp; heeded the stings of <lb/>remorse before you had urged your diabolical <lb/>vengeance to this extremity; Frankenstein would <lb/>yet have lived.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>And do you dream — said the Dæmon,
      do <lb/>you think that I was then dead to agony &amp; <lb/>remorse. – He– he <del rend="strikethrough">ex</del> p continued, pointing to <lb/>the corpse, he suffered not more in <w ana="start"/>consum<lb/>mation<w ana="end"/> of the deed; oh not the ten thousandth <lb/>portion of the anguish that was mine during <lb/>the lingering detail of its execution. A <w ana="start"/>frigh<lb/>tful<w ana="end"/> selfishness hurried me on, while my heart <lb/>was poisoned with remorse. Think ye that <lb/>the groans of Clerval were music to my ear. <lb/>My heart was fashioned to be susceptible of <lb/>love &amp; sympathy, &amp; when wrenched by misery <lb/>to vice &amp; hatred it did not endure the <lb/>violence of the change without torture</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="26v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0052.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0052">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0052.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>such as you cannot even <mod>
            <del rend="overwritten">
               <del rend="smear">
                  <unclear reason="illegible">ing</unclear>
               </del>
            </del>
            <add place="intralinear">im</add>
         </mod>agine— After the <lb/>murder of Clerval I returned to Switzerland <lb/>heart-broken &amp; overcome - I pitied Frankenstein <lb/>My pity ammounted to horror – I abhorred myself. <lb/>But when I discovered that he– the author <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> 
         <lb/>at once of my existence and of all its <w ana="start"/>unspea<lb/>kable<w ana="end"/> torments dared to hope for happiness — <lb/>that whilst he accumulated upon me wretchedness <lb/>&amp; despair, he sought his own enjoyment in <lb/>feelings &amp; passions from the indulgence of <lb/>which I was barred— then impotent envy &amp; <lb/>bitter indignation filled me with an insatiable <lb/>thirst for vengeance. I recollected my threat <lb/>&amp; resolved that it should be accomplished. I <lb/>knew that I was preparing for myselft a deadly <lb/>torture.. but I was the slave not the master <lb/>of an impulse which I detested but could not <lb/>disobey. – Yet when she died! Nay then I <lb/>was not miserable. I had cast off all feeling, <lb/>subdued all anguish to riot in the excess of <lb/>my despair. Evil thenceforth became my good. <lb/>
         <mod>
            <mdel>
               <unclear extent="5" unit="chars"/>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">Urged</add>
         </mod> thus far I had no choice but to adapt</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="27r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0053.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0053">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0053.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>
         <damage/>nature to an element which <add place="superlinear">I</add> had chosen willingly. <lb/>The completion of my demoniacal design <w ana="start"/>thencefor<lb/>ward<w ana="end"/> became an insatiable pasion— And now <lb/>
         <damage/>t is ended— there is my last victim!"<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>I was <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">at first</add>
         </mod> touched by the expression of his misery, <lb/>yet when I called to mind what Frankenstein <lb/>had said of his powers of eloquence &amp; <w ana="start"/>persua<lb/>sion<w ana="end"/>, &amp; when I again cast my eyes on the <lb/>lifeless form of my friend, indignation was <lb/>re-kindled within me. — Wretch, I said, <lb/>it is well that you come here to whine over <lb/>the desolation which you have made – you <lb/>throw a torch into a pile of buildings, &amp; <lb/>when they are consumed you sit among the <lb/>ruins &amp; lament the fall. Hypocritical <lb/>fiend! If he whom you lament still lived, <lb/>still would he be the object, again would he <lb/>become the prey of your accursed vengeance. <lb/>It is not pity that you feel– you lament <lb/>only because the victim of your malignity <lb/>is withdrawn from your power.——<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Oh! it is not thus— not thus – interrupted</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="27v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0054.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0054">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0054.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>the Being=yet such must be the impression <lb/>conveyed to you by what appears to be the <lb/>purport of my actions. – Yet, I seek not a <lb/>fellow-feeling in my misery. No sympathy <lb/>may I ever find. When I first sought it, it <lb/>was the love of virtue. I desired that the feelings <lb/>of happiness &amp; affection with the hope of which <lb/>my whole "being" once overflowed, should be <w ana="start"/>par<lb/>ticipated<w ana="end"/> – But now, that virtue has become <lb/>to me a shadow, &amp; happiness &amp; affection are <lb/>turned into bitter &amp; loath<mod>
            <del rend="overwritten">
               <unclear reason="illegible">some</unclear>
            </del>
            <add place="intralinear">ing</add>
         </mod> despair, in what <lb/>should I seek for sympathy? I am contented <lb/>to suffer alone whilst my sufferings shall <lb/>endure. When I die, I am well satisfied <lb/>that abhorrence &amp; opprobrium should load <lb/>my memory. Once my fancy was soothed with <lb/>dreams of virtue of fame &amp; of enjoyment. <lb/>Once I falsely hoped to meet with beings <lb/>who pardoning my outward form would love me <lb/>for the <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">eminent</del>
            <add place="superlinear">excellent</add>
         </mod> qualities which I was so <lb/>eminently capable of bringing forth. I was</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="28r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0055.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0055">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0055.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>
         <damage/> nourished with high thoughts of honour &amp; <lb/>
         <damage/>lf devotion. But now vice has degraded me <lb/>
         <damage/>neath the meanest animal. No crimes no <lb/>mischief, no malignity no misery can be  <lb/>found parallell with mine. When I call over <lb/>the frightful catalogue of my deeds I cannot <lb/>believe that I am he, whose thoughts were once <lb/>filled with sublime &amp; transcendent visions of <lb/>the beauty &amp; the majesty of goodness – But <lb/>it is even so – The fallen Angel becomes a <lb/>malignant devil – Yet even that enemy of <lb/>God &amp; man had friends &amp; associates in his <lb/>desolation. I am quite alone.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>You, who call Frankenstein your friend, seem <lb/>to have a knowledge of my crimes &amp; his <lb/>misfortunes. But in the detail which he <lb/>gave you of them he could not sum up the <lb/>hours &amp; months of misery which I endured <lb/>wasting in impotent passions. For whilst I <lb/>destroyed his hopes, I did not satisfy my <lb/>own desires. They were forever ardent &amp; craving.</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="28v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0056.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0056">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0056.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>Still I desired love &amp; fellowship, &amp; I was stil<damage/> 
         <lb/>spurned — Was there no injustice in this? <lb/>Am I to be thought the only criminal whi<damage/> 
         <lb/>all human kind sinned against me? — Why d<damage/> 
         <lb/>you not hate <mod>
            <del rend="overwritten">
               <del rend="smear">
                  <unclear reason="illegible">Felix</unclear>
               </del>
            </del>
            <add place="intralinear">Felix</add>
         </mod> who drove his friend f<damage/> 
         <lb/>his door with contumely? Why do you not <lb/>execrate the rustic who sought to destroy th<damage/> 
         <lb/>saviour of his child? Nay, these are virtuo<damage/> 
         <lb/>&amp; immaculate beings. I the miserable &amp; the <lb/>abandoned am an abortion to be spurned at, <lb/>&amp; kicked &amp; trampled upon— Even now my bloo<damage/> 
         <lb/>boils at the recollection <mod>
            <mdel>
               <unclear reason="illegible">t</unclear>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">o</add>
         </mod>f this injustice.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>But it is true that I am a wretch. I <lb/>have murdered the lovely &amp; the helpless. I have <lb/>
         <mod>
            <del rend="overwritten">
               <del rend="smear">
                  <unclear reason="illegible">strangled</unclear>
               </del>
            </del>
            <add place="intralinear">strangled</add>
         </mod> the innocent as they slept, &amp; grasped <lb/>to death <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> his throat who never injured me <lb/>
         <mod>
            <mdel>
               <unclear reason="illegible">an</unclear>
            </mdel>
            <add place="intralinear">or</add>
         </mod> any other living thing. I have devoted <lb/>my creator, <del rend="strikethrough">a spec</del> the select specimen of all <lb/>that <add place="superlinear">is</add> worthy of love &amp; admiration among men, <lb/>to misery: I have pursued him even to that <lb/>irremdiable ruin. There he lies, white &amp; cold</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="29r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0057.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0057">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0057.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>
         <damage/> death. You hate me but your abhorrence cannot <lb/>
         <damage/>al that with which I regard myself. I look <lb/>
         <damage/> the hands which executed that deed, I think <lb/>
         <damage/> the heart in which the imagination of it was <lb/>
         <damage/>ncieved, &amp; long for the moment when they will <lb/>
         <damage/>eet my eyes, when it will haunt my thoughts <lb/>
         <damage/>o more.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Fear not that I shall be the instrument of <lb/>
         <damage/>uture mischief. My work is nearly complete. Neither <lb/>
         <damage/>ours nor any mans death is needed to <w ana="start"/>consum<lb/>
         <damage/>mate<w ana="end"/> the series of my being, &amp; accomplish that <lb/>which must be done; but it requires my own. <lb/>Do not fear that I shall be slow to perform <lb/>this sacrifize. I shall quit your vessel on the <lb/>ice-raft which brought me hither; &amp; shall <lb/>seek with rapid steps, the most northern <w ana="start"/>ex<lb/>tremity<w ana="end"/> of the globe. I shall collect my funeral <lb/>pile, &amp; consume to ashes this miserable frame, <lb/>that its remains may afford no light to any <lb/>curious &amp; unhallowed <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add hand="#mws" place="superlinear">wretch</add>
         </mod> who would create such <lb/>another as I have been. I shall die. I shall <lb/>no longer feel the agonies which now consume</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="29v"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0058.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0058">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0058.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>me, or be the prey of feelings unsatisfied yet <lb/>unquenched. He is <mod>
                        <mdel>h</mdel>
                        <add place="intralinear">d</add>
                  </mod>ead who called me into <lb/>being <mod>
                        <mdel>w</mdel>
                        <add place="intralinear">a</add>
                  </mod>nd when I shall be no more, the <mod>
                        <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
                        <add place="superlinear">very</add>
                  </mod> 
         <w ana="start"/>rem<damage/>
         <lb/>brance<w ana="end"/> of us both will speedily perish. I s<damage/> 
         <lb/>no longer see the sun or stars, or feel the wind<damage/> 
         <lb/>play on my cheeks. Light, feeling &amp; sense wi<damage/> 
         <lb/>pass away. And in this condition must I find <damage/> 
         <lb/>happiness.– Some years ago when the images whi<damage/> 
         <lb/>this world affords first opened upon me, when I <lb/>felt the cheering warmth of summer, &amp; hea<damage/> 
         <lb/>the rustling of leaves &amp; the <del rend="strikethrough">music</del> chirping
                  of <lb/>birds, &amp; these were all to me, I should have wep<damage/> 
         <lb/>to die, &amp; now it is my only consolation. Pollut<damage/> 
         <lb/>by crimes &amp; torn by the bitterest remorse where ca<damage/> 
         <lb/>I find rest but in death.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>Farewell. I leave you, &amp; in you the last of <lb/>hum<retrace cause="unclear">an</retrace> kind whom these eyes will ever
                  behold. <lb/>Farewell, Frankenstein. If thou wert yet alive <lb/>&amp; yet cherished a desire of revenge against me, <lb/>it would be better satiated in my life than my <lb/>destruction. But it was not so. You sought</zone>
   </surface>
        <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="5410"
            lry="6660"
            partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="30r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0059.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0059">
      <graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0059.jp2"/>
      <zone type="main">
         <handShift medium="pen" new="#pbs"/> 
         <lb/>my extinction <del rend="strikethrough">because</del> that I might not cause <lb/>greater wretchedness; &amp; if yet <del rend="strikethrough">by</del> in some mode <lb/>unknown to me, <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">you</del>
            <add place="superlinear">thou</add>
         </mod> hast not ceased to think <lb/>&amp; feel, <mod>
            <del rend="strikethrough">you</del>
            <add place="superlinear">thou</add>
         </mod> desirest not my life for my own <lb/>misery. Blasted as thou wert, my agony <lb/>was still superior to thine: for the bitter sting <lb/>of remorse may not cease to Rankle in my wounds, <lb/>until death shall close them forever.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>But soon, he cried with sad &amp; solemn <w ana="start"/>enthusi<lb/>asm<w ana="end"/>, I shall die, &amp; what I now feel be no <lb/>longer felt. . . Soon these burning miseries will <lb/>be extinct. I shall <mod>
            <add place="sublinear">
               <metamark function="insert">^</metamark>
            </add>
            <add place="superlinear">
               <mod>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">moun</del>
                  <add place="superlinear">ascend</add>
               </mod>
            </add>
         </mod> my funeral pile triumphantly; <lb/>&amp; exult in the agony of the torturing flames. <lb/>The light of that conflagration will fade away. <lb/>
         <del rend="strikethrough">
            <unclear reason="illegible">I know not</unclear>
         </del> My ashes will be swept into the sea <lb/>by the winds. My spirit will sleep in peace; <lb/>or if it thinks will surely not think thus. <lb/>Adieu.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> 
         <lb/>He sprung from the cabin-window, as he said this, <lb/>upon an ice raft which lay close to the vessel; <lb/>he was soon borne away by the waves, &amp; lost <lb/>in the darkness of distance.</zone>
   </surface>
      

      
       
    </xml>
