<!-- 2017-05-30 20:37:29.578633 --><p>&lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C29"/&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818">&lt;p&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">&lt;head&gt; </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">“&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;To&lt;/hi&gt; </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">V&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;ICTOR&lt;/hi&gt; F&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;RANKENSTEIN&lt;/hi&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">Victor Frankenstein. &lt;/head&gt; </rdg></app>&lt;p&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">“&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;MY </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">“My dear Friend, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">DEAREST </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">DEAR </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">FRIEND&lt;/hi&gt;, </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “It gave me the greatest pleasure to receive a letter from my uncle dated at Paris; you are no longer at a formidable distance, and I may hope to see you in less than a fortnight. My poor cousin, how much you must have suffered! I expect to see you looking even more ill than when you quitted Geneva. This winter has been passed most miserably, tortured as I have been by anxious suspense; yet I hope to see peace in your countenance, and to find that your heart is not totally <app><rdg wit="#f1818">devoid </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">void </rdg></app>of comfort and tranquillity. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">“Yet </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">"Yet </rdg></app>I fear that the same feelings now exist that made you so miserable a year ago, even perhaps augmented by time. I would not disturb you at this period, when so many misfortunes weigh upon you; but a conversation that I had with my uncle previous to his departure renders some explanation necessary before we meet. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Explanation! you may possibly say; what can Elizabeth have to explain? If you really say this, my questions are answered, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">I have no more to do than to sign myself your affectionate cousin. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">all my doubts satisfied. </rdg></app>But you are distant from me, and it is possible that you may dread, and yet be pleased with this explanation; and, in a probability of this being the case, I dare not any longer postpone writing what, during your absence, I have often wished to express to you, but have never had the courage to begin. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “You well know, Victor, that our union had been the favourite plan of your parents ever since our <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">infancy. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">intimacy. </rdg></app>We were told this when young, and taught to look forward to it as an event that would certainly take place. We were affectionate playfellows during childhood, and, I believe, dear and valued friends to one another as we grew older. But as brother and sister often entertain a lively affection towards each other, without desiring a more intimate union, may not such also be our case? Tell me, dearest Victor. Answer me, I conjure you, by our mutual happiness, with simple truth—Do you not love another? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “You have travelled; you have spent several years of your life at Ingolstadt; and I confess to you, my friend, that when I saw you last autumn so unhappy, flying to solitude, from the society of every creature, I could not help supposing that you might regret our <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">connection, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">connexion, </rdg></app>and believe yourself bound in honour to <app><rdg wit="#f1818">fulfill </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">fulfil </rdg></app>the wishes of your parents, although they opposed themselves to your inclinations. But this is false reasoning. I confess to you, my <app><rdg wit="#f1818">cousin, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">cowsin, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">friend, </rdg></app>that I love you, and that in my airy dreams of futurity you have been my constant friend and companion. But it is your happiness I desire as well as my own, when I declare to you, that our marriage would render me eternally miserable, unless it were the dictate of your own free choice. Even now I weep to think, that, borne down as you are by the <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">cruellest </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">cruelest </rdg></app>misfortunes, you may stifle, by the word &lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;honour&lt;/hi&gt;, all hope of that love and happiness which would alone restore you to <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">yourself. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">yourself </rdg></app>I, who have so <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">interested </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">disinterested </rdg></app>an affection for you, may increase your miseries <app><rdg wit="#f1818">ten-fold </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">tenfold, </rdg></app>by being an obstacle to your wishes. <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Ah, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">Ah! </rdg></app>Victor, be assured that your cousin and playmate has too sincere a love for you not to be made miserable by this supposition. Be happy, my friend; and if you obey me in this one request, remain satisfied that nothing on earth will have the power to interrupt my tranquillity. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Do not let this letter disturb you; do not answer <app><rdg wit="#f1823">it </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">tomorrow, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">to-morrow, </rdg></app>or the next day, or even until you come, if it will give you pain. My uncle will send me news of your health; and if I see but one smile on your lips when we meet, occasioned by this or any other exertion of mine, I shall need no other happiness. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “E&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;LIZABETH&lt;/hi&gt; L&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;AVENZA&lt;/hi&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Geneva, May 18th, 17—.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; This letter revived in my memory what I had before forgotten, the threat of the <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">fiend—“&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;I </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">fiend—&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;”I </rdg></app>will be with you on your <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">wedding-night!&lt;/hi&gt;” </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">wedding night!”&lt;/hi&gt; </rdg></app>Such was my sentence, and on that night would the dæmon employ every art to destroy me, and tear me from the glimpse of happiness which promised partly to console my sufferings. On that night he had determined to consummate his crimes by my death. Well, be it so; a deadly struggle would then assuredly take place, in which if he <app><rdg wit="#f1818">was </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">were </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">victorious, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">victorious </rdg></app>I should be at peace, and his power over me be at an end. If he were vanquished, I should be a free man. Alas! what freedom? such as the peasant enjoys when his family have been massacred before his eyes, his cottage burnt, his lands laid waste, and he is turned adrift, homeless, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">pennyless, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">penniless, </rdg></app>and alone, but free. Such would be my liberty, except that in my Elizabeth I possessed a treasure; alas! <app><rdg wit="#f1818">balancedby </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">balanced by </rdg></app>those horrors of remorse and guilt, which would pursue me until death. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Sweet and beloved Elizabeth! I read and re-read her letter, and some softened feelings stole into my heart, and dared to whisper <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">paradisaical </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">paradisiacal </rdg></app>dreams of love and joy; but the apple was already eaten, and the angel’s arm bared to drive me from all hope. Yet I would die to make her happy. If the monster executed his threat, death was inevitable; yet, again, I considered whether my marriage would hasten <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">my </rdg></app>fate. My destruction might indeed arrive a few months sooner; but if my torturer should suspect that I postponed it, influenced by his menaces, he would surely find other, and perhaps more dreadful means of revenge. He had vowed &lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;to be with me on my wedding-night&lt;/hi&gt;, yet he did not consider that threat as binding him to peace in the <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">mean time; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">meantime; </rdg></app>for, as if to <app><rdg wit="#f1818">shew </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">show </rdg></app>me that he was not yet satiated with blood, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">he </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">be </rdg></app>had murdered Clerval immediately after the enunciation of his <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">threats. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">threats, </rdg></app>I resolved, therefore, that if my immediate union with my cousin would conduce either to <app><rdg wit="#f1818">her’s </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">hers </rdg></app>or my father’s happiness, my adversary’s designs against my life should not retard it a single hour. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; In this state of mind I wrote to Elizabeth. My letter was calm and affectionate. “I fear, my beloved girl,” I said, “little happiness remains for us on earth; yet all that I may one day enjoy is <app><rdg wit="#f1818">concentered </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">centred </rdg></app>in you. Chase away your idle fears; to you alone do I consecrate my life, and my endeavours for contentment. I have one secret, Elizabeth, a dreadful one; when revealed to you, it will chill your frame with horror, and then, far from being surprised at my misery, you will only wonder that I survive what I have endured. I will confide this tale of misery and terror to you the day after our marriage shall take place; for, my sweet cousin, there must be perfect confidence between us. But until then, I conjure you, do not mention or allude to it. This I most earnestly entreat, and I know you will comply.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; In about a week after the arrival of Elizabeth’s letter, we returned to Geneva. <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">My cousin </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">The sweet girl </rdg></app>welcomed me with warm affection; yet tears were in her eyes, as she beheld my emaciated frame and feverish cheeks. I saw a change in her also. She was thinner, and had lost much of that heavenly vivacity that had before charmed me; but her gentleness, and soft looks of compassion, made her a more fit companion for one blasted and miserable as I was. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; The tranquillity which I now enjoyed did not endure. Memory brought madness with it; and when I thought of what had passed, a real insanity possessed me; sometimes I was furious, and burnt with <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">rage; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">rage, </rdg></app>sometimes low and despondent. I neither <app><rdg wit="#f1818">spoke or looked, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">spoke, nor looked at any one, </rdg></app>but sat motionless, bewildered by the multitude of miseries that overcame me. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Elizabeth alone had the power to draw me from these fits; her gentle voice would soothe me when transported by passion, and inspire me with human feelings when sunk in torpor. She wept with me, and for me. When reason returned, she would remonstrate, and endeavour to inspire me with resignation. Ah! it is well for the unfortunate to be resigned, but for the guilty there is no peace. The agonies of remorse poison the luxury there is otherwise sometimes found in indulging the excess of grief. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Soon after my <app><rdg wit="#f1818">arrival </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">arrival, </rdg></app>my father spoke of my immediate marriage with <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">my cousin. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">Elizabeth. </rdg></app>I remained silent. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Have you, then, some other attachment?” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “None on earth. I love Elizabeth, and look forward to our union with delight. Let the day therefore be fixed; and on it I will consecrate myself, in life or death, to the happiness of my cousin.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “My dear Victor, do not speak thus. Heavy misfortunes have befallen <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">us; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">us, </rdg></app>but let us only cling closer to what remains, and transfer our love for those whom we have <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">lost </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">lost, </rdg></app>to those who yet live. Our circle will be small, but bound close by the ties of affection and mutual misfortune. And when time shall have softened your despair, new and dear objects of care will be born to replace those of whom we have been so cruelly deprived.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Such were the lessons of my father. But to me the remembrance of the threat returned: nor can you wonder, that, omnipotent as the fiend had yet been in his deeds of blood, I <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">should </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">shouid </rdg></app>almost regard him as invincible; and that when he had pronounced the words, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">“&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;I </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">“I </rdg></app>shall be with you on your <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">wedding-night&lt;/hi&gt;,” </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">wedding-night,” </rdg></app>I should regard the threatened fate as unavoidable. But death was no evil to me, if the loss of Elizabeth were balanced with it; and I therefore, with a contented and even cheerful countenance, agreed with my father, that if my cousin would consent, the ceremony should take place in ten days, and thus put, as I imagined, the seal to my fate. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Great God! if for one instant I had thought what might be the hellish intention of my fiendish adversary, I would rather have banished myself for ever from my native country, and wandered a friendless outcast over the earth, than have consented to this miserable marriage. But, as if possessed of magic powers, the monster had blinded me to his real intentions; and when I thought that I <app><rdg wit="#f1831">had </rdg></app>prepared only my own death, I hastened that of a far dearer victim. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; As the period fixed for our marriage drew nearer, whether from cowardice or a prophetic feeling, I felt my heart sink within me. But I concealed my feelings by an appearance of hilarity, that brought smiles and joy to the countenance of my father, but hardly deceived the ever-watchful and nicer eye of Elizabeth. She looked forward to our union with placid contentment, not unmingled with a little fear, which past misfortunes had impressed, that what now appeared certain and tangible happiness, might soon dissipate into an airy dream, and leave no trace but deep and everlasting regret. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Preparations were made for the event; congratulatory visits were received; and all wore a smiling appearance. I shut up, as well as I could, in my own heart the anxiety that preyed there, and entered with seeming earnestness into the plans of my father, although they might only serve as the decorations of my tragedy. <app><rdg wit="#f1823">A. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">Through my father’s exertions, a part of the inheritance of Elizabeth had been restored to her by the Austrian government. </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">A </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">house was purchased for us near Cologny, by which </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">small possession on the shores of Como belonged to her. It was agreed that, immediately after our union, </rdg></app>we should <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">enjoy the pleasures of the country, and yet be so near Geneva as to see my father every day; who would still reside within the walls, for the benefit </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">proceed to Villa Lavenza, and spend our first days </rdg></app>of <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Ernest, that he might follow his studies at the schools. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">happiness beside the beautiful lake near which it stood. </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; In the mean time I took every precaution to defend my person, in case the fiend should openly attack me. I carried pistols and a dagger constantly about me, and was ever on the watch to prevent artifice; and by these means gained a greater degree of tranquillity. Indeed, as the period approached, the threat appeared more as a delusion, not to be regarded as worthy to disturb my peace, while the happiness I hoped for in my marriage wore a greater appearance of certainty, as the day fixed for its <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">solemnization </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">solemnisation </rdg></app>drew nearer, and I heard it continually spoken of as an occurrence which no accident could possibly prevent. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Elizabeth seemed happy; my tranquil demeanour contributed greatly to calm her mind. But on the day that was to <app><rdg wit="#f1818">fulfill </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">fulfil </rdg></app>my wishes and my destiny, she was melancholy, and a presentiment of evil pervaded her; and perhaps also she thought of the dreadful <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">secret, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">secret </rdg></app>which I had promised to reveal to her <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">on </rdg></app>the following day. My father was in the mean time <app><rdg wit="#f1818">overjoyed; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">overjoyed, </rdg></app>and, in the bustle of preparation, only <app><rdg wit="#f1818">observed </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">recognised </rdg></app>in the melancholy of his niece the diffidence of a bride. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; After the ceremony was performed, a large party assembled at my father’s; but it was agreed that Elizabeth and I should <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">pass the afternoon and </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">commence our journey by water, sleeping that </rdg></app>night at Evian, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">return to Cologny the next morning. As the </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">continuing our voyage on the following day. The </rdg></app>day was fair, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">and </rdg></app>the wind favourable, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">we resolved to go by water. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">all smiled on our nuptial embarkation. </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Those were the last moments of my life during which I enjoyed the feeling of happiness. We passed rapidly along: the sun was hot, but we were <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">sheltered </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">Sheltered </rdg></app>from its rays by a kind of canopy, while we enjoyed the beauty of the scene, sometimes on one side of the lake, where we saw Mont Salêve, the pleasant banks of <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Montalêgre, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">Montalègre, </rdg></app>and at a distance, surmounting all, the beautiful Mont <app><rdg wit="#f1818">Blânc, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">Blanc, </rdg></app>and the assemblage of snowy mountains that in vain endeavour to emulate her; sometimes coasting the opposite banks, we saw the mighty Jura opposing its dark side to the ambition that would quit its native country, and an almost insurmountable barrier to the invader who should wish to enslave it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I took the hand of Elizabeth: “You are sorrowful, my love. Ah! if you knew what I have suffered, and what I may yet endure, you would endeavour to let me taste the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">quiet, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">quiet </rdg></app>and freedom from despair, that this one day at least permits me to enjoy.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Be happy, my dear Victor,” replied Elizabeth; <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">“there </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">there </rdg></app>is, I hope, nothing to distress you; and be assured that if a lively joy is not painted in my face, my heart is contented. Something whispers to me not to depend too much on the prospect that is opened before us; but I will not listen to such a sinister voice. Observe how fast we move along, and how the <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">clouds </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">clouds, </rdg></app>which sometimes <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">obscure, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">obscure </rdg></app>and sometimes rise above the dome of Mont <app><rdg wit="#f1818">Blânc, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">Blanc, </rdg></app>render this scene of beauty still more interesting. Look also at the innumerable fish that are swimming in the clear waters, where we can distinguish every pebble that lies at the bottom. What a divine day! how happy and serene all nature appears!” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Thus Elizabeth endeavoured to divert her thoughts and mine from all reflection upon melancholy subjects. But her temper was fluctuating; joy for a few instants shone in her eyes, but it continually gave place to distraction and reverie. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; The sun <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">sunk </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">sank </rdg></app>lower in the heavens; we passed the river Drance, and observed its path through the chasms of the higher, and the glens of the lower hills. The Alps here come closer to the lake, and we approached the amphitheatre of mountains which forms its eastern boundary. The spire of Evian shone under the woods that surrounded it, and the range of mountain above mountain by which it was overhung. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; The wind, which had hitherto <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">carried </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">earned </rdg></app>us along with amazing rapidity, sunk at sunset to a light breeze; the soft air just ruffled the water, and caused a pleasant motion among the trees as we approached the shore, from which it wafted the most delightful scent of flowers and hay. The sun sunk beneath the horizon as we landed; and as I touched the shore, I felt those cares and fears revive, which soon were to clasp me, and cling to me for ever. <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">&lt;/p&gt;&lt;milestone n="21" type="end" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">&lt;/p&gt;&lt;milestone n="22" type="end" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg></app></p>
