<!-- 2017-05-29 16:49:46.760738 --><p><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">&lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C11"/&gt;&lt;milestone n="5" type="start" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">&lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C11"/&gt;&lt;milestone n="6" type="start" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg></app>&lt;head&gt; CHAPTER <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">V. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">VI. </rdg></app>&lt;/head&gt; &lt;p&gt; C&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;LERVAL&lt;/hi&gt; then put the following letter into my hands. <app><rdg wit="#f1818">&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ab&gt; &lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;To&lt;/hi&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;To&lt;/hi&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">It was from my own Elizabeth:— &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “My dearest Cousin, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">V. F&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;RANKENSTEIN&lt;/hi&gt;. </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">&lt;/ab&gt; &lt;p&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">“&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;MY DEAR COUSIN&lt;/hi&gt;, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “ I </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">“I </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">“You </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">cannot describe to you the uneasiness we have all felt concerning your health. We cannot help imagining that your friend Clerval conceals the extent of your disorder: for it is now several months since we have seen your hand-writing; and all this time you </rdg></app>have been <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">obliged to dictate your </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">ill, very ill, and even the constant </rdg></app>letters <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">to Henry. Surely, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">of dear kind Henry are not sufficient to reassure me on your account. You are forbidden to write—to hold a pen; yet one word from you, dear </rdg></app>Victor, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">you must have been exceedingly ill; and </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">is necessary to calm our apprehensions. For a long time I have thought that each post would bring </rdg></app>this <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">makes us all very wretched, as much so nearly as after the death of your dear mother. My uncle was almost persuaded that you were indeed dangerously ill, and could hardly be </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">line, and my persuasions have </rdg></app>restrained <app><rdg wit="#f1831">my uncle </rdg></app>from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Clerval always </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">I have prevented his encountering the inconveniences and perhaps dangers of so long a journey; yet how often have I regretted not being able to perform it myself! I figure to myself that the task of attending on your sick bed has devolved on some mercenary old nurse, who could never guess your wishes, nor minister to them with the care and affection of your poor cousin. Yet that is over now: Clerval </rdg></app>writes <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">that </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">that indeed </rdg></app>you are getting <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">better; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">better. </rdg></app>I eagerly hope that you will confirm this intelligence soon in your own <app><rdg wit="#f1818">hand-writing; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">handwritiug; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">handwriting. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Get well—and return to us. You will find a happy, cheerful home, and friends who love you dearly. </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">for indeed, indeed, Victor, we are all very miserable on this account. Relieve us from this fear, and we shall be the happiest creatures in the world. </rdg></app>Your father’s health is <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">now so </rdg></app>vigorous, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">that he appears ten years younger since last winter. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">and he asks but to see you,—but to be assured that you are well; and not a care will ever cloud his benevolent countenance. How pleased </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1823">, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Ernest also is so much improved, that </rdg></app>you would <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">hardly know him: he is now nearly </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">be to remark the improvement of our Ernest! He is now </rdg></app>sixteen, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">has lost that sickly appearance which he had some years ago; he is grown quite robust and active. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “My uncle and I conversed a long time last night about what profession </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">full of activity and spirit. He is desirous to be a true Swiss, and to enter into foreign service; but we cannot part with him, at least until his elder brother return to us. My uncle is not pleased with the idea of a military career in a distant country; but </rdg></app>Ernest <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">should follow. His constant illness when young has deprived him of the habits of application; and now that he enjoys good health, he is continually </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">never had your powers of application. He looks upon study as an odious fetter;—his time is spent </rdg></app>in the open air, climbing the <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">hills, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">hills </rdg></app>or rowing on the lake. I <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">therefore proposed </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">fear </rdg></app>that he <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">should be a farmer; which you know, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">will </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">Cousin, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">cousin, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">is a favourite scheme of mine. A farmer’s is a very healthy happy life; and the least hurtful, or rather the most beneficial profession of any. My uncle had an idea of his being educated as an advocate, that through his interest he might </rdg></app>become <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">a judge. But, besides that he is not at all fitted for such an occupation, it is certainly more creditable to cultivate the earth for the sustenance of man, than to be the confidant, and sometimes the accomplice, of his vices; which is </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">an idler, unless we yield the point, and permit him to enter on </rdg></app>the profession <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">of a lawyer. I said, that the employments of a prosperous farmer, if they were not a more honourable, they were at least a happier species of occupation than that of a judge, whose misfortune it was always to meddle with the dark side of human nature. My uncle smiled, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">which he has selected. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Little alteration, except the growth of our dear children, has taken place since you left us. The blue lake, </rdg></app>and <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">said, that I ought to be an advocate myself, which put an end to the conversation </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">snow-clad mountains, they never change;—and I think our placid home, and our contented hearts are regulated by the same immutable laws. My trifling occupations take up my time and </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">on </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">on, </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">that subject. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “And now I must tell you a little story that will </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">please, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">please </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">and perhaps </rdg></app>amuse <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">you. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">me, and I am rewarded for any exertions by seeing none but happy, kind faces around me. Since you left us, but one change has taken place in our little household. </rdg></app>Do you <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">not </rdg></app>remember <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Justine Moritz? </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">on what occasion Justine Moritz entered our family? </rdg></app>Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but, through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">her </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">our </rdg></app>house. The republican institutions of our country have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several classes of its inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised, their manners are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same thing as a servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned the duties of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include the idea of ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">“After what I have said, I dare say you well remember the heroine of my little tale: for Justine </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">“Justine, you may remember, </rdg></app>was a great favourite of <app><rdg wit="#f1818">your’s; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">yours; </rdg></app>and I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">ill humour, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">ill-humour, </rdg></app>one glance from Justine could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">professions, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">professions; </rdg></app>I never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">respects </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">respects, </rdg></app>inconsiderate, yet she paid <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">thegreatest </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">the greatest </rdg></app>attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model of all excellence, <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">and </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">and, </rdg></app>endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “When my dearest aunt died, <app><rdg wit="#f1818">everyone </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">every one </rdg></app>was too much occupied in their own grief to notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise her partiality. She was a Roman <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">Catholic; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">catholic; </rdg></app>and I believe her confessor confirmed the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our <app><rdg wit="#f1818">house: </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">house; </rdg></app>she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">forever. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">for ever. </rdg></app>She died on the first approach of cold weather, at the beginning of this last winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little &lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;wives&lt;/hi&gt;, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of age. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">every body. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">everybody. </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “I have written myself into <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">good </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">better </rdg></app>spirits, dear <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">cousin; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">cousin ; </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">yet </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">but my anxiety returns upon me as </rdg></app>I <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">cannot conclude without again anxiously inquiring concerning your health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill, write yourself, and make your father and all </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">conclude. Write, dearest Victor,—one line—one word will be a blessing to us. Ten thousand thanks to Henry for his kindness, his affection, and his many letters: we are sincerely grateful. Adieu! my cousin; take care </rdg></app>of <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">us happy; or——I cannot bear to think of the other side of the question; my tears already flow. Adieu, my dearest cousin. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">yourself; and, I entreat you, write! </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; “E&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;LIZABETH&lt;/hi&gt; L&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;AVENZA&lt;/hi&gt;. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818">“&lt;hi rend="italic"&gt;Geneva, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">&lt;comment&gt; RM: location and date are 2 points smaller than body text &lt;/comment&gt; </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">“Geneva, </rdg></app>March 18th, <app><rdg wit="#f1818">17—&lt;/hi&gt;.” </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">17—. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">17—.” </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; </p>
