<!-- 2017-05-30 20:37:29.578633 --><p><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">&lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C31"/&gt;&lt;milestone n="23" type="start" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">&lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C31"/&gt;&lt;milestone n="24" type="start" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg></app>&lt;head&gt; CHAPTER <app><rdg wit="#f1818">VII. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">XII </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">XXIV. </rdg></app>&lt;/head&gt; &lt;p&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">M&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;Y&lt;/hi&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">My </rdg></app>present situation was one in which all voluntary thought was swallowed up and lost. I was hurried away by fury; revenge alone endowed me with strength and composure; it <app><rdg wit="#f1818">modelled </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">moulded </rdg></app>my feelings, and allowed me to be calculating and calm, at periods when otherwise delirium or death would have been my portion. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; My first <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">resolution </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">resol utibn </rdg></app>was to quit Geneva for ever; my country, which, when I was happy and beloved, was dear to me, now, in my adversity, became hateful. I provided myself with a sum of money, together with a few jewels which had belonged to my mother, and departed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">And </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">And, </rdg></app>now my wanderings began, which are to cease but with life. I have traversed a vast portion of the earth, and have endured all the hardships which travellers, in deserts and barbarous countries, are wont to meet. How I have lived I hardly know; many times have I stretched my failing limbs upon the sandy plain, and prayed for death. But revenge kept me alive; I dared not die, and leave my adversary in being. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; When I quitted Geneva, my first labour was to gain some clue by which I might trace the steps of my fiendish enemy. But my plan was unsettled; and I wandered many hours <app><rdg wit="#f1818">around </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">round </rdg></app>the confines of the town, uncertain what path I should pursue. As night approached, I found myself at the entrance of the cemetery where William, Elizabeth, and my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">father, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">father </rdg></app>reposed. I entered it, and approached the tomb which marked their graves. Every thing was silent, except the leaves of the trees, which were gently agitated by the wind; the night was nearly dark; and the scene would have been solemn and affecting even to an uninterested observer. The spirits of the departed seemed to flit around, and to cast a shadow, which was felt but <app><rdg wit="#f1818">seen not, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">not seen, </rdg></app>around the head of the mourner. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; The deep grief which this scene had at first excited quickly gave way to rage and despair. They were dead, and I lived; their murderer also lived, and to destroy him I must drag out my weary existence. I knelt on the grass, and kissed the earth, and with quivering lips exclaimed, “By the sacred earth on which I kneel, by the shades that wander near me, by the deep and eternal grief that I feel, I swear; and by thee, O Night, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818">by </rdg></app>the spirits that preside over thee, <app><rdg wit="#f1818">I swear </rdg></app>to pursue the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">daemon, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">dæmon, </rdg></app>who caused this misery, until he or I shall perish in mortal conflict. For this purpose I will preserve my life: to execute this dear revenge, will I again behold the sun, and tread the green herbage of earth, which otherwise should vanish from my eyes for ever. And I call on you, spirits of the dead; and on you, wandering ministers of vengeance, to aid and conduct me in my work. Let the cursed and hellish monster drink deep of agony; let him feel the despair that now torments me.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I had begun my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">abjuration </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">adjuration </rdg></app>with solemnity, and an awe which almost assured me that the shades of my murdered friends heard and approved my devotion; but the furies possessed me as I concluded, and rage <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">choaked </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">choked </rdg></app>my utterance. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I was answered through the stillness of night by a loud and fiendish laugh. It rung on my ears long and heavily; the mountains re-echoed it, and I felt as if all hell surrounded me with mockery and laughter. Surely in that moment I should have been possessed by <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">phrenzy, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">frenzy, </rdg></app>and have destroyed my miserable existence, but that my vow was heard, and that I was reserved for vengeance. The laughter died <app><rdg wit="#f1818">away: </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">away; </rdg></app>when a well-known and abhorred voice, apparently close to my ear, addressed me in an audible whisper—“I am satisfied: miserable wretch! you have determined to live, and I am satisfied.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I darted towards the spot from which the sound proceeded; but the devil eluded my grasp. Suddenly the broad disk of the moon arose, and shone full upon his ghastly and distorted shape, as he fled with more than mortal speed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I pursued him; and for many months this has been my task. Guided by a slight clue, I followed the windings of the Rhone, but vainly. The blue Mediterranean appeared; and, by a strange chance, I saw the fiend enter by night, and hide himself in a vessel bound for the Black Sea. I took my passage in the same ship; but he escaped, I know not how. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Amidst the wilds of Tartary and Russia, although he still evaded me, I have ever followed in his track. Sometimes the peasants, scared by this horrid apparition, informed me of his path; sometimes he himself, who feared that if I lost all trace <app><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">of him, </rdg></app>I should despair and die, <app><rdg wit="#f1818">often </rdg></app>left some mark to guide me. The snows descended on my head, and I saw the print of his huge step on the white plain. To you first entering on life, to whom care is new, and agony unknown, how can you understand what I have felt, and still feel? Cold, want, and fatigue, were the least pains which I was destined to endure; I was cursed by some devil, and carried about with me my eternal hell; yet still a spirit of good followed and directed my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">steps, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">steps; </rdg></app>and, when I most murmured, would suddenly extricate me from seemingly insurmountable difficulties. Sometimes, when nature, overcome by hunger, sunk under the exhaustion, a repast was prepared for me in the desert, that restored and inspirited me. The fare <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">was indeed </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">was, indeed, </rdg></app>coarse, such as the peasants of the country ate; but I <app><rdg wit="#f1818">may </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">will </rdg></app>not doubt that it was set there by the spirits that I had invoked to aid me. Often, when all was dry, the heavens cloudless, and I was parched by thirst, a slight cloud would bedim the sky, shed the few drops that revived me, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">vanish. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">vanjsh. </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I followed, when I could, the courses of the rivers; but the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">daemon </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">dæmon </rdg></app>generally avoided these, as it was here that the population of the country chiefly collected. In other places human beings were seldom seen; and I generally subsisted on the wild animals that crossed my path. I had money with me, and gained the friendship of the villagers by distributing <app><rdg wit="#f1818">it, or bringing </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">it; or I brought </rdg></app>with me some food that I had killed, which, after taking a small part, I always presented to those who had provided me with fire and utensils for cooking. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; My life, as it passed thus, was indeed hateful to me, and it was during sleep alone that I could taste joy. O blessed sleep! often, when most miserable, I sank to repose, and my dreams lulled me even to rapture. The spirits that guarded me had provided these moments, or rather hours, of happiness, that I might retain strength to <app><rdg wit="#f1818">fulfill </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">fulfil </rdg></app>my pilgrimage. Deprived of this respite, I should have sunk under my hardships. During the day I was sustained and inspirited by the hope of night: for in sleep I saw my friends, my wife, and my beloved country; again I saw the benevolent countenance of my father, heard the silver tones of my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">Elizabeth’s </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">Elizabeth's </rdg></app>voice, and beheld Clerval enjoying health and youth. Often, when wearied by a toilsome march, I persuaded myself that I was dreaming until night should come, and that I should then enjoy reality in the arms of my dearest friends. What <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">agonizing </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">agonising </rdg></app>fondness did I feel for them! how did I cling to their dear forms, as sometimes they haunted even my waking hours, and persuade myself that they still lived! At such moments vengeance, that burned within me, died in my heart, and I pursued my path towards the destruction of the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">daemon, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">dæmon, </rdg></app>more as a task enjoined by heaven, as the mechanical impulse of some power of which I was unconscious, than as the ardent desire of my soul. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; What his feelings were whom I <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">pursued, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">pursued </rdg></app>I cannot know. Sometimes, indeed, he left marks in writing on the barks of the trees, or cut in stone, that guided me, and instigated my fury. “My reign is not yet over,” (these words were legible in one of these <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">inscriptions); </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">inscriptions;) </rdg></app>“you live, and my power is complete. Follow me; I seek the everlasting ices of the north, where you will feel the misery of cold and frost, to which I am impassive. You will find near this place, if you follow not too tardily, a dead hare; eat, and be refreshed. Come on, my enemy; we have yet to wrestle for our lives; but many hard and miserable hours must you <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">endure, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">endure </rdg></app>until that period shall arrive.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Scoffing devil! Again do I vow vengeance; again do I devote thee, miserable fiend, to torture and death. Never will I <app><rdg wit="#f1818">omit </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">give up </rdg></app>my search, until he or I perish; and then with what <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">ecstasy </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">ecstacy </rdg></app>shall I join my Elizabeth, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818">those </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">my departed friends, </rdg></app>who even now prepare for me the reward of my tedious toil and horrible <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">pilgrimage. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">pilgrimage! </rdg></app>&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; As I still pursued my journey to the northward, the snows thickened, and the cold increased in a degree almost too severe to <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">support. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">-support. </rdg></app>The peasants were shut up in their hovels, and only a few of the most hardy ventured forth to seize the animals whom starvation had forced from their hiding-places to seek for prey. The rivers were covered with ice, and no fish could be procured; and thus I was cut off from my chief article of maintenance. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; The triumph of my enemy increased with the difficulty of my labours. One inscription that he left was in these <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">words: “Prepare! </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">words:—“Prepare! </rdg></app>your toils only begin: wrap yourself in furs, and provide <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">food, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">food; </rdg></app>for we shall soon enter upon a journey where your sufferings will satisfy my everlasting hatred.” &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; My courage and perseverance were invigorated by these scoffing words; I resolved not to fail in my purpose; and, calling on <app><rdg wit="#f1818">heaven </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">Heaven </rdg></app>to support me, I continued with unabated fervour to traverse immense deserts, until the ocean appeared at a distance, and formed the utmost boundary of the horizon. Oh! how unlike it was to the blue seas of the south! Covered with ice, it was only to be distinguished from land by its superior wildness and ruggedness. The Greeks wept for joy when they beheld the Mediterranean from the hills of Asia, and hailed with rapture the boundary of their toils. I did not weep; but I knelt down, and, with a full heart, thanked my guiding spirit for conducting me in safety to the place where I hoped, notwithstanding my adversary’s gibe, to meet and grapple with him. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Some weeks before this period I had procured a sledge and dogs, and thus traversed the snows with inconceivable speed. I know not whether the fiend possessed the same advantages; but I found that, as before I had daily lost ground in the pursuit, I now gained on <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">him; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">him: </rdg></app>so much so, that when I first saw the ocean, he was but one <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">day’s </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">day's </rdg></app>journey in advance, and I hoped to intercept him before he should reach the beach. With new courage, therefore, I pressed on, and in two days arrived at a wretched hamlet on the sea-shore. I <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">inquired </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">enquired </rdg></app>of the inhabitants concerning the fiend, and gained accurate information. A gigantic monster, they said, had arrived the night before, armed with a gun and many pistols; putting to flight the inhabitants of a solitary cottage, through fear of his terrific appearance. He had carried off their store of winter food, and, placing it in a sledge, to draw which he had seized on a numerous drove of trained dogs, he had harnessed them, and the same night, to the joy of the horror-struck villagers, had pursued his journey across the sea in a direction that led to no land; and they conjectured that he must speedily be destroyed by the breaking of the ice, or frozen by the eternal frosts. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; On hearing this information, I suffered a temporary access of despair. He had escaped me; and I must commence a destructive and almost endless journey across the mountainous ices <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">of the ocean,—amidst </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">of-the ocean, —amidst </rdg></app>cold that few of the inhabitants could long endure, and which I, the native of a genial and sunny climate, could not hope to survive. Yet at the idea that the fiend should live and be triumphant, my rage and vengeance returned, and, like a mighty tide, overwhelmed every other feeling. After a slight repose, during which the spirits of the dead hovered round, and instigated me to toil and revenge, I prepared for my journey. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I exchanged my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">land sledge </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">land-sledge </rdg></app>for one fashioned for the inequalities of the <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">frozen ocean; and, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">Frozen Ocean; and </rdg></app>purchasing a plentiful stock of provisions, I departed from land. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; I cannot guess how many days have passed since then; but I have endured misery, which nothing but the eternal sentiment of a just retribution burning within my heart could have enabled me to support. Immense and rugged mountains of ice often barred up my passage, and I often heard the thunder of the ground sea, which threatened my destruction. But again the frost came, and made the paths of the sea secure. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; By the quantity of provision which I had <app><rdg wit="#f1818">consumed </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">consumed, </rdg></app>I should guess that I had passed three weeks in this journey; and the continual protraction of hope, returning back upon the heart, often wrung bitter drops of despondency and grief from my eyes. Despair had indeed almost secured her prey, and I should soon have sunk beneath this <app><rdg wit="#f1818">misery; when once, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">misery. Once, </rdg></app>after the poor animals that <app><rdg wit="#f1818">carried </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">conveyed </rdg></app>me had with incredible toil gained the summit of a sloping <app><rdg wit="#f1818">ice mountain, and one </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">ice-mountain, and one, </rdg></app>sinking under his <app><rdg wit="#f1818">fatigue </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">fatigue, </rdg></app>died, I viewed the expanse before me with anguish, when suddenly my eye caught a dark speck upon the dusky <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">plain. </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">plain, </rdg></app>I strained my sight to discover what it could be, and uttered a wild cry of <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">ecstasy when </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">ecstacy When </rdg></app>I distinguished a sledge, and the distorted proportions of a <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">well-known </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">wellknown </rdg></app>form within. Oh! with what a burning gush did hope revisit my heart! warm tears filled my eyes, which I hastily wiped away, that they might not intercept the view I had of the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">daemon; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">dæmon; </rdg></app>but still my sight was dimmed by the burning drops, until, giving way to the emotions that oppressed me, I wept aloud. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; But this was not the time for <app><rdg wit="#f1818">delay; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">delay: </rdg></app>I disencumbered the dogs of their dead companion, gave them a plentiful portion of food; and, after an hour’s rest, which was absolutely necessary, and yet which was bitterly irksome to me, I continued my route. The sledge was still visible; nor did I again lose sight of it, except at the moments when for a short time some <app><rdg wit="#f1818">ice rock </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">ice-rock </rdg></app>concealed it with its intervening crags. I indeed perceptibly gained on it; and when, after nearly two days’ journey, I beheld my enemy at no more than a mile distant, my heart bounded within me. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; But now, when I appeared almost within grasp of my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">enemy, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">foe, </rdg></app>my hopes were suddenly extinguished, and I lost all trace of him more utterly than I had ever done before. A ground sea was heard; the thunder of its progress, as the waters rolled and swelled beneath me, became every moment more ominous and terrific. I pressed on, but in vain. The wind arose; the sea roared; and, as with the mighty shock of an earthquake, it split, and cracked with a tremendous and overwhelming sound. The work was soon finished: in a few minutes a tumultuous sea rolled between me and my enemy, and I was left drifting on a scattered piece of ice, that was continually lessening, and thus preparing for me a hideous death. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; In this manner many appalling hours passed; several of my dogs died; and I myself was about to sink under the accumulation of distress, when I saw your vessel riding at anchor, and holding forth to me hopes of succour and life. I had no conception that vessels ever came so far north, and was astounded at the sight. I quickly destroyed part of my sledge to construct oars; and by these means was enabled, with infinite fatigue, to move my ice-raft in the direction of your ship. I had determined, if you were <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1831">going </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823">going, </rdg></app>southward, still to trust myself to the mercy of the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">seas, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">seas </rdg></app>rather than abandon my purpose. I hoped to induce you to grant me a boat with which I could pursue my <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">enemy. But </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">enemy.But </rdg></app>your direction was northward. You took me on board when my vigour was exhausted, and I should soon have sunk under my multiplied hardships into a <app><rdg wit="#f1818">death, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">death </rdg></app>which I still <app><rdg wit="#f1818">dread,—for </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">dread—for </rdg></app>my task is unfulfilled. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; Oh! when will my guiding spirit, in conducting me to the <app><rdg wit="#f1818">daemon, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">dæmon, </rdg></app>allow me the rest I so much desire; or must I die, and he yet live? If I do, swear to me, Walton, that he shall not escape; that you will seek him, and satisfy my vengeance in his death. <app><rdg wit="#f1818">Yet, </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">And </rdg></app>do I dare <app><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">to </rdg></app>ask <app><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">of </rdg></app>you to undertake my pilgrimage, to endure the hardships that I have undergone? No; I am not so selfish. Yet, when I am dead, if he should appear; if the ministers of vengeance should conduct him to you, swear that he shall not live—swear that he shall not triumph over my accumulated woes, and <app><rdg wit="#f1818">live </rdg><rdg wit="#f1823 #f1831">survive </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1831">to add </rdg></app>to <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">make another such </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">the list of his dark crimes. </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818">a </rdg></app><app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">wretch as I am. </rdg></app>He is eloquent and persuasive; and once his words had even power over my heart: but trust him not. His soul is as hellish as his form, full of treachery and <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">fiend-like </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">fiendlike </rdg></app>malice. Hear him not; call on the manes of William, Justine, Clerval, Elizabeth, my father, and of the wretched Victor, and thrust your sword into his heart. I will hover near, and direct the steel aright. <app><rdg wit="#f1818 #f1823">&lt;/p&gt;&lt;milestone n="23" type="end" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg><rdg wit="#f1831">&lt;/p&gt;&lt;milestone n="24" type="end" unit="chapter"/&gt; </rdg></app></p>
