<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C25a"/>
    <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="18"/>
    <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_025" n="021"/>
    <head sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_head1"/>CHAPTER II.<head eID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_head1"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1"/>L<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1_hi1"/>ONDON<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1_hi1"/> was our present point of rest; we determined to remain
    several months in this wonderful and celebrated city. Clerval desired the intercourse of
    the men of genius and talent who flourished at this time; but this was with me a
    secondary object; I was principally occupied with the means of obtaining the information
    necessary for the completion of my promise, and quickly availed myself of the letters of
    introduction that I had brought with me, addressed to the most distinguished natural
    philosophers.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p1"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p2"/>If this journey had taken place during <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_026" n="022"/>my days of
    study and happiness, it would have afforded me inexpressible pleasure. But a blight had
    come over my existence, and I only visited these people for the sake of the information
    they might give me on the subject in which my interest was so terribly profound. Company
    was irksome to me; when alone, I could fill my mind with the sights of heaven and earth;
    the voice of Henry soothed me, and I could thus cheat myself into a transitory peace.
    But busy uninteresting joyous faces brought back despair to my heart. I saw an
    insurmountable barrier placed between me and my fellow-men; this barrier was sealed with
    the blood of William and Justine; and to reflect on the events connected with those
    names filled my soul with anguish.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p2"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter18_div4_div20_p3"/>But in Clerval I saw the image of my former self; he was inquisitive, and an<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_027" n="023"/>xious to gain experience and instruction. The
    difference of manners which he observed was to him an inexhaustible source of
    instruction and amusement.</xml>
