<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C07"/>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="1"/>
   <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
   <p> I <hi rend="smallcaps">AM</hi> by birth a Genevese; and my family is one of the most
            distinguished of that republic. My ancestors had been for many years counsellors and
            syndics; and my father had filled several public situations with honour and reputation.
            He was respected by all who knew him for his integrity and indefatigable attention to
            public business. He passed his younger days perpetually occupied by the affairs of <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_052" n="040"/>his country; and it was not until the decline of
            life that he thought of marrying, and bestowing on the state sons who might carry his
            virtues and his name down to posterity.</p>
   <p>As the circumstances of his marriage illustrate his character, I cannot refrain from
            relating them. One of his most intimate friends was a merchant, who, from a flourishing
            state, fell, through numerous mischances, into poverty. This man, whose name was
            Beaufort, was of a proud and unbending disposition, and could not bear to live in
            poverty and oblivion in the same country where he had formerly been distinguished for
            his rank and magnificence. Having paid his debts, therefore, in the most honourable
            manner, he retreated with his daughter to the town of Lucerne, where he lived unknown
            and in wretchedness. My father loved Beau<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_053" n="041"/>fort with
            the truest friendship, and was deeply grieved by his retreat in these unfortunate
            circumstances. He grieved also for the loss of his society, and resolved to seek him out
            and endeavour to persuade him to begin the world again through his credit and
            assistance.</p>
   <p>Beaufort had taken effectual measures to conceal himself; and it was ten months before
            my father discovered his abode. Overjoyed at this discovery, he hastened to the house,
            which was situated in a mean street, near the Reuss. But when he entered, misery and
            despair alone welcomed him. Beaufort had saved but a very small sum of money from the
            wreck of his fortunes; but it was sufficient to provide him with sustenance for some
            months, and in the mean time he hoped to procure some respectable employment in a mer<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_054" n="042"/>chant’s house. The interval was consequently spent
            in inaction; his grief only became more deep and rankling, when he had leisure for
            reflection; and at length it took so fast hold of his mind, that at the end of three
            months he lay on a bed of sickness, incapable of any exertion.</p>
   <p>His daughter attended him with the greatest tenderness; but she saw with despair that
            their little fund was rapidly decreasing, and that there was no other prospect of
            support. But Caroline Beaufort possessed a mind of an uncommon mould; and her courage
            rose to support her in her adversity. She procured plain work; she plaited straw; and by
            various means contrived to earn a pittance scarcely sufficient to support life.</p>
   <p>Several months passed in this manner. Her father grew worse; her time <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_055" n="043"/>was more entirely occupied in attending him; her
            means of subsistence decreased; and in the tenth month her father died in her arms,
            leaving her an orphan and a beggar. This last blow overcame her; and she knelt by
            Beaufort’s coffin, weeping bitterly, when my father entered the chamber. He came like a
            protecting spirit to the poor girl, who committed herself to his care, and after the
            interment of his friend he conducted her to Geneva, and placed her under the protection
            of a relation. Two years after this event Caroline became his wife.</p>
   <p><del rend="strikethrough">When my father became a husband and a parent, he found his time so occupied by the
      duties of his new situation, that he</del><add>As my father’s age encreased he became more attached to the quiet of a domestic life, and he gradually</add> relinquished <del rend="strikethrough">many of</del> his public employments, and
            devoted himself <add place="margin">with ardour </add>to the education of his children. Of these I was the eldest, and the
            destined suc<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_056" n="044"/>cessor to all his labours and utility.
            No creature could have more tender parents than mine. My improvement and health were
            their constant care, especially as I remained for several years their only child. But
            before I continue my narrative, I must record an incident which took place when I was
            four years of age.</p>
   <p>My father had a sister, whom he tenderly loved, and who had married early in life an
            Italian gentleman. Soon after her marriage, she had accompanied her husband into <del>her</del><add>his</add> native country, and for some years my father had very little communication with her. About the time I mentioned she died; and a few months afterwards he received a letter
            from her husband, acquainting him with his intention of marrying an Italian lady, and
            requesting my father to take charge of the in<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_057" n="045"/>fant
            Elizabeth, the only child of his deceased sister. “It is my wish,” he said, “that you
            should consider her as your own daughter, and educate her thus. Her mother’s fortune is
            secured to her, the documents of which I will commit to your keeping. Reflect upon this
            proposition; and decide whether you would prefer educating your niece yourself to her
            being brought up by a stepmother.”</p>
   <p>My father did not hesitate, and immediately went to Italy, that he might accompany the
            little Elizabeth to her future home. I have often heard my mother say, that she was at
            that time the most beautiful child she had ever seen, and shewed <add>every </add>sign<del>s even then</del> of a
            gentle and affectionate disposition. These indications, and a desire to bind as closely
            as possible the ties of domestic love, determined my mother to consider <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_058" n="046"/>Elizabeth as my future wife; a design which she
            never found reason to repent.</p>
   <p>From this time Elizabeth Lavenza became my playfellow, and, as we grew older, my
            friend. She was docile and good tempered, yet gay and playful as a summer insect.
            Although she was lively and animated, her feelings were strong and deep, and her
            disposition uncommonly affectionate. No one could better enjoy liberty, yet no one could
            submit with more grace than she did to constraint and caprice. Her imagination was
            luxuriant, yet her capability of application was great. Her person was the image of her
            mind; her hazel eyes, although as lively as a bird’s, possessed an attractive softness.
            Her figure was light and airy; and, though capable of enduring great fatigue, she
            appeared the most fragile creature in the world. While I admired <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_059" n="047"/>her understanding and fancy, I loved to tend on her,
            as I should on a favourite animal; and I never saw so much grace both of person and mind
            united to so little pretension.</p>
   <p>Every one adored Elizabeth. If the servants had any request to make, it was always
            through her intercession. We were strangers to any species of disunion and dispute; for
            although there was a great dissimilitude in our characters, there was an harmony in that
            very dissimilitude. I was more calm and philosophical than my companion; yet my temper
            was not so yielding. My application was of longer endurance; but it was not so severe
            whilst it endured. I delighted in investigating the facts relative to the actual world;
            she busied herself in following the aërial creations of the poets. The world was to me a
            secret, which I desired to <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_060" n="048"/>discover; to her it was
            a vacancy, which she sought to people with imaginations of her own.</p>
   <p>My brothers were considerably younger than myself; but I had a friend in one of my
            schoolfellows, who compensated for this deficiency. Henry Clerval was the son of a
            merchant of Geneva, an intimate friend of my father. He was a boy of singular talent and
            fancy. <del>I remember, </del>when he was nine years old, he wrote a fairy tale, which was the
            delight and amazement of all his companions. His favourite study consisted in books of
            chivalry and romance; and when very young, I can remember, that we used to act plays
            composed by him out of these favourite books, the principal characters of which were
            Orlando, Robin Hood, Amadis, and St. George.</p>
   <p><del rend="margin_line">No youth could have passed more <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_061" n="049"/>happily than
            mine. My parents were indulgent, and my companions amiable. Our studies were never
            forced; and by some means we always had an end placed in view, which excited us to
            ardour in the prosecution of them. It was by this method, and not by emulation, that we
            were urged to application. Elizabeth was not incited to apply herself to drawing, that
            her companions might not outstrip her; but through the desire of pleasing her aunt, by
            the representation of some favourite scene done by her own hand. We learned Latin and
            English, that we might read the writings in those languages; and so far from study being
            made odious to us through punishment, we loved application, and our amusements would
            have been the labours of other children. Perhaps we did not read so many books, or learn
            languages so <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_062" n="050"/>quickly, as those who are disciplined
            according to the ordinary methods; but what we learned was impressed the more deeply on
            our memories.</del><note resp="#MWS">bad</note><add place="bottom">With what delight do I even now remember the details of our domestic circle, and the happy years of my childhood. Joy attended on my steps—and the ardent affection that attached me to my excellent parents, my beloved Elizabeth, and Henry, the brother of my soul, has given almost a religious and sacred feeling to the recollections of a period passed beneath their eyes, and in their society.</add></p>
   <p>In this description of our domestic circle I include Henry Clerval; for he was
            constantly with us. He went to school with me, and generally passed the afternoon at our
            house: for being an only child, and destitute of companions at home, his father was well
            pleased that he should find associates at our house; and we were never completely happy
            when Clerval was absent.</p>
   <p>I feel pleasure in dwelling on the recollections of childhood, before misfortune had
            tainted my mind, and changed its bright visions of extensive usefulness into gloomy and
            narrow reflections upon self. But, in drawing the picture of my early days, I must not
            omit to record those events which led, by in<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_063" n="051"/>sensible steps to my after tale of misery: for when I would account to myself for the
            birth of that passion, which afterwards ruled my destiny, I find it arise, like a
            mountain river, from ignoble and almost forgotten sources; but, swelling as it
            proceeded, it became the torrent which, in its course, has swept away all my hopes and
            joys.</p>
   <p>Natural philosophy is the genius that has regulated my fate; I desire therefore, in
            this narration, to <del>state</del><add>relate</add> those facts which led to my predilection for that science. When
            I was thirteen years of age, we all went on a party of pleasure to the baths near
            Thonon: the inclemency of the weather obliged us to remain a day confined to the inn. In
            this house I chanced to find a volume of the works of Cornelius Agrippa. I opened it
            with apathy; the theory which he attempts to demonstrate, and the <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_064" n="052"/>wonderful facts which he relates, soon changed this
            feeling into enthusiasm. A new light seemed to dawn upon my mind; and, bounding with
            joy, I communicated my discovery to my father. <del rend="strikethrough">I cannot help remarking here the many
            opportunities instructors possess of directing the attention of their pupils to useful
            knowledge, which they utterly neglect. My father looked</del><add>who looking</add> carelessly at the title-page of
            my book, <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> said, “Ah! Cornelius Agrippa! My dear Victor, do not waste your time upon
            this; it is sad trash.”</p>
   <p>If, instead of this remark, my father had taken the pains to explain to me, that the
            principles of Agrippa had been entirely exploded, and that a modern system of science
            had been introduced, which possessed much greater powers than the ancient, because the
            powers of the latter were chimerical, while <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_065" n="053"/>those
            of the former were real and practical; under such circumstances, I should certainly have
            thrown Agrippa aside, and, with my imagination warmed as it was, should probably have
            applied myself to the more rational theory of chemistry which has resulted from modern
            discoveries. It is even possible, that the train of my ideas would never have received
            the fatal impulse that led to my ruin. But the cursory glance my father had taken of my
            volume by no means assured me that he was acquainted with its contents; and I continued
            to read with the greatest avidity.</p>
   <p>When I returned home, my first care was to procure the whole works of this author, and
            afterwards of Paracelsus and Albertus Magnus. I read and studied the wild fancies of
            these writers with delight; they appeared to me trea<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_066" n="054"/>sures known to few beside myself; and although I often wished to communicate
            these secret stores of knowledge to my father, yet his indefinite censure of my
            favourite Agrippa always withheld me. I disclosed my discoveries to Elizabeth,
            therefore, under a promise of strict secrecy; but she did not interest herself in the
            subject, and I was left by her to pursue my studies alone.</p>
   <p>It may appear very strange, that a disciple of Albertus Magnus should arise in the
            eighteenth century; but our family was not scientifical, and I had not attended any of
            the lectures given at the schools of Geneva. My dreams were therefore undisturbed by
            reality; and I entered with the greatest diligence into the search of the philosopher’s
            stone and the elixir of life. But the latter obtained my most undi<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_067" n="055"/>vided attention: wealth was an inferior object; but what glory would
            attend the discovery, if I could banish disease from the human frame, and render man
            invulnerable to any but a violent death!</p>
   <p>Nor were these my only visions. The raising of ghosts or devils was a promise liberally
            accorded by my favourite authors, the fulfilment of which I most eagerly sought; and if
            my incantations were always unsuccessful, I attributed the failure rather to my own
            inexperience and mistake, than to a want of skill or fidelity in my instructors.</p>
   <p>The natural phænomena that take place every day before our eyes did not escape my
            examinations. Distillation, and the wonderful effects of steam, processes of which my
            favourite authors were utterly ignorant, excited my astonishment; but my utmost wonder
            was <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_068" n="056"/>engaged by some experiments on an air-pump,
            which I saw employed by a gentleman whom we were in the habit of visiting.</p>
   <p>The ignorance of the early philosophers on these and several other points served to
            decrease their credit with me: but I could not entirely throw them aside, before some
            other system should occupy their place in my mind.</p>
   <p>When I was about fifteen years old, we had retired to our house near Belrive, when we
            witnessed a most violent and terrible thunder-storm. It advanced from behind the
            mountains of Jura; and the thunder burst at once with frightful loudness from various
            quarters of the heavens. I remained, while the storm lasted, watching its progress with
            curiosity and delight. As I stood at the door, on a sudden I beheld a stream of fire
            issue from an old and beautiful oak, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_069" n="057"/>which stood
            about twenty yards from our house; and so soon as the dazzling light vanished, the oak
            had disappeared, and nothing remained but a blasted stump. When we visited it the next
            morning, we found the tree shattered in a singular manner. It was not splintered by the
            shock, but entirely reduced to thin ribbands of wood. I never beheld any thing so utterly
            destroyed.</p>
   <p>The catastrophe of this tree excited my extreme astonishment; and I eagerly inquired of
            my father the nature and origin of thunder and lightning. He replied, “Electricity;”
            describing at the same time the various effects of that power. He constructed a small
            electrical machine, and exhibited a few experiments; he made also a kite, with a wire
            and string, which drew down that fluid from the clouds.<note resp="#MWS" cert="low">you said your family was not sientific.</note></p>
   <p>This last stroke completed the overthrow <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_070" n="058"/>of
            Cornelius Agrippa, Albertus Magnus, and Paracelsus, who had so long reigned the lords of
            my imagination. But by some fatality I did not feel inclined to commence the study of
            any modern system; and this disinclination was influenced by the following
            circumstance.</p>
   <p>My father expressed a wish that I should attend a course of lectures upon natural
            philosophy, to which I cheerfully consented. Some accident prevented my attending these
            lectures until the course was nearly finished. The lecture, being therefore one of the
            last, was entirely incomprehensible to me. The professor discoursed with the greatest
            fluency of potassium and boron, of sulphates and oxyds, terms to which I could affix no
            idea; and I became disgusted with the science of natural philosophy, although I still
            read <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_071" n="059"/>Pliny and Buffon with delight, authors, in my
            estimation, of nearly equal interest and utility.</p>
   <p>My occupations at this age were principally the mathematics, and most of the branches
            of study appertaining to that science. I was busily employed in learning languages;
            Latin was already familiar to me, and I began to read some of the easiest Greek authors
            without the help of a lexicon. I also perfectly understood English and German. This is
            the list of my accomplishments at the age of seventeen; and you may conceive that my
            hours were fully employed in acquiring and maintaining a knowledge of this various
            literature.</p>
   <p>Another task also devolved upon me, when I became the instructor of my brothers. Ernest
            was six years younger than myself, and was my principal pu<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_072" n="060"/>pil. He had been afflicted with ill health from his infancy, through which
            Elizabeth and I had been his constant nurses: his disposition was gentle, but he was
            incapable of any severe application. William, the youngest of our family, was yet an
            infant, and the most beautiful little fellow in the world; his lively blue eyes, dimpled
            cheeks, and endearing manners, inspired the tenderest affection.</p>
   <p>Such was our domestic circle, from which care and pain seemed for ever banished. My
            father directed our studies, and my mother partook of our enjoyments. Neither of us
            possessed the slightest pre-eminence over the other; the voice of command was never
            heard amongst us; but mutual affection engaged us all to comply with and obey the
            slightest desire of each other.</p>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="1"/>
</xml>
