<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein"
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 3:  Witness f1823, Collation unit C01</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-10 08:09:03.280903 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation" xml:id="C01">
            <seg xml:id="C01_app1-f1823_start"/>
            <milestone unit="volume"/>
            <milestone type="end" unit="frontmatter"/>
            <milestone type="start" unit="preface"/>PREFACE.<p loc="preface1_p1" ana="Start"/>THE <seg xml:id="C01_app1-f1823_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app2-f1823_start"/>event on which this fiction is founded has been supposed, by Dr. Darwin,
            and some of the physiological writers of Germany, as not of impossible occurrence. I
            shall not be supposed as according the remotest degree of serious faith to such an
            imagination; yet, in assuming it as the basis of a work of fancy, I have not considered
            myself as merely weaving a series of supernatural terrors. The event on which the
            interest of the story depends is exempt from the disadvantages of a mere tale of
            spectres or enchantment. It was recommended by the novelty of the situations which it
            developes; and, however impossible as a physical fact, affords a point of view to the
            imagination for the delineating of human passions more comprehensive and commanding than
            any which the ordinary relations of existing events can yield.<p loc="preface1_p1" ana="End"/>
            <p loc="preface1_p2" ana="Start"/>I have thus endeavoured to
            preserve the truth of the elementary principles of human nature, while I have not
            scrupled to innovate upon their combinations. The Iliad, the tragic poetry of <seg xml:id="C01_app2-f1823_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app3-f1823_start"/>Greece,—Shakespeare, <seg xml:id="C01_app3-f1823_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app4-f1823_start"/>in the <seg xml:id="C01_app4-f1823_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app5-f1823_start"/>Tempest <seg xml:id="C01_app5-f1823_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app6-f1823_start"/>and Midsummer Night’s Dream,—and most especially Milton, in Paradise Lost,
            conform to this rule; and the most humble novelist, who seeks to confer or receive
            amusement from his labours, may, without presumption, apply to prose fiction a licence,
            or rather a rule, from the adoption of which so many exquisite combinations of human
            feeling have resulted in the highest specimens of poetry.<p loc="preface1_p2" ana="End"/>
            <p loc="preface1_p3" ana="Start"/>The circumstance on which
            my story rests was suggested in casual conversation. It was <seg xml:id="C01_app6-f1823_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app7-f1823_start"/>commenced, <seg xml:id="C01_app7-f1823_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app8-f1823_start"/>partly as a source of amusement, and partly as an expedient for exercising
            any untried resources of mind. Other motives were mingled with these, as the work
            proceeded. I am by no means indifferent to the manner in which whatever moral tendencies
            exist in the sentiments or characters it contains shall affect the reader; yet my chief
            concern in this respect has been limited to the avoiding the enervating effects of the
            novels of the present day, and to the exhibition of the amiableness of domestic
            affection, and the excellence of universal virtue. The opinions which naturally spring
            from the character and situation of the hero are by no means to be conceived as existing
            always in my own conviction; nor is any inference justly to be drawn from the following
            pages as prejudicing any philosophical doctrine of whatever kind.<p loc="preface1_p3" ana="End"/>
            <p loc="preface1_p4" ana="Start"/>It is a subject also of
            additional interest to the author, that this story was begun in the majestic region
            where the scene is principally laid, and in society which cannot cease to be regretted.
            I passed the summer of 1816 in the environs of Geneva. The season was cold and rainy,
            and in the evenings we crowded around a blazing wood fire, and occasionally amused
            ourselves with some German stories of ghosts, which happened to fall into our hands.
            These tales excited in us a playful desire of imitation. Two other friends (a tale from
            the pen of one of whom would be far more acceptable to the public than any thing I can
            ever hope to produce) and myself agreed to write each a story, founded on some
            supernatural occurrence.<p loc="preface1_p4" ana="End"/>
            <p loc="preface1_p5" ana="Start"/>The weather, however, suddenly became serene; and my two
            friends left me on a journey among the Alps, and lost, in the magnificent scenes which
            they present, all memory of their ghostly visions. The following tale is the only one
            which has been <seg xml:id="C01_app8-f1823_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app9-f1823_start"/>completed.<p loc="preface1_p5" ana="End"/>
            <milestone type="end" unit="preface"/> 
            <seg xml:id="C01_app9-f1823_end"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
