<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 3:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C01</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 00:49:46.885587 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation" xml:id="C01">
            <seg xml:id="C01_app1-f1831_start"/>
            <milestone n="1" type="start" unit="frontmatter"/>
            <milestone n="1" type="end" unit="frontmatter"/>
            <milestone n="1" type="start" unit="introduction"/>
            <milestone n="1" type="end" unit="introduction"/>
            <milestone n="1" type="start" unit="preface"/>
            <pb xml:id="F1831_v_017"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>T<hi>HE</hi> 
            <seg xml:id="C01_app1-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app2-f1831_start"/>event on which this fiction is founded has been supposed, by Dr. Darwin,
            and some of the physiological writers of Germany, as not of impossible occurrence. I
            shall not be supposed as according the remotest degree of serious faith to such an
            imagination; yet, in assuming it as the basis of a work of fancy, I have not considered
            myself as merely <seg xml:id="C01_app2-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app3-f1831_start"/>weaving <seg xml:id="C01_app3-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app4-f1831_start"/>a series of supernatural terrors. The event on <seg xml:id="C01_app4-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app5-f1831_start"/>which <seg xml:id="C01_app5-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app6-f1831_start"/>the interest of the story depends is exempt from the disadvantages of a
            mere tale of spectres or enchantment. It was recommended by the novelty of the
            situations which it developes; and, however impossible as a physical fact, affords a
            point of view to the imagination for the delineating of human passions more
            comprehensive and commanding than any which the ordinary relations of existing events
            can yield.</p>
            <p>I have thus
            endeavoured to preserve the truth of the elementary <seg xml:id="C01_app6-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app7-f1831_start"/>principles <seg xml:id="C01_app7-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app8-f1831_start"/>of human nature, while I have not scrupled to innovate upon their
            combinations. The Iliad, the tragic poetry of <seg xml:id="C01_app8-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app9-f1831_start"/>Greece,—Shakspeare, <seg xml:id="C01_app9-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app10-f1831_start"/>in the <seg xml:id="C01_app10-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app11-f1831_start"/>Tempest, <seg xml:id="C01_app11-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app12-f1831_start"/>and <seg xml:id="C01_app12-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app13-f1831_start"/>Midsummer <seg xml:id="C01_app13-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app14-f1831_start"/>Night’s Dream,—and most especially Milton, in Paradise Lost, conform to
            this rule; and the most humble novelist, who seeks to confer or receive amusement from
            his labours, may, without presumption, apply to prose fiction a licence, or rather a
            rule, from the adoption of which so many exquisite combinations of human feeling have
            resulted in the highest specimens of <seg xml:id="C01_app14-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app15-f1831_start"/>poetry.</p>
            <p>The <seg xml:id="C01_app15-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app16-f1831_start"/>circumstance on which my story rests was suggested in casual conversation.
            It was <seg xml:id="C01_app16-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app17-f1831_start"/>commenced <seg xml:id="C01_app17-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app18-f1831_start"/>partly as a source of amusement, and partly as an expedient for exercising
            any untried resources of mind. Other motives were <seg xml:id="C01_app18-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app19-f1831_start"/>
            <pb n="2" xml:id="F1831_v_018"/>mingled <seg xml:id="C01_app19-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app20-f1831_start"/>with these, as the work <seg xml:id="C01_app20-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app21-f1831_start"/>proceeded. <seg xml:id="C01_app21-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app22-f1831_start"/>I am by no means indifferent to the manner in which whatever moral
            tendencies exist in the sentiments or characters it contains shall affect the reader;
            yet my chief concern in this respect has been limited to the avoiding the enervating
            effects of the novels of the present day, and to the exhibition <seg xml:id="C01_app22-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app23-f1831_start"/>of <seg xml:id="C01_app23-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app24-f1831_start"/>the amiableness of domestic affection, and the excellence of universal
            virtue. The opinions which naturally spring from the character and situation of the hero
            are by no means to be conceived as existing always in my own conviction; nor is any
            inference justly to be drawn from the following pages as prejudicing any philosophical
            doctrine of whatever <seg xml:id="C01_app24-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app25-f1831_start"/>kind.</p>
            <p>It <seg xml:id="C01_app25-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app26-f1831_start"/>is a subject also of additional interest to the author, that this story
            was begun in the majestic region where the scene is principally laid, and in society
            which cannot cease to <seg xml:id="C01_app26-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app27-f1831_start"/>be <seg xml:id="C01_app27-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app28-f1831_start"/>regretted. I passed the summer of 1816 in the environs of Geneva. The
            season was cold and rainy, and in the evenings we crowded around a blazing wood fire,
            and occasionally amused ourselves with some German stories of ghosts, which happened to
            fall into our hands. These tales excited in us a playful desire of imitation. Two other
            friends (a tale from the pen of one of whom would be far more acceptable to the public
            than any thing I can ever hope to produce) and <seg xml:id="C01_app28-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app29-f1831_start"/>myself <seg xml:id="C01_app29-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app30-f1831_start"/>agreed to write each a story, founded on some supernatural <seg xml:id="C01_app30-f1831_end"/>
            <seg type="invariant-MissingWit" xml:id="C01_app31-f1831_start"/>occurrence.</p>
            <p>The <seg xml:id="C01_app31-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app32-f1831_start"/>weather, however, suddenly became serene; and my two friends left me on a
            journey among the Alps, and lost, in the magnificent scenes which they present, all
            memory of their ghostly visions. The following tale is the only one which has been <seg xml:id="C01_app32-f1831_end"/>
            <seg xml:id="C01_app33-f1831_start"/>completed.</p>
            <p>Marlow,
            September, 1817.</p>
            <milestone n="1" type="end" unit="preface"/> 
            <seg xml:id="C01_app33-f1831_end"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>