<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Bridge Phase 4:  Witness f1823, Collation unit C10</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-05-17 09:45:57.032761 </p>
         </sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="collation" xml:id="C10"><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p133">IT <seg/>was on a dreary night of <seg/>November, <seg/>that I beheld the <seg/>accomplishment of <seg/>my <seg/>toils. <seg/>With an anxiety that almost amounted to <seg/>agony, <seg/>I collected <seg/>the <seg/>instruments of life around <seg/>me, that <seg/>I might infuse a spark of being into the lifeless thing that lay at my feet. It was already one in the <seg/>morning; <seg/>the rain pattered dismally against the panes, and my candle was nearly burnt out, <seg/>when, <seg/>by the glimmer of the <seg/>half-extinguished light, <seg/>I saw the dull yellow eye of the creature <seg/>open; it <seg/>breathed hard, and a convulsive motion agitated its <seg/>limbs.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p134">How <seg/>can I describe my <seg/>emotions <seg/>at this <seg/>catastrophe, <seg/>or how delineate the wretch whom with such infinite pains and care I had endeavoured to <seg/>form? <seg/>His limbs were in <seg/>proportion, <seg/>and I had selected his features as <seg/>beautiful. Beautiful!—Great <seg/>God! His <seg/>yellow <seg/>skin scarcely covered the work of muscles and arteries beneath; his hair <seg/>was of <seg/>a lustrous <seg/>black, <seg/>and <seg/>flowing; <seg/>his teeth of a pearly <seg/>whiteness; <seg/>but these <seg/>luxuriances <seg/>only formed a more horrid contrast with his <seg/>watery eyes, <seg/>that seemed almost of the same colour as the dun white sockets in which they were set, his shrivelled <seg/>complexion, <seg/>and <seg/>straight <seg/>black <seg/>lips.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p135">The <seg/>different accidents of life are not so changeable as the feelings of human nature. I had worked hard for nearly two <seg/>years, <seg/>for the sole purpose of infusing life into an inanimate body. For this I had deprived myself of rest and health. I had desired it with an ardour that far exceeded moderation; but now that I had <seg/>finished, the beauty of the dream vanished, <seg/>and breathless horror and disgust filled my heart. Unable <seg/>to <seg/>endure the aspect of the <seg/>being <seg/>I had created, I rushed out of the <seg/>room, <seg/>and <seg/>continued <seg/>a long time traversing my <seg/>bed-chamber, <seg/>unable to compose my mind to sleep. At <seg/>length <seg/>lassitude succeeded to the tumult I had before <seg/>endured; <seg/>and I threw myself on <seg/>the <seg/>bed in my <seg/>clothes, <seg/>endeavouring to seek a few moments of <seg/>forgetfulness. <seg/>But it was in <seg/>vain: <seg/>I <seg/>slept <seg/>
            <seg/>indeed, <seg/>but I was disturbed by the wildest <seg/>dreams. I thought <seg/>I saw <seg/>Elizabeth, in <seg/>the bloom of <seg/>health, <seg/>walking in the streets of <seg/>Ingolstadt. <seg/>Delighted and <seg/>surprised, <seg/>I embraced <seg/>her; <seg/>but as I imprinted the first kiss on her <seg/>lips, <seg/>they became <seg/>livid <seg/>with the hue of death; her features appeared to <seg/>change, <seg/>and I thought that I held the corpse of my dead mother in my <seg/>arms; a <seg/>shroud <seg/>enveloped <seg/>her <seg/>form, <seg/>and I saw the <seg/>grave-worms <seg/>crawling in the folds of the <seg/>flannel. <seg/>I started <seg/>from <seg/>my sleep with <seg/>horror; <seg/>a cold dew covered my <seg/>forehead, <seg/>my teeth <seg/>chattered, <seg/>and every limb <seg/>became <seg/>
            <seg/>convulsed; <seg/>when, by the dim and yellow light of the <seg/>moon, <seg/>as it forced its way through the <seg/>window shutters, <seg/>I beheld the <seg/>wretch—the <seg/>miserable monster whom I had <seg/>created. <seg/>He held up <seg/>the curtain of <seg/>the <seg/>bed; <seg/>and his <seg/>eyes, <seg/>if eyes they may be <seg/>called, <seg/>were fixed on <seg/>me. His <seg/>jaws <seg/>opened, <seg/>and he muttered some inarticulate <seg/>sounds, <seg/>while a grin wrinkled his cheeks. He might have <seg/>spoken, <seg/>but I did not <seg/>hear; <seg/>one hand was stretched <seg/>out, seemingly <seg/>to detain <seg/>me, <seg/>but I <seg/>escaped, <seg/>and rushed down <seg/>stairs. <seg/>I took refuge in <seg/>the <seg/>court-yard belonging to the house which I inhabited; where I remained during the rest of the <seg/>night, <seg/>walking up and down in the greatest <seg/>agitation, <seg/>listening attentively, catching and fearing each sound as if it were to announce the <seg/>approach <seg/>of the demoniacal corpse to which I had so miserably given <seg/>life.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p136">Oh! <seg/>no mortal could support the horror of that countenance. A mummy <seg/>again <seg/>endued with <seg/>animation <seg/>could not be so hideous as <seg/>that wretch. <seg/>I had gazed on him while unfinished; he was ugly <seg/>then; <seg/>but when those muscles and joints were <seg/>rendered capable of motion, <seg/>it became a thing such as even Dante could <seg/>not <seg/>have <seg/>conceived.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p137">I <seg/>passed the night <seg/>wretchedly. <seg/>Sometimes my <seg/>pulse <seg/>beat so quickly and <seg/>hardly, <seg/>that I felt the palpitation of every <seg/>artery; <seg/>at <seg/>others, <seg/>I nearly <seg/>sank <seg/>to the ground <seg/>through <seg/>languor and extreme weakness. Mingled with this <seg/>horror, <seg/>I felt the bitterness of <seg/>disappointment; <seg/>dreams that had been my food and <seg/>pleasant <seg/>rest for so long a <seg/>space, <seg/>were now become a hell to <seg/>me; <seg/>and the change was so rapid, the overthrow so <seg/>complete!</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p138">Morning, <seg/>dismal and <seg/>wet, <seg/>at length dawned, and discovered to my sleepless and aching eyes the church of <seg/>Ingolstadt, <seg/>its white steeple <seg/>and clock, <seg/>which <seg/>indicated <seg/>the <seg/>sixth <seg/>hour. The porter opened the gates of the <seg/>court, <seg/>which had that night been my <seg/>asylum, <seg/>and I issued into the streets, pacing them with quick <seg/>steps, <seg/>as if I sought to avoid the wretch whom I feared every turning <seg/>of <seg/>the street would present to my view. I did not dare return to the <seg/>apartment which <seg/>I <seg/>inhabited, <seg/>but felt impelled to hurry <seg/>on, <seg/>although <seg/>wetted <seg/>by the <seg/>rain <seg/>which poured from a black and comfortless <seg/>sky.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p139">I <seg/>continued walking in this manner for some <seg/>time, endeavouring, <seg/>by bodily <seg/>exercise, <seg/>to ease the load that weighed upon my mind. I traversed the <seg/>streets, <seg/>without any clear conception of where I <seg/>was, <seg/>or what I was <seg/>doing. <seg/>My heart palpitated <seg/>in <seg/>the sickness of <seg/>fear; <seg/>and I hurried on with irregular <seg/>steps, <seg/>not daring to look about <seg/>me:</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p140"> 
            <seg/>
            <seg/>
            <cit/> 
            <quote/> 
            <lg/> 
            <l/> Like <seg/>one <seg/>who, <seg/>on a <seg/>lonely road, <l/> 
            <l/> Doth <seg/>walk in fear and <seg/>dread, <l/> 
            <l/> And, <seg/>having once <seg/>turned <seg/>
            <seg/>round, walks on, <l/> 
            <seg/>
            <l/> 
            <seg/>And <seg/>turns no more his <seg/>head; <l/> 
            <seg/>
            <l/> 
            <seg/>Because <seg/>he knows a frightful <seg/>fiend <l/> 
            <seg/>
            <l/> 
            <seg/>Doth <seg/>close behind him <seg/>tread*. <l/> 
            <lg/> 
            <quote/> 
            <note/> * <seg/>
            <bibl/> 
            <seg/>Coleridge’s “Ancient Mariner.” <bibl/> 
            <note/>
            <cit/>
            </p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p141">Continuing <seg/>thus, I came at <seg/>length opposite <seg/>to the inn at which the <seg/>various <seg/>diligences and carriages usually stopped. Here I <seg/>paused, <seg/>I knew not <seg/>why; <seg/>but <seg/>I <seg/>remained some minutes with my eyes fixed on a coach that was coming towards me from the other end of the street. As <seg/>it <seg/>drew <seg/>nearer, <seg/>I observed that it was the Swiss <seg/>diligence: <seg/>it stopped just where I was <seg/>standing; and, <seg/>on the <seg/>door <seg/>being <seg/>opened, <seg/>I perceived Henry Clerval, <seg/>who, <seg/>on seeing <seg/>me, <seg/>instantly sprung out. <seg/>“My <seg/>dear <seg/>Frankenstein,” <seg/>exclaimed <seg/>he, “how <seg/>glad I am to see <seg/>you! <seg/>how <seg/>fortunate <seg/>that you should be here at the <seg/>very <seg/>moment of my <seg/>alighting!”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p142">Nothing <seg/>could equal my delight on <seg/>seeing Clerval; <seg/>his presence brought back to my thoughts my father, <seg/>Elizabeth, <seg/>and all those scenes of home so dear to my recollection. I grasped his hand, and in a moment forgot my horror and <seg/>misfortune; <seg/>I <seg/>felt suddenly, <seg/>and for the first time <seg/>during <seg/>many months, calm and serene joy. I welcomed my <seg/>friend, therefore, <seg/>in the most cordial <seg/>manner, <seg/>and we walked towards my <seg/>college. <seg/>Clerval continued talking for some time about our mutual <seg/>friends, <seg/>and his <seg/>own good <seg/>fortune in being <seg/>permitted <seg/>to come to Ingolstadt. <seg/>“You <seg/>may <seg/>easily believe,” <seg/>said he, <seg/>“how great <seg/>was <seg/>the difficulty to persuade <seg/>my <seg/>father <seg/>that <seg/>it <seg/>
            <seg/>was <seg/>
            <seg/>not absolutely <seg/>
            <seg/>necessary <seg/>
            <seg/>for a merchant <seg/>
            <seg/>not <seg/>
            <seg/>to <seg/>
            <seg/>understand any thing <seg/>
            <seg/>except <seg/>
            <seg/>book-keeping; and, indeed, <seg/>I believe I left him <seg/>incredulous <seg/>to the <seg/>last, <seg/>for his constant answer to my <seg/>unwearied entreaties was <seg/>the same as <seg/>that of the <seg/>Dutch <seg/>schoolmaster <seg/>in the Vicar of <seg/>Wakefield: ‘I <seg/>have ten thousand <seg/>florins a year without Greek, I eat <seg/>heartily <seg/>without Greek.’ But <seg/>his affection for me at <seg/>length <seg/>overcame his dislike <seg/>of learning, <seg/>and he <seg/>has <seg/>permitted me <seg/>to undertake <seg/>a voyage of <seg/>discovery to <seg/>the land of <seg/>knowledge.”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p143">“It gives me the greatest delight to see
            you; but tell me how you left <seg/>my father, <seg/>brothers, and Elizabeth.”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p144">“Very well, <seg/>and very <seg/>happy, only <seg/>a little uneasy that <seg/>they <seg/>hear from you so <seg/>seldom. By <seg/>the <seg/>by, <seg/>I mean to lecture you <seg/>a <seg/>little upon their account <seg/>myself.—But, <seg/>my dear <seg/>Frankenstein,” <seg/>continued <seg/>he, <seg/>stopping <seg/>short, <seg/>and gazing <seg/>full <seg/>in my <seg/>face, “I <seg/>did not before <seg/>remark <seg/>how very ill you <seg/>appear; <seg/>so thin <seg/>and <seg/>pale; you <seg/>look <seg/>as if you had <seg/>been <seg/>watching for several <seg/>nights.”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p145">“You <seg/>have guessed <seg/>right; <seg/>I have lately been so <seg/>deeply <seg/>engaged in one <seg/>occupation, <seg/>that I <seg/>have not allowed myself <seg/>sufficient <seg/>rest, <seg/>as you <seg/>see: <seg/>but I hope, I sincerely <seg/>hope, that <seg/>all <seg/>these employments <seg/>are <seg/>now <seg/>at an <seg/>end, and that I am at length <seg/>
            <seg/>free.” <seg/>
            <seg/>
            </p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p146">I <seg/>trembled <seg/>excessively; <seg/>I could not <seg/>endure <seg/>to think <seg/>of, and <seg/>far less to allude <seg/>to <seg/>the <seg/>occurrences <seg/>of the <seg/>preceding <seg/>night. I walked with a quick pace, and we soon arrived at my <seg/>college. <seg/>I then <seg/>reflected, <seg/>and the thought made me <seg/>shiver, <seg/>that the creature whom I had left in my <seg/>apartment <seg/>might <seg/>still <seg/>be <seg/>there, alive, <seg/>and walking about. I dreaded to <seg/>behold this monster; <seg/>but I <seg/>feared <seg/>still more that Henry should <seg/>see him. <seg/>Entreating <seg/>him <seg/>
            <seg/>therefore <seg/>
            <seg/>to <seg/>remain a few minutes at the bottom of the stairs, I darted up towards my own room. My hand was already on the lock <seg/>of the door <seg/>before I <seg/>recollected myself. <seg/>I <seg/>then paused; <seg/>and a cold shivering came over me. I threw the door <seg/>forcibly open, <seg/>as children are accustomed to do when they expect a spectre to stand in waiting for them on the other <seg/>side; <seg/>but nothing appeared. I stepped fearfully <seg/>in: <seg/>the <seg/>apartment <seg/>was <seg/>empty; <seg/>and my <seg/>bed-room <seg/>was also freed from its hideous guest. I could hardly believe that so great a <seg/>good-fortune <seg/>could have befallen me; but when I <seg/>became <seg/>assured that my enemy had indeed fled, I clapped my hands for <seg/>joy, <seg/>and ran down to <seg/>Clerval.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p147">We <seg/>ascended into my <seg/>room, and <seg/>the servant <seg/>presently <seg/>brought <seg/>breakfast; <seg/>but I was unable to contain myself. It was not joy only that possessed <seg/>me; I <seg/>felt my flesh tingle with excess of <seg/>sensitiveness, <seg/>and my pulse beat rapidly. I was unable to remain for a single instant in the same <seg/>place; <seg/>I jumped over the chairs, clapped my <seg/>hands, and <seg/>laughed aloud. Clerval at first attributed my unusual spirits to joy on his <seg/>arrival; <seg/>but when he observed me <seg/>more attentively, <seg/>he saw a wildness in my eyes for which he could not <seg/>account; <seg/>and my <seg/>loud, unrestrained, <seg/>heartless <seg/>laughter, <seg/>frightened and astonished <seg/>him.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p148">“My <seg/>dear <seg/>Victor,” <seg/>cried <seg/>he, “what, <seg/>for <seg/>God’s sake, <seg/>is the <seg/>matter? <seg/>Do not laugh <seg/>in that manner. <seg/>How ill you are! What is the cause of all <seg/>this?</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p149">“Do <seg/>not ask <seg/>me,” <seg/>cried I, putting my <seg/>hands <seg/>before my eyes, for I thought I saw the <seg/>dreaded <seg/>spectre glide into the <seg/>room; “he <seg/>can <seg/>tell.—Oh, <seg/>save <seg/>me! <seg/>save <seg/>me!” <seg/>I imagined that the monster seized <seg/>me; <seg/>I struggled <seg/>furiously, and <seg/>fell down in a <seg/>fit.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p150">Poor <seg/>Clerval! what must have been his <seg/>feelings? <seg/>A <seg/>meeting, <seg/>which he anticipated with such <seg/>joy, <seg/>so strangely turned to bitterness. But I <seg/>was <seg/>not <seg/>the <seg/>witness <seg/>of <seg/>his <seg/>grief; <seg/>for I was <seg/>lifeless, <seg/>and did not recover my senses for a long, long <seg/>time.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p151">This <seg/>was the commencement of a nervous <seg/>fever, <seg/>which confined me for several months. During all <seg/>that <seg/>time Henry was my only nurse. I afterwards learned <seg/>that, <seg/>knowing my <seg/>father’s <seg/>advanced <seg/>age, <seg/>and unfitness for so long a <seg/>journey, <seg/>and <seg/>how <seg/>wretched <seg/>my sickness <seg/>would <seg/>make Elizabeth, <seg/>he spared them this <seg/>grief <seg/>by <seg/>concealing <seg/>the extent of my <seg/>disorder. <seg/>He knew that I could not have a more kind and attentive nurse than <seg/>himself; and, <seg/>firm in the hope he <seg/>felt <seg/>of my <seg/>recovery, <seg/>he did not doubt <seg/>that, <seg/>instead of doing <seg/>harm, <seg/>he performed the kindest action that he could towards <seg/>them.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p152">But <seg/>I was in reality very <seg/>ill; <seg/>and surely nothing but the unbounded <seg/>and <seg/>unremitting attentions of my friend could have restored me to life. The form of the <seg/>monster <seg/>on whom I had bestowed <seg/>existence <seg/>was for ever before my eyes, and I raved incessantly concerning him. <seg/>Doubtless my <seg/>words surprised <seg/>Henry: <seg/>he at first believed them <seg/>to be <seg/>the wanderings of my <seg/>disturbed imagination; <seg/>but the pertinacity with which I continually recurred to the same <seg/>subject <seg/>persuaded him that my disorder <seg/>indeed <seg/>owed its origin to some uncommon and terrible <seg/>event.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p153">By <seg/>very slow <seg/>degrees, <seg/>and with frequent <seg/>relapses, <seg/>that alarmed and grieved my <seg/>friend, <seg/>I recovered. I remember the first time I <seg/>became <seg/>capable of observing outward objects with any kind of pleasure, I perceived that the fallen leaves had <seg/>disappeared, <seg/>and that <seg/>the <seg/>young buds were shooting forth from the <seg/>trees that shaded my window. <seg/>It was a divine <seg/>spring; <seg/>and the season contributed greatly to my convalescence. I felt also sentiments of joy and affection revive in my <seg/>bosom; <seg/>my gloom <seg/>disappeared, <seg/>and in a short time I became as cheerful as before I was attacked by the fatal <seg/>passion.</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p154">“Dearest Clerval,” exclaimed I, “how <seg/>kind, <seg/>how <seg/>very good you are to me. This <seg/>whole winter, <seg/>instead of <seg/>being spent <seg/>in <seg/>study, <seg/>as you promised yourself, <seg/>has <seg/>been consumed in my sick <seg/>room. How <seg/>shall I ever repay you? I feel <seg/>the <seg/>greatest remorse for the disappointment <seg/>of which <seg/>I have been the <seg/>occasion; <seg/>but you will forgive <seg/>me.”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p155">“You <seg/>will repay <seg/>me entirely, if <seg/>you do not <seg/>discompose yourself, but <seg/>get well as fast as you <seg/>can; <seg/>and <seg/>since <seg/>you appear in such good <seg/>spirits, <seg/>I may speak to you on <seg/>one subject, <seg/>may I <seg/>not?”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p156">I trembled. <seg/>One subject! what could it be? Could he allude <seg/>to an <seg/>object on whom I dared not even <seg/>think?</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p157">“Compose yourself,” <seg/>said Clerval, who observed my change of <seg/>colour, “I <seg/>will not mention <seg/>it, <seg/>if it agitates <seg/>you; <seg/>but your father <seg/>and <seg/>cousin would be <seg/>very <seg/>happy if they received a letter from you in <seg/>your <seg/>own <seg/>hand-writing. <seg/>They hardly know how <seg/>ill <seg/>you have been, and are uneasy <seg/>at <seg/>your long <seg/>silence.”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p158">“Is <seg/>that <seg/>all? <seg/>
            <seg/>my <seg/>dear <seg/>Henry. <seg/>How could you suppose <seg/>that <seg/>my first <seg/>thought <seg/>would not <seg/>fly towards those <seg/>dear, dear friends <seg/>whom <seg/>I <seg/>love, <seg/>and who are so deserving <seg/>of <seg/>my <seg/>love.”</p><p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter4_p159">“If <seg/>this is your present <seg/>temper, my friend, you <seg/>will <seg/>perhaps <seg/>be glad <seg/>to <seg/>see a letter that has been <seg/>lying <seg/>here some days <seg/>for you: <seg/>it is from your <seg/>cousin, <seg/>I <seg/>believe.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>