<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C06"/>
   <p>August 13th, 17—.</p>
   <p>My affection for my guest increases every day. He excites at once my admiration and my
          pity to an astonishing degree. How can I see so noble a creature destroyed by misery
          without feeling the most poignant grief? He is so gentle, yet so wise; his mind is so
          cultivated; and when he speaks, <add>in his native language which is French, </add>although his words are culled with the choicest art, yet
          they flow with rapidity and unparalleled eloquence.</p>
   <p>He is now much recovered from his illness, and is continually on the deck, apparently
          watching for the sledge that preceded his own. Yet, although un<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_044" n="032"/>happy, he is not so utterly occupied by his own misery, but that he
          interests himself deeply in the employments of others. He has asked me many questions
          concerning my design; and I have related my little history frankly to him. He appeared
          pleased with the confidence, and suggested several alterations in my plan, which I shall
          find exceedingly useful. There is no pedantry in his manner; but all he does appears to
          spring solely from the interest he instinctively takes in the welfare of those who
          surround him. He is often overcome by <add>a</add> gloom, <del rend="strikethrough">and then he sits by himself, and tries to
          overcome all that is sullen or unsocial in his humour. These paroxysms pass from him like
          a cloud from before the sun, though his dejection never leaves him.</del><add>Which veils his countenance like deep night—he neither speaks or notices anything around him, but sitting on a gun will gaze on the sea and I have sometimes observed his dark eyelash wet with a tear which falls <del rend="strikethrough">silently</del> silently in the deep. This unobtrusive sorrow excites in me the most painful interest, and he will at times reward my sympathy by throwing aside this veil of mortal woe, and then his ardent looks, his deep toned voice and powerful eloquence entrance me with delight.</add> I have endeavoured to
          win his confidence; and I trust that I have suc<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_045" n="033"/>ceeded. One day I mentioned to him the desire I had always felt of finding a friend who
          might sympathize with me, and direct me by his counsel. I said, I did not belong to that
          class of men who are offended by advice. “I am self-educated, and perhaps I hardly rely
          sufficiently upon my own powers. I wish therefore that my companion should be wiser and
          more experienced than myself, to confirm and support me; nor have I believed it impossible
          to find a true friend.”</p>
   <p>“I agree with you,” replied the stranger, “in believing that friendship is not only a
          desirable, but a possible acquisition. I once had a friend, the most noble of human
          creatures, and am entitled, therefore, to judge respecting friendship. You have hope, and
          the world before you, and have no cause for despair. But I—I have lost <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_046" n="034"/>every thing, and cannot begin life anew.”</p>
   <p>As he said this, his countenance became expressive of a calm settled grief, that touched
          me to the heart. But he was silent, and presently retired to his cabin.</p>
   <p>Even broken in spirit as he is, no one can feel more deeply than he does the beauties of
          nature. The starry sky, the sea, and every sight afforded by these wonderful regions,
          seems still to have the power of elevating his soul from earth. Such a man has a double
          existence: he may suffer misery, and be overwhelmed by disappointments; yet when he has
          retired into himself, he will be like a celestial spirit, that has a halo around him,
          within whose circle no grief or folly ventures.</p>
   <p>Will you laugh at the enthusiasm I express concerning this divine wan<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_047" n="035"/>derer? If you do, you must have certainly lost that
          simplicity which was once your characteristic charm. Yet, if you will, smile at the warmth
          of my expressions, while I find every day new causes for repeating them.</p>
   <p>August 19th, 17—.</p>
   <p>Yesterday the stranger said to me, “You may easily perceive, Captain Walton, that I have
          suffered great and unparalleled misfortunes. I had determined, once, that the memory of
          these evils should die with me; but you have won me to alter my determination. You seek
          for knowledge and wisdom, as I once did; and I ardently hope that the gratification of
          your wishes may not be a serpent to sting you, as mine has been. I do not know that the
          relation of my misfortunes will be useful to you, yet, if you are inclined, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_048" n="036"/>listen to my tale. I believe that the strange
          incidents connected with it will afford a view of nature, which may enlarge your faculties
          and understanding. You will hear of powers and occurrences, such as you have been
          accustomed to believe impossible: but I do not doubt that my tale conveys in its series
          internal evidence of the truth of the events of which it is composed.”</p>
   <p>You may easily conceive that I was much gratified by the offered communication; yet I
          could not endure that he should renew his grief by a recital of his misfortunes. I felt
          the greatest eagerness to hear the promised narrative, partly from curiosity, and partly
          from a strong desire to ameliorate his fate, if it were in my power. I expressed these
          feelings in my answer.</p>
   <p>“I thank you,” he replied, “for <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_049" n="037"/>your sympathy, but
          it is useless; my fate is nearly fulfilled. I wait but for one event, and then I shall
          repose in peace. I understand your feeling,” continued he, perceiving that I wished to
          interrupt him; “but you are mistaken, my friend, if thus you will allow me to name you;
          nothing can alter my destiny: listen to my history, and you will perceive how irrevocably
          it is determined.</p>
   <p>He then told me, that he would commence his narrative the next day when I should be at
          leisure. This promise drew from me the warmest thanks. I have resolved every night, when I
          am not engaged, to record, as nearly as possible in his own words, what he has related
          during the day. If I should be engaged, I will at least make notes. This manuscript will
          doubtless afford you the greatest <hi rend="underline">pleasure</hi><note place="below" resp="#MWS">impossible</note>: but to me, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_050" n="038"/>who know him, and who hear it from his own lips, with what interest and
          sympathy shall I read it in some future day!</p>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_051" n="039"/>
   <head>FRANKENSTEIN;</head>
   <head>
      <hi rend="smallcaps">OR</hi>,</head>
   <head>THE MODERN PROMETHEUS.</head>
   <comment text=" RM: centered ornamental "/>
</xml>
