<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<header>
    <title level="m">FRANKENSTEIN; OR, THE MODERN PROMETHEUS</title>
    
    <edition>The Pittsburgh Bicentennial Edition</edition>
    
    <div type="editIntro">
        <head>INTRODUCTORY NOTE ON THE TEXT</head>
        
        <p>This is a digital edition prepared for the Frankenstein Bicentennial project, commemorating the 200th anniversary of the first published edition of <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein; or, the
            Modern Prometheus</hi> in
            1818.</p>
        
        <p><title level="m">Frankenstein; or, the Modern Prometheus: Pittsburgh Bicentennial
            Edition</title> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
            4.0 International License.</p>
        
        <p>Date this document was first produced: 2017-05-07. Amended: 2018-03-18.</p>
        
        <p>This edition of the 1818 text is part of the Pittsburgh research team’s contribution to the Bicentennial
            Frankenstein Project, and is prepared by Elisa Beshero-Bondar of the University of
            Pittsburgh at Greensburg and Rikk Mulligan of Carnegie Mellon University. We are grateful
            for consultation from Wendell Piez, David J. Birnbaum, and Raffaele Viglianti, as well as
            Neil Fraistat and Dave Rettenmaier. This edition’s stages of development are stored and
            documented in the <ref target="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein/"
                >Pittsburgh_Frankenstein GitHub repository</ref>.</p>
        
        <resp>We have produced this XML edition for two purposes:</resp>
        <list type="numbered">
            <item>To prepare for automated collation of the 1818, 1823, and 1831 editions of <hi
                rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi> using CollateX, in order to generate a TEI XML document
                that stores the variations of these texts.</item>
            
            <item>To provide a reliable digital base text of each edition tractable for collation, as a
                stage in preparing a TEI P5 edition, and as a basis for related projects.</item>
        </list>
        
        <p>This edition is one of two that share the same electronic source, representing the 1818 and
            1831 editions of the novel. This pair of editions is based on the Pennsylvania Electronic
            Edition of <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein; or, the Modern Prometheus</hi> by Mary Shelley,
            edited by Stuart Curran and assisted by Jack Lynch, located at <ref
                target="http://knarf.english.upenn.edu/">http://knarf.english.upenn.edu/</ref> and
            hereafter referred to as PA EE. Elisa Beshero-Bondar and Rikk Mulligan have corrected these
            texts against photo facsimiles of the 1818 and 1831 publications.</p>
        
        <!--<p>Our plain text edition preserves the rendering of italics, square brackets, and centered
        text from the PA EE HTML texts.</p>
-->
        <p>We have added page breaks using the TEI self-closing pb element. We will not be preserving
            the running headers but will retain page number in order to link to page images in future
            iterations of the text.</p>
        
        <!--<p>To track pages from our source images we will be using the TEI self-closing milestone
        element with "unNum" as the marker.</p>-->
        
        <list>
            <!-- <item>In the PA EE there is no distinction between italics for titles and italics for
          emphasized words. Italics have been converted to hi elements with @rend="italic"</item>-->
            
            <item>We preserved italics and small caps.</item>
            
            <item>We have not normalized the spelling, and where the PA EE did so, we have silently
                restored the spelling to its original state as observed in the photo facsimile
                nineteenth-century editions. To prevent errors in collation, we have commented out editor
                notes written by us recording our observations of errors in the source text. We have also
                commented out the one instance in the 1831 PA EE HTML in which square brackets were used
                to hold a normalized variant of a word, to suppress that from the output.</item>
            
            <!--<item>When centered text is the heading of a chapter or book, we render it inside head
          elements. Otherwise we use hi @rend="center".</item>-->
        </list>
        <!--<note resp="#ebb">Note for later processing: In the PA EE of this text, there are 1337 encoded links, each pointing to an editorial annotation.</note> -->
    </div>
</header>
