<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="introduction">
    <pb xml:id="F1831_v_009"/>
    <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
    <comment>ebb: centered underscore a few lines below</comment>
    <p>The Publishers of the Standard Novels, in selecting “Frankenstein” for one of their series,
        expressed a wish that I should furnish them with some account of the origin of the story. I
        am the more willing to comply, because I shall thus give a general answer to the question,
        so very frequently asked me—“How I, then a young girl, came to think of, and to dilate upon,
        so very hideous an idea?” It is true that I am very averse to bringing myself forward in
        print; but as my account will only appear as an appendage to a former production, and as it
        will be confined to such topics as have connection with my authorship alone, I can scarcely
        accuse myself of a personal intrusion.</p>
    <p>It is not singular that, as the daughter of two persons of distinguished literary
        celebrity, I should very early in life have thought of writing. As a child I scribbled; and
        my favourite pastime, during the hours given me for recreation, was to “write stories.”
        Still I had a dearer pleasure than this, which was the formation of castles in the air—the
        indulging in waking dreams—the following up trains of thought, which had for their subject
        the formation of a succession of imaginary incidents. My dreams were at once more fantastic
        and agreeable than my writings. In the latter I was a close imitator—rather doing<pb
            xml:id="F1831_v_010" n="vi"/> as others had done, than putting down the suggestions of my
        own mind. What I wrote was intended at least for one other eye—my childhood’s companion and
        friend; but my dreams were all my own; I accounted for them to nobody; they were my refuge
        when annoyed—my dearest pleasure when free.</p>
    <p>I lived principally in the country as a girl, and passed a considerable time in Scotland. I
        made occasional visits to the more picturesque parts; but my habitual residence was on the
        blank and dreary northern shores of the Tay, near Dundee. Blank and dreary on retrospection
        I call them; they were not so to me then. They were the eyry of freedom, and the pleasant
        region where unheeded I could commune with the creatures of my fancy. I wrote then—but in a
        most common-place style. It was beneath the trees of the grounds belonging to our house, or
        on the bleak sides of the woodless mountains near, that my true compositions, the airy
        flights of my imagination, were born and fostered. I did not make myself the heroine of my
        tales. Life appeared to me too common-place an affair as regarded myself. I could not figure
        to myself that romantic woes or wonderful events would ever be my lot; but I was not
        confined to my own identity, and I could people the hours with creations far more
        interesting to me at that age, than my own sensations.</p>
    <p>After this my life became busier, and reality stood in place of fiction. My husband,
        however, was from the first, very anxious that I should prove myself worthy of my parentage,
        and enrol myself on the page of fame. He was for ever inciting me to obtain literary
        reputation, which even on my own part I cared for then,<pb xml:id="F1831_v_011" n="vii"/>
        though since I have become infinitely indifferent to it. At this time he desired that I
        should write, not so much with the idea that I could produce any thing worthy of notice, but
        that he might himself judge how far I possessed the promise of better things hereafter.
        Still I did nothing. Travelling, and the cares of a family, occupied my time; and study, in
        the way of reading, or improving my ideas in communication with his far more cultivated
        mind, was all of literary employment that engaged my attention.</p>
    <p>In the summer of 1816, we visited Switzerland, and became the neighbours of Lord Byron. At
        first we spent our pleasant hours on the lake, or wandering on its shores; and Lord Byron,
        who was writing the third canto of Childe Harold, was the only one among us who put his
        thoughts upon paper. These, as he brought them successively to us, clothed in all the light
        and harmony of poetry, seemed to stamp as divine the glories of heaven and earth, whose
        influences we partook with him.</p>
    <p>But it proved a wet, ungenial summer, and incessant rain often confined us for days to the
        house. Some volumes of ghost stories, translated from the German into French, fell into our
        hands. There was the History of the Inconstant Lover, who, when he thought to clasp the
        bride to whom he had pledged his vows, found himself in the arms of the pale ghost of her
        whom he had deserted. There was the tale of the sinful founder of his race, whose miserable
        doom it was to bestow the kiss of death on all the younger sons of his fated house, just
        when they reached the age of promise. His gigantic, shadowy form, clothed like the ghost in
        Hamlet, in complete armour, but with the<pb xml:id="F1831_v_012" n="viii"/> beaver up, was
        seen at midnight, by the moon’s fitful beams, to advance slowly along the gloomy avenue. The
        shape was lost beneath the shadow of the castle walls; but soon a gate swung back, a step
        was heard, the door of the chamber opened, and he advanced to the couch of the blooming
        youths, cradled in healthy sleep. Eternal sorrow sat upon his face as he bent down and
        kissed the forehead of the boys, who from that hour withered like flowers snapt upon the
        stalk. I have not seen these stories since then; but their incidents are as fresh in my mind
        as if I had read them yesterday.</p>
    <p>“We will each write a ghost story,” said Lord Byron; and his proposition was acceded to.
        There were four of us. The noble author began a tale, a fragment of which he printed at the
        end of his poem of Mazeppa. Shelley, more apt to embody ideas and sentiments in the radiance
        of brilliant imagery, and in the music of the most melodious verse that adorns our language,
        than to invent the machinery of a story, commenced one founded on the experiences of his
        early life. Poor Polidori had some terrible idea about a skull-headed lady, who was so
        punished for peeping through a key-hole—what to see I forget—something very shocking and
        wrong of course; but when she was reduced to a worse condition than the renowned Tom of
        Coventry, he did not know what to do with her, and was obliged to despatch her to the tomb
        of the Capulets, the only place for which she was fitted. The illustrious poets also,
        annoyed by the platitude of prose, speedily relinquished their uncongenial task.</p>
    <p>I busied myself <hi rend="italic">to think of a story</hi>,—a story to rival those which
        had excited us to this task. One which<pb xml:id="F1831_v_013" n="ix"/> would speak to the
        mysterious fears of our nature, and awaken thrilling horror — one to make the reader dread
        to look round, to curdle the blood, and quicken the beatings of the heart. If I did not
        accomplish these things, my ghost story would be unworthy of its name. I thought and
        pondered — vainly. I felt that blank incapability of invention which is the greatest misery
        of authorship, when dull Nothing replies to our anxious invocations. <hi rend="italic">Have
            you thought of a story?</hi> I was asked each morning, and each morning I was forced to
        reply with a mortifying negative.</p>
    <p>Every thing must have a beginning, to speak in Sanchean phrase; and that beginning must be
        linked to something that went before. The Hindoos give the world an elephant to support it,
        but they make the elephant stand upon a tortoise. Invention, it must be humbly admitted,
        does not consist in creating out of void, but out of chaos; the materials must, in the first
        place, be afforded: it can give form to dark, shapeless substances, but cannot bring into
        being the substance itself. In all matters of discovery and invention, even of those that
        appertain to the imagination, we are continually reminded of the story of Columbus and his
        egg. Invention consists in the capacity of seizing on the capabilities of a subject, and in
        the power of moulding and fashioning ideas suggested to it.</p>
    <p>Many and long were the conversations between Lord Byron and Shelley, to which I was a
        devout but nearly silent listener. During one of these, various philosophical doctrines were
        discussed, and among others the nature of the principle of life, and whether there was any
        probability of its ever being discovered and communicated. They talked of the experiments of
        <pb xml:id="F1831_v_014" n="x"/>Dr. Darwin, (I speak not of what the Doctor really did, or
        said that he did, but, as more to my purpose, of what was then spoken of as having been done
        by him,) who preserved a piece of vermicelli in a glass case, till by some extraordinary
        means it began to move with voluntary motion. Not thus, after all, would life be given.
        Perhaps a corpse would be re-animated; galvanism had given token of such things: perhaps the
        component parts of a creature might be manufactured, brought together, and endued with vital
        warmth.</p>
    <p>Night waned upon this talk, and even the witching hour had gone by, before we retired to
        rest. When I placed my head on my pillow, I did not sleep, nor could I be said to think. My
        imagination, unbidden, possessed and guided me, gifting the successive images that arose in
        my mind with a vividness far beyond the usual bounds of reverie. I saw — with shut eyes, but
        acute mental vision, — I saw the pale student of unhallowed arts kneeling beside the thing
        he had put together. I saw the hideous phantasm of a man stretched out, and then, on the
        working of some powerful engine, show signs of life, and stir with an uneasy, half vital
        motion. Frightful must it be; for supremely frightful would be the effect of any human
        endeavour to mock the stupendous mechanism of the Creator of the world. His success would
        terrify the artist; he would rush away from his odious handywork, horror-stricken. He would
        hope that, left to itself, the slight spark of life which he had communicated would fade;
        that this thing, which had received such imperfect animation, would subside into dead
        matter; and he might sleep in the belief that the silence of the grave would quench for ever
        the transient existence of the hideous corpse <pb xml:id="F1831_v_015" n="xi"/>which he had
        looked upon as the cradle of life. He sleeps; but he is awakened; he opens his eyes; behold
        the horrid thing stands at his bedside, opening his curtains, and looking on him with
        yellow, watery, but speculative eyes.</p>
    <p>I opened mine in terror. The idea so possessed my mind, that a thrill of fear ran through
        me, and I wished to exchange the ghastly image of my fancy for the realities around. I see
        them still; the very room, the dark <hi rend="italic">parquet</hi>, the closed shutters,
        with the moonlight struggling through, and the sense I had that the glassy lake and white
        high Alps were beyond. I could not so easily get rid of my hideous phantom; still it haunted
        me. I must try to think of something else. I recurred to my ghost story, — my tiresome
        unlucky ghost story! O! if I could only contrive one which would frighten my reader as I
        myself had been frightened that night!</p>
    <p>Swift as light and as cheering was the idea that broke in upon me. “I have found it! What
        terrified me will terrify others; and I need only describe the spectre which had haunted my
        midnight pillow.” On the morrow I announced that I had <hi rend="italic">thought of a
            story</hi>. I began that day with the words, <hi rend="italic">It was on a dreary night of
                November</hi>, making only a transcript of the grim terrors of my waking dream.</p>
    <p>At first I thought but of a few pages — of a short tale; but Shelley urged me to develope
        the idea at greater length. I certainly did not owe the suggestion of one incident, nor
        scarcely of one train of feeling, to my husband, and yet but for his incitement, it would
        never have taken the form in which it was presented to the world. From this declaration I
        must except the preface. As far as I can recollect, it was entirely written by him.</p>
    <p><pb xml:id="F1831_v_016" n="xii"/>And now, once again, I bid my hideous progeny go forth
        and prosper. I have an affection for it, for it was the offspring of happy days, when death
        and grief were but words, which found no true echo in my heart. Its several pages speak of
        many a walk, many a drive, and many a conversation, when I was not alone; and my companion
        was one who, in this world, I shall never see more. But this is for myself; my readers have
        nothing to do with these associations.</p>
    <p>I will add but one word as to the alterations I have made. They are principally those of
        style. I have changed no portion of the story, nor introduced any new ideas or
        circumstances. I have mended the language where it was so bald as to interfere with the
        interest of the narrative; and these changes occur almost exclusively in the beginning of
        the first volume. Throughout they are entirely confined to such parts as are mere adjuncts
        to the story, leaving the core and substance of it untouched.</p>
    <p>M.W.S.</p>
    <p><hi rend="italic">London, October</hi> 15, 1831.</p>
</div>
