<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein"
     xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
     xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness fThomas, Collation unit C20</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg th:sID="C20_app1-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>
            <milestone n="13" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <pb n="084" xml:id="F1818_v2_088"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_head1">CHAPTER VI.</head>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p1">“S<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p1_hi1">OME</hi> 
               <seg th:eID="C20_app1-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app2-fThomas"/>time <seg th:eID="C20_app2-fThomas"/>elapsed before I <seg th:sID="C20_app4-fThomas"/>learned <seg th:eID="C20_app4-fThomas"/>the history of my friends. It was one which could not fail to impress itself deeply <seg th:sID="C20_app8-fThomas"/>on <seg th:eID="C20_app8-fThomas"/>my <seg th:sID="C20_app10-fThomas"/>mind, <seg th:eID="C20_app10-fThomas"/>unfolding as it did a number of <seg th:sID="C20_app13-fThomas"/>circumstances <seg th:eID="C20_app13-fThomas"/>each <seg th:sID="C20_app15-fThomas"/>interesting and wonderful <seg th:eID="C20_app15-fThomas"/>to one so utterly inexperienced as I <seg th:sID="C20_app17-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>was.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p2">“The <seg th:eID="C20_app17-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>name of the old man was De Lacey. He was <seg th:sID="C20_app21-fThomas"/>descended <seg th:eID="C20_app21-fThomas"/>from a good family in <seg th:sID="C20_app23-fThomas"/>France, where he <seg th:eID="C20_app23-fThomas"/>had <seg th:sID="C20_app25-fThomas"/>lived <seg th:eID="C20_app25-fThomas"/>for many years in <seg th:sID="C20_app30-fThomas"/>affluence, <seg th:eID="C20_app30-fThomas"/>respected by his <seg th:sID="C20_app32-fThomas"/>superiors, <seg th:eID="C20_app32-fThomas"/>and beloved by his equals. His son was bred <seg th:sID="C20_app36-fThomas"/>in <seg th:eID="C20_app36-fThomas"/>the <seg th:sID="C20_app38-fThomas"/>ser<pb n="085" xml:id="F1818_v2_089"/>vice <seg th:eID="C20_app38-fThomas"/>of his <seg th:sID="C20_app40-fThomas"/>country; <seg th:eID="C20_app40-fThomas"/>and Agatha had <seg th:sID="C20_app42-fThomas"/>ranked with <seg th:eID="C20_app42-fThomas"/>ladies of the highest distinction. A few months <seg th:sID="C20_app46-fThomas"/>before <seg th:eID="C20_app46-fThomas"/>my <seg th:sID="C20_app48-fThomas"/>arrival, <seg th:eID="C20_app48-fThomas"/>they had lived in a large <seg th:sID="C20_app50-fThomas"/>and luxurious city, <seg th:eID="C20_app50-fThomas"/>called Paris, surrounded by <seg th:sID="C20_app52-fThomas"/>friends, <seg th:eID="C20_app52-fThomas"/>and possessed of every enjoyment <seg th:sID="C20_app54-fThomas"/>which virtue, <seg th:eID="C20_app54-fThomas"/>refinement of <seg th:sID="C20_app56-fThomas"/>intellect, or taste, accompanied by <seg th:eID="C20_app56-fThomas"/>a <seg th:sID="C20_app58-fThomas"/>moderate fortune, <seg th:eID="C20_app58-fThomas"/>could <seg th:sID="C20_app60-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>afford.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p3">“The <seg th:eID="C20_app60-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>father of Safie <seg th:sID="C20_app62-fThomas"/>had <seg th:eID="C20_app62-fThomas"/>been the cause of their <seg th:sID="C20_app64-fThomas"/>ruin. <seg th:eID="C20_app64-fThomas"/>He was a <seg th:sID="C20_app66-fThomas"/>Turkish merchant, <seg th:eID="C20_app66-fThomas"/>and had inhabited Paris for many <seg th:sID="C20_app70-fThomas"/>years, when, for <seg th:eID="C20_app70-fThomas"/>some reason which I could not <seg th:sID="C20_app72-fThomas"/>learn, he became <seg th:eID="C20_app72-fThomas"/>obnoxious to the <seg th:sID="C20_app74-fThomas"/>government. <seg th:eID="C20_app74-fThomas"/>He was seized and cast into prison the very day that Safie arrived from Constantinople to join him. He was <seg th:sID="C20_app78-fThomas"/>tried, <seg th:eID="C20_app78-fThomas"/>and condemned to death. The injustice of his sentence was very <seg th:sID="C20_app82-fThomas"/>flagrant; <seg th:eID="C20_app82-fThomas"/>all Paris <seg th:sID="C20_app84-fThomas"/>was indignant; <seg th:eID="C20_app84-fThomas"/>and it was judged that his <seg th:sID="C20_app88-fThomas"/>religion <seg th:eID="C20_app88-fThomas"/>and <seg th:sID="C20_app90-fThomas"/>wealth, rather <seg th:eID="C20_app90-fThomas"/>than the <seg th:sID="C20_app92-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="086" xml:id="F1818_v2_090"/>crime <seg th:eID="C20_app92-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app93-fThomas"/>alleged <seg th:eID="C20_app93-fThomas"/>against <seg th:sID="C20_app95-fThomas"/>him, <seg th:eID="C20_app95-fThomas"/>had been the cause of his <seg th:sID="C20_app99-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>condemnation.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p4">“Felix had <seg th:eID="C20_app99-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app101-fThomas"/>been <seg th:eID="C20_app101-fThomas"/>present at <seg th:sID="C20_app103-fThomas"/>the <seg th:eID="C20_app103-fThomas"/>trial; his horror and <seg th:sID="C20_app107-fThomas"/>indignation were uncontrollable, <seg th:eID="C20_app107-fThomas"/>when he heard the decision of the court. He <seg th:sID="C20_app111-fThomas"/>made, <seg th:eID="C20_app111-fThomas"/>at that <seg th:sID="C20_app113-fThomas"/>moment, <seg th:eID="C20_app113-fThomas"/>a solemn vow to deliver <seg th:sID="C20_app117-fThomas"/>him, <seg th:eID="C20_app117-fThomas"/>and then looked around for the means. After many fruitless attempts to gain admittance to the <seg th:sID="C20_app123-fThomas"/>prison, <seg th:eID="C20_app123-fThomas"/>he found a strongly grated window in an unguarded part of the <seg th:sID="C20_app127-fThomas"/>building, <seg th:eID="C20_app127-fThomas"/>which lighted the dungeon of the unfortunate <seg th:sID="C20_app133-fThomas"/>Mahometan; who, <seg th:eID="C20_app133-fThomas"/>loaded with <seg th:sID="C20_app135-fThomas"/>chains, <seg th:eID="C20_app135-fThomas"/>waited in despair the execution of the barbarous sentence. Felix visited the grate at <seg th:sID="C20_app139-fThomas"/>night, <seg th:eID="C20_app139-fThomas"/>and made known to the prisoner his intentions in his favour. The <seg th:sID="C20_app143-fThomas"/>Turk, <seg th:eID="C20_app143-fThomas"/>amazed and <seg th:sID="C20_app145-fThomas"/>delighted, <seg th:eID="C20_app145-fThomas"/>endeavoured to <seg th:sID="C20_app147-fThomas"/>kindle <seg th:eID="C20_app147-fThomas"/>the zeal of his deliverer by promises of reward and wealth. Felix rejected his offers with <seg th:sID="C20_app155-fThomas"/>contempt; <seg th:eID="C20_app155-fThomas"/>yet <seg th:sID="C20_app157-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="087" xml:id="F1818_v2_091"/>when <seg th:eID="C20_app157-fThomas"/>he saw the lovely <seg th:sID="C20_app161-fThomas"/>Safie, <seg th:eID="C20_app161-fThomas"/>who was allowed to visit her <seg th:sID="C20_app165-fThomas"/>father, <seg th:eID="C20_app165-fThomas"/>and <seg th:sID="C20_app167-fThomas"/>who, <seg th:eID="C20_app167-fThomas"/>by her <seg th:sID="C20_app169-fThomas"/>gestures, <seg th:eID="C20_app169-fThomas"/>expressed her lively gratitude, the youth could not help owning to his own <seg th:sID="C20_app173-fThomas"/>mind, <seg th:eID="C20_app173-fThomas"/>that the captive possessed a treasure which would fully reward his toil and <seg th:sID="C20_app181-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>hazard.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p5">“The <seg th:eID="C20_app181-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>Turk quickly perceived the impression that his daughter had made on <seg th:sID="C20_app183-fThomas"/>the <seg th:eID="C20_app183-fThomas"/>heart of <seg th:sID="C20_app185-fThomas"/>Felix, <seg th:eID="C20_app185-fThomas"/>and <seg th:sID="C20_app187-fThomas"/>endeavoured <seg th:eID="C20_app187-fThomas"/>to secure him <seg th:sID="C20_app191-fThomas"/>more entirely in his interests <seg th:eID="C20_app191-fThomas"/>by the promise <seg th:sID="C20_app195-fThomas"/>of <seg th:eID="C20_app195-fThomas"/>her hand in <seg th:sID="C20_app197-fThomas"/>marriage, so soon as he should be conveyed to a place of safety. <seg th:eID="C20_app197-fThomas"/>Felix was too delicate to accept <seg th:sID="C20_app199-fThomas"/>this offer; <seg th:eID="C20_app199-fThomas"/>yet he looked forward to the probability of <seg th:sID="C20_app204-fThomas"/>that <seg th:eID="C20_app204-fThomas"/>event as <seg th:sID="C20_app206-fThomas"/>to <seg th:eID="C20_app206-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app207-fThomas"/>that <seg th:eID="C20_app207-fThomas"/>consummation <seg th:sID="C20_app209-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>of his happiness.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p6">“During the ensuing days, while the preparations were going forward for the escape of the merchant, the zeal of Felix was warmed by several letters <seg th:eID="C20_app209-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app210-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="088" xml:id="F1818_v2_092"/>that <seg th:eID="C20_app210-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app211-fThomas"/>he received from this lovely girl, who found means to express her thoughts in the language of her lover by the aid of an old man, a servant of her <seg th:eID="C20_app211-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app212-fThomas"/>father’s, <seg th:eID="C20_app212-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app213-fThomas"/>who understood French. She thanked him in the most ardent terms for his intended services towards her <seg th:eID="C20_app213-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app214-fThomas"/>father; <seg th:eID="C20_app214-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app215-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>and at the same time she gently deplored her own fate.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p7">“I have copies of these letters; for I found means, during my residence in the hovel, to procure the implements of writing; and the letters were often in the hands of Felix or Agatha. Before I depart, I will give them to you, they will prove the truth of my tale; but at present, as the sun is already far declined, I shall only have time to repeat the substance of them to you.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p8">“Safie related, that her mother was a Christian Arab, seized and made a slave by the Turks; recommended by <seg th:eID="C20_app215-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app216-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="089" xml:id="F1818_v2_093"/>her <seg th:eID="C20_app216-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app217-fThomas"/>beauty, she had won the heart of the father of Safie, who married her. The young girl spoke in high and enthusiastic terms of her mother, who, born in <seg th:eID="C20_app217-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app218-fThomas"/>freedom <seg th:eID="C20_app218-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app219-fThomas"/>spurned the bondage to which she was now reduced. She instructed her daughter in the tenets of her religion, and taught her to aspire to higher powers of intellect, and an independence of spirit, forbidden to the female followers of Mahomet. This lady died; but her lessons were indelibly impressed on the mind of Safie, who sickened at the prospect of again returning to Asia, and <seg th:eID="C20_app219-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app220-fThomas"/>the <seg th:eID="C20_app220-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app221-fThomas"/>being immured within the walls of a haram, allowed only to occupy herself with <seg th:eID="C20_app221-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app222-fThomas"/>puerile <seg th:eID="C20_app222-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app223-fThomas"/>amusements, ill suited to the temper of her soul, now accustomed to grand ideas and a noble emulation for virtue. The prospect of marrying a Christian, and remaining in a country <seg th:eID="C20_app223-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app224-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="090" xml:id="F1818_v2_094"/>where <seg th:eID="C20_app224-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app225-fThomas"/>women <seg th:eID="C20_app225-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app226-fThomas"/>were <seg th:eID="C20_app226-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app227-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>allowed to take a rank in society, was enchanting to her.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p9">“The day for the execution of the Turk was fixed; but, on the night previous to it, he <seg th:eID="C20_app227-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app228-fThomas"/>had <seg th:eID="C20_app228-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app229-fThomas"/>quitted <seg th:eID="C20_app229-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app231-fThomas"/>prison, and <seg th:eID="C20_app231-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app232-fThomas"/>before <seg th:eID="C20_app232-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app233-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>morning was distant many leagues from Paris. Felix had procured passports in the name of his father, sister, and himself. He had previously communicated his plan to the former, who aided the deceit by quitting his house, under the pretence of a journey, and concealed himself, with his daughter, in an obscure part of Paris.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p10">“Felix conducted the fugitives through France to Lyons, and across Mont Cenis to Leghorn, where the merchant had decided to wait a favourable opportunity of passing into some part of the Turkish dominions.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p11">“Safie resolved to remain with her father until the moment <seg th:eID="C20_app233-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>of <seg th:sID="C20_app235-fThomas"/>his <seg th:eID="C20_app235-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app236-fThomas"/>depar<pb n="091" xml:id="F1818_v2_095"/>ture, <seg th:eID="C20_app236-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app237-fThomas"/>before which time the Turk renewed his promise that she should be united to <seg th:eID="C20_app237-fThomas"/>his <seg th:sID="C20_app239-fThomas"/>deliverer; and Felix remained with them in expectation of that event; and in the mean time he enjoyed the society of the Arabian, who exhibited towards him the simplest and tenderest affection. They conversed with one another through the means of an interpreter, and sometimes with the interpretation of looks; and Safie sang to him <seg th:eID="C20_app239-fThomas"/>the <seg th:sID="C20_app241-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>divine airs of her native country.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p12">“The <seg th:eID="C20_app241-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>Turk <seg th:sID="C20_app243-fThomas"/>allowed this intimacy to take place, and encouraged the hopes of the youthful lovers, while in his heart he had formed far other plans. He loathed the idea that his daughter should be united to a Christian; but he feared the resentment of <seg th:eID="C20_app243-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app244-fThomas"/>Felix <seg th:eID="C20_app244-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app245-fThomas"/>if he should appear lukewarm; for he knew that he was still in the power of his deliverer, if he should choose to betray <seg th:eID="C20_app245-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app246-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="092" xml:id="F1818_v2_096"/>him <seg th:eID="C20_app246-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app247-fThomas"/>to the Italian state which they inhabited. He revolved a thousand plans by which he should be enabled to prolong the deceit until it might be no longer necessary, and secretly to take his daughter with him when he departed. His plans were <seg th:eID="C20_app247-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app248-fThomas"/>greatly <seg th:eID="C20_app248-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app249-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>facilitated by the news which arrived from Paris.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p13">“The government of France were greatly enraged at the escape of their victim, and spared no pains to detect and punish his deliverer. The plot of Felix was quickly discovered, and De Lacey and Agatha were thrown into prison. The news reached Felix, and roused him from his dream of pleasure. His blind and aged father, and his gentle sister, lay in a noisome dungeon, while he enjoyed the free air, and the society of her whom he loved. This idea was <seg th:eID="C20_app249-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app250-fThomas"/>torture <seg th:eID="C20_app250-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app251-fThomas"/>to him. He quickly arranged with the <seg th:eID="C20_app251-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app252-fThomas"/>Turk, <seg th:eID="C20_app252-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app253-fThomas"/>that if the <seg th:eID="C20_app253-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app254-fThomas"/>lat<pb n="093" xml:id="F1818_v2_097"/>ter <seg th:eID="C20_app254-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app255-fThomas"/>should find a favourable opportunity for escape before Felix could return to Italy, <seg th:eID="C20_app255-fThomas"/>Safie <seg th:sID="C20_app257-fThomas"/>should remain as a boarder at a convent at Leghorn; and then, quitting the lovely Arabian, he hastened to Paris, and delivered himself up to the vengeance of the law, hoping to free De Lacey and Agatha by this <seg th:eID="C20_app257-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app258-fThomas"/>proceeding.<note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p13_note1">Thomas copy: pencil mark joins paragraphs.</note> “He <seg th:eID="C20_app258-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app259-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>did not succeed. They remained confined for five months before the trial took place; the result of which deprived them of their fortune, and condemned them to a perpetual exile from their native country.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p14">“They found a miserable asylum in the cottage in Germany, where I discovered them. Felix soon learned that the treacherous Turk, for whom he and his family endured such unheard-of oppression, on discovering that his deliverer was thus reduced to poverty and <seg th:eID="C20_app259-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app260-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="094" xml:id="F1818_v2_098"/>impotence, <seg th:eID="C20_app260-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app261-fThomas"/>became a traitor to good feeling and honour, and had quitted Italy with his daughter, insultingly sending Felix a pittance of <seg th:eID="C20_app261-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app262-fThomas"/>money <seg th:eID="C20_app262-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app263-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>to aid him, as he said, in some plan of future maintenance.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p15">“Such were the events that preyed on the heart of Felix, and rendered him, when I first saw him, the most miserable of his family. He could have endured <seg th:eID="C20_app263-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app264-fThomas"/>poverty, <seg th:eID="C20_app264-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app265-fThomas"/>and <seg th:eID="C20_app265-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app266-fThomas"/>when <seg th:eID="C20_app266-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app267-fThomas"/>this distress had been the meed <seg th:eID="C20_app267-fThomas"/>of his <seg th:sID="C20_app269-fThomas"/>virtue, he <seg th:eID="C20_app269-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app270-fThomas"/>would have <seg th:eID="C20_app270-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app271-fThomas"/>gloried in it: but the ingratitude of the Turk, <seg th:eID="C20_app271-fThomas"/>and <seg th:sID="C20_app273-fThomas"/>the loss of his beloved Safie, were misfortunes more bitter <seg th:eID="C20_app273-fThomas"/>and <seg th:sID="C20_app275-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>irreparable. The arrival of the Arabian now infused new life into his soul.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p16">“When the news reached Leghorn, that Felix was deprived of his wealth and rank, the <seg th:eID="C20_app275-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>merchant <seg th:sID="C20_app277-fThomas"/>commanded his <seg th:eID="C20_app277-fThomas"/>daughter to think no more of <seg th:sID="C20_app279-fThomas"/>her <seg th:eID="C20_app279-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app280-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="095" xml:id="F1818_v2_099"/>lover, <seg th:eID="C20_app280-fThomas"/>but to <seg th:sID="C20_app282-fThomas"/>prepare <seg th:eID="C20_app282-fThomas"/>to return <seg th:sID="C20_app284-fThomas"/>with him <seg th:eID="C20_app284-fThomas"/>to her native <seg th:sID="C20_app286-fThomas"/>country. The <seg th:eID="C20_app286-fThomas"/>generous nature of Safie was outraged by this <seg th:sID="C20_app290-fThomas"/>command; she <seg th:eID="C20_app290-fThomas"/>attempted to expostulate with her <seg th:sID="C20_app292-fThomas"/>father, <seg th:eID="C20_app292-fThomas"/>but he <seg th:sID="C20_app296-fThomas"/>left <seg th:eID="C20_app296-fThomas"/>her <seg th:sID="C20_app298-fThomas"/>angrily, <seg th:eID="C20_app298-fThomas"/>reiterating his tyrannical <seg th:sID="C20_app302-fThomas"/>mandate.<note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p16_note1">Thomas copy: pencil mark joins paragraphs.</note> “A <seg th:eID="C20_app302-fThomas"/>few days <seg th:sID="C20_app304-fThomas"/>after, <seg th:eID="C20_app304-fThomas"/>the Turk entered his <seg th:sID="C20_app308-fThomas"/>daughter’s apartment, <seg th:eID="C20_app308-fThomas"/>and told her <seg th:sID="C20_app310-fThomas"/>hastily, <seg th:eID="C20_app310-fThomas"/>that he had reason to believe that his residence <seg th:sID="C20_app314-fThomas"/>at <seg th:eID="C20_app314-fThomas"/>Leghorn had been <seg th:sID="C20_app316-fThomas"/>divulged, <seg th:eID="C20_app316-fThomas"/>and that he <seg th:sID="C20_app318-fThomas"/>should <seg th:eID="C20_app318-fThomas"/>speedily be delivered up to the French <seg th:sID="C20_app322-fThomas"/>government; <seg th:eID="C20_app322-fThomas"/>he <seg th:sID="C20_app324-fThomas"/>had, <seg th:eID="C20_app324-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app325-fThomas"/>consequently, <seg th:eID="C20_app325-fThomas"/>hired a vessel to convey <seg th:sID="C20_app327-fThomas"/>him <seg th:eID="C20_app327-fThomas"/>to <seg th:sID="C20_app329-fThomas"/>Constantinople, for <seg th:eID="C20_app329-fThomas"/>which city he should sail in <seg th:sID="C20_app333-fThomas"/>a <seg th:eID="C20_app333-fThomas"/>few hours. He intended to leave his daughter under the care of a <seg th:sID="C20_app339-fThomas"/>confidential servant, <seg th:eID="C20_app339-fThomas"/>to follow at her leisure with the greater part of his <seg th:sID="C20_app343-fThomas"/>property, <seg th:eID="C20_app343-fThomas"/>which had not yet arrived at <seg th:sID="C20_app347-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>Leghorn.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p17">“When alone, <seg th:eID="C20_app347-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>Safie <seg th:sID="C20_app349-fThomas"/>resolved <seg th:eID="C20_app349-fThomas"/>in her <seg th:sID="C20_app351-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="096" xml:id="F1818_v2_100"/>own <seg th:eID="C20_app351-fThomas"/>mind the <seg th:sID="C20_app353-fThomas"/>plan <seg th:eID="C20_app353-fThomas"/>of conduct that it <seg th:sID="C20_app355-fThomas"/>would <seg th:eID="C20_app355-fThomas"/>become her to pursue in this <seg th:sID="C20_app357-fThomas"/>emergency. <seg th:eID="C20_app357-fThomas"/>A residence in Turkey was abhorrent to <seg th:sID="C20_app359-fThomas"/>her; <seg th:eID="C20_app359-fThomas"/>her religion and <seg th:sID="C20_app361-fThomas"/>her <seg th:eID="C20_app361-fThomas"/>feelings were alike adverse to it. By some papers of her <seg th:sID="C20_app367-fThomas"/>father’s, <seg th:eID="C20_app367-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app368-fThomas"/>which <seg th:eID="C20_app368-fThomas"/>fell into her <seg th:sID="C20_app370-fThomas"/>hands, <seg th:eID="C20_app370-fThomas"/>she heard of the exile of her <seg th:sID="C20_app374-fThomas"/>lover, <seg th:eID="C20_app374-fThomas"/>and learnt the name of the spot where he <seg th:sID="C20_app380-fThomas"/>then <seg th:eID="C20_app380-fThomas"/>resided. She hesitated some <seg th:sID="C20_app382-fThomas"/>time, <seg th:eID="C20_app382-fThomas"/>but at length she formed her <seg th:sID="C20_app386-fThomas"/>determination. Taking <seg th:eID="C20_app386-fThomas"/>with her some jewels that belonged to her, and a <seg th:sID="C20_app390-fThomas"/>small <seg th:eID="C20_app390-fThomas"/>sum of <seg th:sID="C20_app392-fThomas"/>money, <seg th:eID="C20_app392-fThomas"/>she quitted <seg th:sID="C20_app394-fThomas"/>Italy, <seg th:eID="C20_app394-fThomas"/>with <seg th:sID="C20_app397-fThomas"/>an attendant, <seg th:eID="C20_app397-fThomas"/>a native of <seg th:sID="C20_app401-fThomas"/>Leghorn, <seg th:eID="C20_app401-fThomas"/>but who understood <seg th:sID="C20_app403-fThomas"/>the common language of Turkey, <seg th:eID="C20_app403-fThomas"/>and departed for <seg th:sID="C20_app405-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>Germany.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter13_div4_div14_p18">“She <seg th:eID="C20_app405-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>arrived in safety at a town about <seg th:sID="C20_app409-fThomas"/>twenty <seg th:eID="C20_app409-fThomas"/>leagues from the cottage of De <seg th:sID="C20_app413-fThomas"/>Lacey, when <seg th:eID="C20_app413-fThomas"/>her attendant fell dangerously <seg th:sID="C20_app417-fThomas"/>ill. <seg th:eID="C20_app417-fThomas"/>Safie nursed her with the most devoted <seg th:sID="C20_app421-fThomas"/>affection; <seg th:eID="C20_app421-fThomas"/>but the <seg th:sID="C20_app423-fThomas"/>
               <pb n="097" xml:id="F1818_v2_101"/>poor <seg th:eID="C20_app423-fThomas"/>girl <seg th:sID="C20_app425-fThomas"/>died, and the <seg th:eID="C20_app425-fThomas"/>Arabian was <seg th:sID="C20_app427-fThomas"/>left <seg th:eID="C20_app427-fThomas"/>
               <seg th:sID="C20_app428-fThomas"/>alone, <seg th:eID="C20_app428-fThomas"/>unacquainted with the language of the <seg th:sID="C20_app430-fThomas"/>country, <seg th:eID="C20_app430-fThomas"/>and utterly ignorant of the customs of the <seg th:sID="C20_app434-fThomas"/>world. <seg th:eID="C20_app434-fThomas"/>She <seg th:sID="C20_app436-fThomas"/>fell, however, into <seg th:eID="C20_app436-fThomas"/>good <seg th:sID="C20_app438-fThomas"/>hands. <seg th:eID="C20_app438-fThomas"/>The Italian <seg th:sID="C20_app440-fThomas"/>had <seg th:eID="C20_app440-fThomas"/>mentioned the name of the spot for which they were <seg th:sID="C20_app444-fThomas"/>bound; and, <seg th:eID="C20_app444-fThomas"/>after her <seg th:sID="C20_app448-fThomas"/>death, <seg th:eID="C20_app448-fThomas"/>the woman of the house in which they had lived took care that Safie should arrive <seg th:sID="C20_app454-fThomas"/>in safety <seg th:eID="C20_app454-fThomas"/>at the cottage of her <seg th:sID="C20_app458-fThomas__Pt1" part="I"/>lover.</p>
            <milestone n="13" type="end" unit="chapter"/> 
            <seg th:eID="C20_app458-fThomas__Pt2" part="F"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
