<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>frequently conversed with me on mine, which I have communicated to him
    without disguise. He entered attentively into all my arguments in favour of my eventual
    success, and into every minute detail of the measures I had taken to secure it. I was
    easily led by the sympathy which he evinced, to use the language of my heart; to give
    utterance to the burning ardour of my soul; and to say, with all the fervour that warmed
    me, how gladly I would sacrifice my fortune, my existence, my every hope, to the
    furtherance of my enterprise. One man’s life or death were but a small price to pay for
    the acquirement of the knowledge which I sought; for the dominion I should acquire and
    transmit over the elemental foes of our race. As I spoke, a dark gloom spread over my
    listener’s countenance. At first I perceived that he tried to suppress his emotion; he
    placed his hands before his eyes; and my voice quivered and failed me, as I beheld tears
    trickle fast from between his fingers,—a groan burst from his heaving breast. I paused;
    —at length he spoke, in broken accents:—“Unhappy man! Do you share my madness? Have you
    drank also of the intoxicating draught? Hear me,—let me reveal my tale, and you will
    dash the cup from your lips!”<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p27"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p28"/>Such words, you may imagine, strongly excited my curiosity; but the paroxysm of grief
    that had seized the stranger overcame his weakened powers, and many hours of repose and
    tranquil conversation were necessary to restore his composure.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p28"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p29"/>Having conquered the violence of his feelings, he appeared to despise himself for being
    the slave of passion; and quelling the dark tyranny of despair, he led me again to
    converse concerning myself personally. He asked me the history of my earlier years. The
    tale was quickly told: <pb xml:id="F1831_v_032" n="16"/>but it awakened various trains of
    reflection. I spoke of my desire of finding a friend—of my thirst for a more intimate
    sympathy with a fellow mind than had ever fallen to my lot; and expressed my conviction
    that a man could boast of little happiness, who did not enjoy this blessing.<p eID="novel1_letter4_div4_p29"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_div4_p30"/>“I agree with you,” replied the stranger; “we are unfashioned creatures, but half made
    up, if one wiser, better, dearer than ourselves—such a friend ought to be—do not lend
    his aid to perfectionate our weak and faulty natures.</xml>
