<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p4"/>My temper was sometimes violent, and my passions vehement; but by some law in my
    temperature they were turned, not towards childish pursuits, but to an eager desire to
    learn, and not to learn all things indiscriminately. I confess that neither the
    structure of languages, nor the code of governments, nor the politics of various states,
    possessed attractions for me. It was the secrets of heaven and earth that I desired to
    learn; and whether it was the outward substance of things, or the inner spirit of nature
    and the mysterious soul of man that occupied me, still my enquiries were directed to the
    metaphysical, or, in its highest sense, the physical secrets of the world.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p4"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p5"/>Meanwhile Clerval occupied himself, so to speak, with the moral relations of things.
    The busy stage of life, the virtues of heroes, and the actions of men, were his theme;
    and his hope and his dream was to become one among those <pb xml:id="F1831_v_041" n="25"/>whose names are recorded in story, as the gallant and adventurous benefactors of our
    species. The saintly soul of Elizabeth shone like a shrine-dedicated lamp in our
    peaceful home. Her sympathy was ours; her smile, her soft voice, the sweet glance of her
    celestial eyes, were ever there to bless and animate us. She was the living spirit of
    love to soften and attract: I might have become sullen in my study, rough through the
    ardour of my nature, but that she was there to subdue me to a semblance of her own
    gentleness. And Clerval—could aught ill entrench on the noble spirit of Clerval?—yet
    he might not have been so perfectly humane, so thoughtful in his generosity—so full of
    kindness and tenderness amidst his passion for adventurous exploit, had she not unfolded
    to him the real loveliness of beneficence, and made the doing good the end and aim of
    his soaring ambition.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter2_div4_div2_p5"/>
</xml>
