<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C33"/>
   <p>September 2d.</p>
   <p>
      <hi rend="smallcaps">MY BELOVED SISTER</hi>,</p>
   <p>I write to you, encompassed by peril, and ignorant whether I am ever doomed to see again
          dear England, and the dearer friends that inhabit it. I <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_168" n="164"/>am surrounded by mountains of ice, which admit of no escape, and threaten
          every moment to crush my vessel. The brave fellows, whom I have persuaded to be my
          companions, look towards me for aid; but I have none to bestow. There is something terribly
          appalling in our situation, yet my courage and hopes do not desert me. We may survive; and
          if we do not, I will repeat the lessons of my Seneca, and die with a good heart.</p>
   <p>Yet what, Margaret, will be the state of your mind? You will not hear of my destruction,
          and you will anxiously await my return. Years will pass, and you will have visitings of
          despair, and yet be tortured by hope. Oh! my beloved sister, the sickening failings of
          your heart-felt expectations are, in prospect, more terrible to me than my own death. But
          you have a <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_169" n="165"/>husband, and lovely children; you may be
          happy: heaven bless you, and make you so!</p>
   <p>My unfortunate guest regards me with the tenderest compassion. He endeavours to fill me
          with hope; and talks as if life were a possession which he valued. He reminds me how often
          the same accidents have happened to other navigators, who have attempted this sea, and, in
          spite of myself, he fills me with cheerful auguries. Even the sailors feel the power of
          his eloquence: when he speaks, they no longer despair; he rouses their energies, and,
          while they hear his voice, they believe these vast mountains of ice are mole-hills, which
          will vanish before the resolutions of man. These feelings are transitory; each day’s
          expectation delayed fills them with fear, and I almost dread a mutiny caused by this
          despair.</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_170" n="166"/>September 5th.</p>
   <p>A scene has just passed of such uncommon interest, that although it is highly probable
          that these papers may never reach you, yet I cannot forbear recording it.</p>
   <p>We are still surrounded by mountains of ice, still in imminent danger of being crushed in
          their conflict. The cold is excessive, and many of my unfortunate comrades have already
          found a grave amidst this scene of desolation. Frankenstein has daily declined in health:
          a feverish fire still glimmers in his eyes; but he is exhausted, and, when suddenly roused
          to any exertion, he speedily sinks again into apparent lifelessness.</p>
   <p>I mentioned in my last letter the fears I entertained of a mutiny. This morning, as I sat
          watching the wan countenance of my friend—his eyes <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_171" n="167"/>half closed, and his limbs hanging listlessly,—I was roused by half a dozen of the
          sailors, who desired admission into the cabin. They entered; and their leader addressed
          me. He told me that he and his companions had been chosen by the other sailors to come in
          deputation to me, to make me a demand, which, in justice, I could not refuse. We were
          immured in ice, and should probably never escape; but they feared that if, as was
          possible, the ice should dissipate, and a free passage be opened, I should be rash enough
          to continue my voyage, and lead them into fresh dangers, after they might happily have
          surmounted this. They desired, therefore, that I should engage with a solemn promise, that
          if the vessel should be freed, I would instantly direct my course southward.</p>
   <p>This speech troubled me. I had <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_172" n="168"/>not despaired; nor
          had I yet conceived the idea of returning, if set free. Yet could I, in justice, or even
          in possibility, refuse this demand? I hesitated before I answered; when Frankenstein, who
          had at first been silent, and, indeed, appeared hardly to have force enough to attend, now
          roused himself; his eyes sparkled, and his cheeks flushed with momentary vigour. Turning
          towards the men, he said—</p>
   <p>“What do you mean? What do you demand of your captain? Are you then so easily turned from
          your design? Did you not call this a glorious expedition? and wherefore was it glorious?
          Not because the way was smooth and placid as a southern sea, but because it was full of
          dangers and terror; because, at every new incident, your fortitude was to be called forth,
          and your courage exhibited; because <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_173" n="169"/>danger and death
          surrounded, and these dangers you were to brave and overcome. For this was it a glorious,
          for this was it an honourable undertaking. You were hereafter to be hailed as the
          benefactors of your species; your name<add place="margin">s</add> adored, as belonging to brave men who encountered
          death for honour and the benefit of mankind. And now, behold, with the first imagination
          of danger, or, if you will, the first mighty and terrific trial of your courage, you
          shrink away, and are content to be handed down as men who had not strength enough to
          endure cold and peril; and so, poor souls, they were chilly, and returned to their warm
          fire-sides. Why, that requires not this preparation; ye need not have come thus far, and
          dragged your captain to the shame of a defeat, merely to prove yourselves cowards. Oh! be
          men, or <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_174" n="170"/>be more than men. Be steady to your
          purposes, and firm as a rock. This ice is not made of such stuff as your hearts might be;
          it is mutable, cannot withstand you, if you say that it shall not. Do not return to your
          families with the stigma of disgrace marked on your brows. Return as heroes who have
          fought and conquered, and who know not what it is to turn their backs on the foe.”</p>
   <p>He spoke this with a voice so modulated to the different feelings expressed in his
          speech, with an eye so full of lofty design and heroism, that can you wonder that these
          men were moved. They looked at one another, and were unable to reply. I spoke; I told them
          to retire, and consider of what had been said: that I would not lead them further north,
          if they strenuously desired the contrary; but that I hoped <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_175" n="171"/>that, with reflection, their courage would return.</p>
   <p>They retired, and I turned towards my friend; but he was sunk in languor, and almost
          deprived of life.</p>
   <p>How all this will terminate, I know not; but I had rather die, than return shamefully,—my
          purpose unfulfilled. Yet I fear such will be my fate; the men, unsupported by ideas of
          glory and honour, can never willingly continue to endure their present hardships.</p>
   <p>September 7th.</p>
   <p>The die is cast; I have consented to return, if we are not destroyed. Thus are my hopes
          blasted by cowardice and indecision; I come back ignorant and disappointed. It requires
          more philosophy than I possess, to bear this injustice with patience.</p>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_176" n="172"/>
   <p>September 12th.</p>
   <p>It is past; I am returning to England. I have lost my hopes of utility and glory;—I have
          lost my friend. But I will endeavour to detail these bitter circumstances to you, my dear
          sister; and, while I am wafted towards England, and towards you, I will not despond.</p>
   <p>September 19th, <comment elem="note"
               type="editor"
               resp="rm"
               text="PDF displays 19 but correct date               should be SEPTEMBER 9"/> the ice began to move, and roarings like
          thunder were heard at a distance, as the islands split and cracked in every direction. We
          were in the most imminent peril; but, as we could only remain passive, my chief attention
          was occupied by my unfortunate guest, whose illness increased in such a degree, that he
          was entirely confined to his bed. The ice cracked behind us, and was driven with force
          towards the north; a breeze sprung from the west, and on the 11th <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_177" n="173"/>the passage towards the south became perfectly free.
          When the sailors saw this, and that their return to their native country was apparently
          assured, a shout of tumultuous joy broke from them, loud and long-continued. Frankenstein,
          who was dozing, awoke, and asked the cause of the tumult. “They shout,” I said, “because
          they will soon return to England.”</p>
   <p>“Do you then really return?”</p>
   <p>“Alas! yes; I cannot withstand their demands. I cannot lead them unwillingly to danger,
          and I must return.”</p>
   <p>“Do so, if you will; but I will not. You may give up your purpose; but mine is assigned
          to me by heaven, and I dare not. I am weak; but surely the spirits who assist my vengeance
          will endow me with sufficient strength.” Saying this, he endeavoured to spring from the
          bed, but the exertion was <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_178" n="174"/>too great for him; he fell
          back, and fainted.</p>
   <p>It was long before he was restored; and I often thought that life was entirely extinct.
          At length he opened his eyes, but he breathed with difficulty, and was unable to speak.
          The surgeon gave him a composing draught, and ordered us to leave him undisturbed. In the
          mean time he told me, that my friend had certainly not many hours to live.</p>
   <p>His sentence was pronounced; and I could only grieve, and be patient. I sat by his bed
          watching him; his eyes were closed, and I thought he slept; but presently he called to me
          in a feeble voice, and, bidding me come near, said—“Alas! the strength I relied on is
          gone; I feel that I shall soon die, and he, my enemy and persecutor, may still be in
          being. Think <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_179" n="175"/>not, Walton, that in the last moments
          of my existence I feel that burning hatred, and ardent desire of revenge, I once expressed;
          but I feel myself justified in desiring the death of my adversary. During these last days
          I have been occupied in examining my past conduct; nor do I find it blameable. In a fit of
          enthusiastic madness I created a rational creature, and was bound towards him, to assure,
          as far as was in my power, his happiness and well-being. This was my duty; but there was
          another still paramount to that. My duties towards my fellow-creatures had greater claims
          to my attention, because they included a greater proportion of happiness or misery. Urged
          by this view, I refused, and I did right in refusing, to create a companion for the first
          creature. He showed unparalleled malignity and selfishness, in <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_180" n="176"/>evil: he destroyed my friends; he devoted to destruction beings who
          possessed exquisite sensations, happiness, and wisdom; nor do I know where this thirst for
          vengeance may end. Miserable himself, that he may render no other wretched, he ought to
          die. The task of his destruction was mine, but I have failed. When actuated by selfish and
          vicious motives, I asked you to undertake my unfinished work; and I renew this request
          now, when I am only induced by reason and virtue.</p>
   <p>“Yet I cannot ask you to renounce your country and friends, to fulfil this task; and
          now, that you are returning to England, you will have little chance of meeting with him.
          But the consideration of these points, and the well-balancing of what you may esteem your
          duties, I leave to you; my judg<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_181" n="177"/>ment and ideas are
          already disturbed by the near approach of death. I dare not ask you to do what I think
          right, for I may still be misled by passion.</p>
   <p>“That he should live to be an instrument of mischief disturbs me; in other respects this
          hour, when I momentarily expect my release, is the only happy one which I have enjoyed for
          several years. The forms of the beloved dead flit before me, and I hasten to their arms.
          Farewell, Walton! Seek happiness in tranquillity, and avoid ambition, even if it be only
          the apparently innocent one of distinguishing yourself in science and discoveries. Yet why
          do I say this? I have myself been blasted in these hopes, yet another may succeed.”</p>
   <p>His voice became fainter as he spoke; and at length, exhausted by <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_182" n="178"/>his effort, he sunk into silence. About half an hour
          afterwards he attempted again to speak, but was unable; he pressed my hand feebly, and his
          eyes closed for ever, while the irradiation of a gentle smile passed away from his
          lips.</p>
   <p>Margaret, what comment can I make on the untimely extinction of this glorious spirit?
          What can I say, that will enable you to understand the depth of my sorrow? All that I
          should express would be inadequate and feeble. My tears flow; my mind is overshadowed by a
          cloud of disappointment. But I journey towards England, and I may there find
          consolation.</p>
   <p>I am interrupted. What do these sounds portend? It is midnight; the breeze blows fairly,
          and the watch on deck scarcely stir. Again; there is a sound as of a human voice, but <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_183" n="179"/>hoarser; it comes from the cabin where the remains of
          Frankenstein still lie. I must arise, and examine. Good night, my sister.</p>
   <p>Great God! what a scene has just taken place! I am yet dizzy with the remembrance of it.
          I hardly know whether I shall have the power to detail it; yet the tale which I have
          recorded would be incomplete without this final and wonderful catastrophe.</p>
   <p>I entered the cabin, where lay the remains of my ill-fated and admirable friend. Over him
          hung a form which I cannot find words to describe; gigantic in stature, yet uncouth and
          distorted in its proportions. As he hung over the coffin, his face was concealed by long
          locks of ragged hair; but one vast hand was extended, in colour and apparent texture like
          that of a mummy. When he heard the sound of my ap<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_184" n="180"/>proach, he ceased to utter exclamations of grief and horror, and sprung towards the
          window. Never did I behold a vision so horrible as his face, of such loathsome, yet
          appalling hideousness. I shut my eyes involuntarily, and endeavoured to recollect what
          were my duties with regard to this destroyer. I called on him to stay.</p>
   <p>He paused, looking on me with wonder; and, again turning towards the lifeless form of his
          creator, he seemed to forget my presence, and every feature and gesture seemed instigated
          by the wildest rage of some uncontrollable passion.</p>
   <p>“That is also my victim!” he exclaimed; “in his murder my crimes are consummated; the
          miserable series of my being is wound to its close! Oh, Frankenstein! generous and
          self-devoted being! what does it avail that <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_185" n="181"/>I now
          ask thee to pardon me? I, who irretrievably destroyed thee by destroying all thou lovedst.
          Alas! he is cold; he may not answer me.”</p>
   <p>His voice seemed suffocated; and my first impulses, which had suggested to me the duty of
          obeying the dying request of my friend, in destroying his enemy, were now suspended by a
          mixture of curiosity and compassion. I approached this tremendous being; I dared not again
          raise my looks upon his face, there was something so scaring and unearthly in his
          ugliness. I attempted to speak, but the words died away on my lips. The monster continued
          to utter wild and incoherent self-reproaches. At length I gathered resolution to address
          him, in a pause of the tempest of his passion: “Your repentance,” I said, “is now
          superfluous. If you had listened to the voice of con<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_186" n="182"/>science, and heeded the stings of remorse, before you had urged your diabolical
          vengeance to this extremity, Frankenstein would yet have lived.”</p>
   <p>“And do you dream?” said the dæmon; “do you think that I was then dead to agony and
          remorse?—He,” he continued, pointing to the corpse, “he suffered not more in the
          consummation of the deed;—oh! not the ten-thousandth portion of the anguish that was mine
          during the lingering detail of its execution. A frightful selfishness hurried me on, while
          my heart was poisoned with remorse. Think ye that the groans of Clerval were music to my
          ears? My heart was fashioned to be susceptible of love and sympathy; and, when wrenched by
          misery to vice and hatred, it did not endure the violence of the change without torture
          such as you cannot even imagine.</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_187" n="183"/>“After the murder of Clerval, I returned to
          Switzerland, heartbroken and overcome. I pitied Frankenstein; my pity amounted to horror: I
          abhorred myself. But when I discovered that he, the author at once of my existence and of
          its unspeakable torments, dared to hope for happiness; that while he accumulated
          wretchedness and despair upon me, he sought his own enjoyment in feelings and passions from
          the indulgence of which I was for ever barred, then impotent envy and bitter indignation
          filled me with an insatiable thirst for vengeance. I recollected my threat, and resolved
          that it should be accomplished. I knew that I was preparing for myself a deadly torture;
          but I was the slave, not the master of an impulse, which I detested, yet could not
          disobey. Yet when she died!—nay, then I was not miserable. I had cast <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_188" n="184"/>off all feeling, subdued all anguish to riot in the
          excess of my despair. Evil thenceforth became my good. Urged thus far, I had no choice but
          to adapt my nature to an element which I had willingly chosen. The completion of my
          demoniacal design became an insatiable passion. And now it is ended; there is my last
          victim!”</p>
   <p>I was at first touched by the expressions of his misery; yet, when I called to mind what
          Frankenstein had said of his powers of eloquence and persuasion, and when I again cast my
          eyes on the lifeless form of my friend, indignation was re-kindled within me. “Wretch!” I
          said, “it is well that you come here to whine over the desolation that you have made. You
          throw a torch into a pile of buildings; and when they are consumed you sit among the
          ruins, and lament the fall. Hypo<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_189" n="185"/>critical fiend! if
          he whom you mourn still lived, still would he be the object, again would he become the
          prey of your accursed vengeance. It is not pity that you feel; you lament only because the
          victim of your malignity is withdrawn from your power.”</p>
   <p>“Oh, it is not thus—not thus,” interrupted the being; “yet such must be the impression
          conveyed to you by what appears to be the purport of my actions. Yet I seek not a
          fellow-feeling in my misery. No sympathy may I ever find. When I first sought it, it was
          the love of virtue, the feelings of happiness and affection with which my whole being
          overflowed, that I wished to be participated. But now, that virtue has become to me a
          shadow, and that happiness and affection are turned into bitter and loathing despair, in
          what should I seek for sym<pb xml:id="F1818_v3_190" n="186"/>pathy? I am content to
          suffer alone, while my sufferings shall endure: when I die, I am well satisfied that
          abhorrence and opprobrium should load my memory. Once my fancy was soothed with dreams of
          virtue, of fame, and of enjoyment. Once I falsely hoped to meet with beings, who,
          pardoning my outward form, would love me for the excellent qualities which I was capable
          of bringing forth. I was nourished with high thoughts of honour and devotion. But now vice
          has degraded me beneath the meanest animal. No crime, no mischief, no malignity, no
          misery, can be found comparable to mine. When I call over the frightful catalogue of my
          deeds, I cannot believe that I am he whose thoughts were once filled with sublime and
          transcendent visions of the beauty and the majesty of goodness. But it is even so; <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_191" n="187"/>the fallen angel becomes a malignant devil. Yet even
          that enemy of God and man had friends and associates in his desolation; I am quite
          alone.</p>
   <p>“You, who call Frankenstein your friend, seem to have a knowledge of my crimes and his
          misfortunes. But, in the detail which he gave you of them, he could not sum up the hours
          and months of misery which I endured, wasting in impotent passions. For whilst I destroyed
          his hopes, I did not satisfy my own desires. They were for ever ardent and craving; still
          I desired love and fellowship, and I was still spurned. Was there no injustice in this? Am
          I to be thought the only criminal, when all human kind sinned against me? Why do you not
          hate Felix, who drove his friend from his door with contumely? Why do you not execrate the
          rustic who sought to <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_192" n="188"/>destroy the saviour of his
          child? Nay, these are virtuous and immaculate beings! I, the miserable and the abandoned,
          am an abortion, to be spurned at, and kicked, and trampled on. Even now my blood boils at
          the recollection of this injustice.</p>
   <p>“But it is true that I am a wretch. I have murdered the lovely and the helpless; I have
          strangled the innocent as they slept, and grasped to death his throat who never injured me
          or any other living thing. I have devoted my creator, the select specimen of all that is
          worthy of love and admiration among men, to misery; I have pursued him even to that
          irremediable ruin. There he lies, white and cold in death. You hate me; but your
          abhorrence cannot equal that with which I regard myself. I look on the hands which
          executed the deed; I think on the <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_193" n="189"/>heart in which the
          imagination of it was conceived, and long for the moment when they will meet my eyes, when
          it will haunt my thoughts, no more.</p>
   <p>“Fear not that I shall be the instrument of future mischief. My work is nearly complete.
          Neither your’s nor any man’s death is needed to consummate the series of my being, and
          accomplish that which must be done; but it requires my own. Do not think that I shall be
          slow to perform this sacrifice. I shall quit your vessel on the ice-raft which brought me
          hither, and shall seek the most northern extremity of the globe; I shall collect my
          funeral pile, and consume to ashes this miserable frame, that its remains may afford no
          light to any curious and unhallowed wretch, who would create such another as I have been.
          I shall <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_194" n="190"/>die. I shall no longer feel the agonies
          which now consume me, or be the prey of feelings unsatisfied, yet unquenched. He is dead
          who called me into being; and when I shall be no more, the very remembrance of us both
          will speedily vanish. I shall no longer see the sun or stars, or feel the winds play on my
          cheeks. Light, feeling, and sense, will pass away; and in this condition must I find my
          happiness. Some years ago, when the images which this world affords first opened
          upon me, when I felt the cheering warmth of summer, and heard the rustling of the leaves
          and the chirping of the birds, and these were all to me, I should have wept to die; now it
          is my only consolation. Polluted by crimes, and torn by the bitterest remorse, where can I
          find rest but in death?</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_195" n="191"/>“Farewell! I leave you, and in you the last of
          human kind whom these eyes will ever behold. Farewell, Frankenstein! If thou wert yet
          alive, and yet cherished a desire of revenge against me, it would be better satiated in my
          life than in my destruction. But it was not so; thou didst seek my extinction, that I
          might not cause greater wretchedness; and if yet, in some mode unknown to me, thou hast
          not yet ceased to think and feel, thou desirest not my life for my own misery. Blasted as
          thou wert, my agony was still superior to thine; for the bitter sting of remorse may not
          cease to rankle in my wounds until death shall close them for ever.</p>
   <p>“But soon,” he cried, with sad and solemn enthusiasm, “I shall die, and what I now feel
          be no longer felt. Soon these burning miseries will be extinct. I shall ascend my funeral 
          <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_196" n="192"/>pile triumphantly, and exult in the agony of the
          torturing flames. The light of that conflagration will fade away; my ashes will be swept
          into the sea by the winds. My spirit will sleep in peace; or if it thinks, it will not
          surely think thus. Farewell.”</p>
   <p>He sprung from the cabin-window, as he said this, upon the ice-raft which lay close to
          the vessel. He was soon borne away by the waves, and lost in darkness and distance.</p>
   <head>THE END.</head>
   <milestone unit="letter" type="end" n="4"/>
   <milestone unit="novel" type="end" n="1"/>
   <milestone unit="backmatter" type="start" n="1"/>
   <include href="standOff_Includes/1818_backMatter.xml" parse="xml"/>
   <milestone unit="backmatter" type="end" n="1"/>
</xml>
