<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein"
     xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
     xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1823, Collation unit C19</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Produced from collation output: 2018-07-23 21:10:08.230935 </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="collation">
            <seg th:sID="C19_app1-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            <milestone n="12" type="start" unit="chapter"/>
            <head xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_head1">CHAPTER I.</head>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p1">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app1-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“I <seg th:eID="C19_app1-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app2-f1823"/>
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p1_hi1">NOW</hi> hasten to the more moving part of my story. I shall relate <seg th:eID="C19_app2-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app3-f1823"/>events, <seg th:eID="C19_app3-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app4-f1823"/>that impressed me with feelings which, from what I <seg th:eID="C19_app4-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app5-f1823"/>had been, <seg th:eID="C19_app5-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app6-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>have made me what I am.<seg th:eID="C19_app6-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p2">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app6-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“Spring advanced rapidly; the weather became fine, and the skies cloudless. It surprised me, that what before was desert and gloomy should now bloom with the most beautiful flowers and verdure. My senses were gratified and refreshed by a thousand scents of delight, and a thousand sights of <seg th:eID="C19_app6-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app7-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>beauty.<seg th:eID="C19_app7-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p3">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app7-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <pb n="2" xml:id="F1823_v2_275"/>“It <seg th:eID="C19_app7-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app8-f1823"/>was on one of these days, when my cottagers periodically rested from labour—the old man played on his guitar, and the children listened to <seg th:eID="C19_app8-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app9-f1823"/>him—that I <seg th:eID="C19_app9-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app10-f1823"/>observed <seg th:eID="C19_app10-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app12-f1823"/>the countenance of Felix was melancholy beyond expression; he sighed frequently; and once his father paused in his music, and I conjectured by his manner that he <seg th:eID="C19_app12-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app13-f1823"/>inquired <seg th:eID="C19_app13-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app14-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>the cause of his son’s sorrow. Felix replied in a cheerful accent, and the old man was recommencing his music, when some one tapped at the door.<seg th:eID="C19_app14-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p4">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app14-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“It was a lady on horseback, accompanied by a countryman as a guide. The lady was dressed in a dark suit, and covered with a thick black veil. Agatha asked a question; to which the stranger only replied by pronouncing, in a sweet accent, the name of Felix. Her voice was musical, but unlike that of <seg th:eID="C19_app14-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app15-f1823"/>
               <pb n="3" xml:id="F1823_v2_276"/>either <seg th:eID="C19_app15-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app16-f1823"/>of my friends. On hearing this word, Felix came up hastily to the lady; who, when she saw him, threw up her veil, and I beheld a countenance of angelic beauty and expression. Her hair of a shining <seg th:eID="C19_app16-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app17-f1823"/>raven <seg th:eID="C19_app17-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app18-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>black, and curiously braided; her eyes were dark, but gentle, although animated; her features of a regular proportion, and her complexion wondrously fair, each cheek tinged with a lovely pink.<seg th:eID="C19_app18-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p5">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app18-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“Felix seemed ravished with delight when he saw her, every trait of sorrow vanished from his face, and it instantly expressed a degree of ecstatic joy, of which I could hardly have believed it capable; his eyes sparkled, as his cheek flushed with pleasure; and at that moment I thought him as beautiful as the stranger. She appeared affected by different feelings; wiping a few tears from her lovely eyes, <seg th:eID="C19_app18-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app19-f1823"/>
               <pb n="4" xml:id="F1823_v2_277"/>she <seg th:eID="C19_app19-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app20-f1823"/>held out her hand to Felix, who kissed it rapturously, and called her, as well as I could distinguish, his sweet Arabian. She did not appear to understand him, but smiled. He assisted her to dismount, <seg th:eID="C19_app20-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app21-f1823"/>and <seg th:eID="C19_app21-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app22-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>dismissing her guide, conducted her into the cottage. Some conversation took place between him and his father; and the young stranger knelt at the old man’s feet, and would have kissed his hand, but he raised her, and embraced her affectionately.<seg th:eID="C19_app22-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p6">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app22-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“I soon perceived, that although the stranger uttered articulate sounds, and appeared to have a language of her own, she was neither understood by, <seg th:eID="C19_app22-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app23-f1823"/>nor <seg th:eID="C19_app23-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app24-f1823"/>herself understood, the cottagers. They made many signs which I did not comprehend; but I saw that her presence diffused gladness through the cottage, dispelling their sorrow as the sun dissipates the morning mists. Felix seemed <seg th:eID="C19_app24-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app25-f1823"/>
               <pb n="5" xml:id="F1823_v2_278"/>peculiarly <seg th:eID="C19_app25-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app26-f1823"/>happy, and with smiles of delight welcomed his Arabian. Agatha, the ever-gentle Agatha, kissed the hands of the lovely stranger; and, pointing to her brother, made signs which appeared to me to mean that he had been sorrowful until she came. Some hours passed thus, while they, by their countenances, expressed joy, the cause of which I did not comprehend. Presently I found, by the frequent recurrence of <seg th:eID="C19_app26-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app27-f1823"/>some <seg th:eID="C19_app27-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app28-f1823"/>sound which the stranger repeated after them, that she was endeavouring to learn their language; and the idea instantly occurred to me, that I should make use of the same instructions to the same end. The stranger learned about twenty words at the first lesson, most of <seg th:eID="C19_app28-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app29-f1823"/>them, indeed, <seg th:eID="C19_app29-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app30-f1823"/>were those which I had before understood, but I profited by the <seg th:eID="C19_app30-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app31-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>others.<seg th:eID="C19_app31-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p7">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app31-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“As <seg th:eID="C19_app31-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app32-f1823"/>night came on, Agatha and the <seg th:eID="C19_app32-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app33-f1823"/>
               <pb n="6" xml:id="F1823_v2_279"/>Arabian <seg th:eID="C19_app33-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app34-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>retired early. When they separated, Felix kissed the hand of the stranger, and said, ‘Good night, sweet Safie.’ He sat up much longer, conversing with his father; and, by the frequent repetition of her name, I conjectured that their lovely guest was the subject of their conversation. I ardently desired to understand them, and bent every faculty towards that purpose, but found it utterly impossible.<seg th:eID="C19_app34-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p8">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app34-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“The next morning Felix went out to his work; and, after the usual occupations of Agatha were finished, the Arabian sat at the feet of the old man, and, taking his guitar, played some airs so entrancingly beautiful, that they at once drew tears of sorrow and delight from my eyes. She sang, and her voice flowed in a rich cadence, swelling or dying away, like a nightingale of the <seg th:eID="C19_app34-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app35-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>woods.<seg th:eID="C19_app35-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p9">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app35-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <pb n="7" xml:id="F1823_v2_280"/>“When <seg th:eID="C19_app35-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app36-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>she had finished, she gave the guitar to Agatha, who at first declined it. She played a simple air, and her voice accompanied it in sweet accents, but unlike the wondrous strain of the stranger. The old man appeared enraptured, and said some words, which Agatha endeavoured to explain to Safie, and by which he appeared to wish to express that she bestowed on him the greatest delight by her music.<seg th:eID="C19_app36-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p10">“The days now passed as peaceably as before, with the sole alteration, that joy had taken place of sadness in the countenances of my friends. Safie was always gay and happy; she and I improved rapidly in the knowledge of language, so that in two months I began to comprehend most of the words uttered by my protectors.</p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p11">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app36-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“In the meanwhile also the black ground was covered with herbage, and <seg th:eID="C19_app36-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app37-f1823"/>
               <pb n="8" xml:id="F1823_v2_281"/>the <seg th:eID="C19_app37-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app38-f1823"/>green banks interspersed with innumerable flowers, sweet to the scent and the eyes, stars of pale radiance among the moonlight woods; the sun became warmer, the nights clear and balmy; and my nocturnal rambles were an extreme pleasure to me, although they were considerably shortened by the late setting and early rising of the sun; for I never ventured abroad during daylight, fearful of meeting with the same treatment <seg th:eID="C19_app38-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app40-f1823"/>I had formerly endured in the first village which <seg th:eID="C19_app40-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app42-f1823"/>I <seg th:eID="C19_app42-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app43-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>entered.<seg th:eID="C19_app43-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p12">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app43-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“My <seg th:eID="C19_app43-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app44-f1823"/>days were spent in close attention, that I might <seg th:eID="C19_app44-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app45-f1823"/>more <seg th:eID="C19_app45-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app46-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>speedily master the language; and I may boast that I improved more rapidly than the Arabian, who understood very little, and conversed in broken accents, whilst I comprehended and could imitate almost every word that was spoken.<seg th:eID="C19_app46-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p13">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app46-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“While I improved in speech, I also <seg th:eID="C19_app46-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app47-f1823"/>
               <pb n="9" xml:id="F1823_v2_282"/>learned <seg th:eID="C19_app47-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app48-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>the science of letters, as it was taught to the stranger; and this opened before me a wide field for wonder and delight.<seg th:eID="C19_app48-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p14">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app48-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“The book from which Felix instructed Safie was Volney’s <seg th:eID="C19_app48-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app49-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
               <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p14_hi1">
                  <seg th:sID="C19_app49-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>Ruins <seg th:eID="C19_app49-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
                  <seg th:sID="C19_app50-f1823"/>of <seg th:eID="C19_app50-f1823"/>
                  <seg th:sID="C19_app51-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>Empires<seg th:eID="C19_app51-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
               </hi>. <seg th:eID="C19_app51-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app52-f1823"/>I should not have understood the purport of this book, had not Felix, in reading it, given very minute explanations. He had chosen this work, he said, because the declamatory style was framed in imitation of the eastern authors. Through this work I obtained a cursory knowledge of history, and a view of the several empires at present existing in the world; it gave me an insight into the manners, governments, and religions of the different nations of the earth. I heard of the slothful Asiatics; of the stupendous genius and mental activity of the Grecians; of the wars and wonderful virtue of the early <seg th:eID="C19_app52-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app53-f1823"/>Romans—of <seg th:eID="C19_app53-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app54-f1823"/>
               <pb n="10" xml:id="F1823_v2_283"/>their <seg th:eID="C19_app54-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app55-f1823"/>subsequent <seg th:eID="C19_app55-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app56-f1823"/>degenerating—of <seg th:eID="C19_app56-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app57-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>the decline of that mighty empire; of chivalry, Christianity, and kings. I heard of the discovery of the American hemisphere, and wept with Safie over the hapless fate of its original inhabitants.<seg th:eID="C19_app57-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p15">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app57-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“These wonderful narrations inspired me with strange feelings. Was man, indeed, at once so powerful, so virtuous, and magnificent, yet so vicious and base? He appeared at one time a mere scion of the evil principle, and at <seg th:eID="C19_app57-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app58-f1823"/>another <seg th:eID="C19_app58-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app59-f1823"/>as all that can be conceived of noble and godlike. To be a great and virtuous man appeared the highest honour that can befall a sensitive being; to be base and vicious, as many on record have been, appeared the lowest degradation, a condition more abject than that of the blind mole or harmless worm. For a long time I could not conceive how one man could go <seg th:eID="C19_app59-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app60-f1823"/>forth <seg th:eID="C19_app60-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app61-f1823"/>to murder his fellow, <seg th:eID="C19_app61-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app62-f1823"/>
               <pb n="11" xml:id="F1823_v2_284"/>or <seg th:eID="C19_app62-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app63-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>even why there were laws and governments; but when I heard details of vice and bloodshed, my wonder ceased, and I turned away with disgust and loathing.<seg th:eID="C19_app63-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p16">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app63-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“Every conversation of the cottagers now opened new <seg th:eID="C19_app63-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app64-f1823"/>wonders <seg th:eID="C19_app64-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app65-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>to me. While I listened to the instructions which Felix bestowed upon the Arabian, the strange system of human society was explained to me. I heard of the division of property, of immense wealth and squalid poverty; of rank, descent, and noble blood.<seg th:eID="C19_app65-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p17">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app65-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“The words induced me to turn towards myself. I learned that the possessions most esteemed by your fellow-creatures were, high and unsullied descent united with riches. A man might be respected with only one of these <seg th:eID="C19_app65-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app66-f1823"/>advantages; <seg th:eID="C19_app66-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app67-f1823"/>but <seg th:eID="C19_app67-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app68-f1823"/>without <seg th:eID="C19_app68-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app69-f1823"/>either <seg th:eID="C19_app69-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app70-f1823"/>he was considered, except in very rare instances, <seg th:eID="C19_app70-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app71-f1823"/>
               <pb n="12" xml:id="F1823_v2_285"/>as <seg th:eID="C19_app71-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app72-f1823"/>a vagabond and a slave, doomed to waste his powers for the <seg th:eID="C19_app72-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app73-f1823"/>profit <seg th:eID="C19_app73-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app74-f1823"/>of the chosen <seg th:eID="C19_app74-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app75-f1823"/>few? <seg th:eID="C19_app75-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app76-f1823"/>And what was I? Of my creation and creator I was absolutely ignorant; but I knew that I possessed no money, no friends, no kind of property. I was, besides, <seg th:eID="C19_app76-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app77-f1823"/>endued <seg th:eID="C19_app77-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app78-f1823"/>with a figure hideously deformed and loathsome; I was not even of the same nature as man. I was more agile than they, and could subsist upon coarser diet; I bore the extremes of heat and cold with less injury to my frame; my stature far exceeded <seg th:eID="C19_app78-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app79-f1823"/>theirs. <seg th:eID="C19_app79-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app80-f1823"/>When I looked around, I saw and heard of none like me. Was I then a monster, a blot upon the earth, from which all men fled, and whom all men <seg th:eID="C19_app80-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app81-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>disowned?<seg th:eID="C19_app81-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p18">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app81-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“I <seg th:eID="C19_app81-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app82-f1823"/>cannot describe to you the agony that these reflections inflicted upon <seg th:eID="C19_app82-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app83-f1823"/>me; <seg th:eID="C19_app83-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app84-f1823"/>I tried to dispel them, but sorrow only increased with knowledge. Oh, that <seg th:eID="C19_app84-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app85-f1823"/>
               <pb n="13" xml:id="F1823_v2_286"/>I <seg th:eID="C19_app85-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app86-f1823"/>had for ever remained in my native wood, nor known <seg th:eID="C19_app86-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app87-f1823"/>nor <seg th:eID="C19_app87-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app88-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>felt beyond the sensations of hunger, thirst, and heat!<seg th:eID="C19_app88-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p19">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app88-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“Of what a strange nature is knowledge! It clings to the mind, when it has once seized on it, like a lichen on the rock. I wished sometimes to shake off all thought and feeling; but I learned that there was but one means to overcome the sensation of pain, and that was death—a state which I feared yet did not understand. I admired virtue and good feelings, and loved the gentle manners and amiable qualities of my cottagers; but I was shut out from intercourse with them, except through means which I obtained by stealth, when I was unseen and unknown, and which rather increased than satisfied the desire I had of becoming one among my fellows. The gentle words of <seg th:eID="C19_app88-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app89-f1823"/>Agatha, <seg th:eID="C19_app89-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app90-f1823"/>and <seg th:eID="C19_app90-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app91-f1823"/>
               <pb n="14" xml:id="F1823_v2_287"/>the <seg th:eID="C19_app91-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app92-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>animated smiles of the charming Arabian, were not for me. The mild exhortations of the old man, and the lively conversation of the loved Felix, were not for me. Miserable, unhappy wretch!<seg th:eID="C19_app92-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p20">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app92-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“Other lessons were impressed upon me even more deeply. I heard of the difference of sexes; <seg th:eID="C19_app92-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app93-f1823"/>of <seg th:eID="C19_app93-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app94-f1823"/>the birth and growth of children; how the father doated on the smiles of the infant, and the lively sallies of the older child; how all the life and cares of the mother were <seg th:eID="C19_app94-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app95-f1823"/>wrapped <seg th:eID="C19_app95-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app96-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>up in the precious charge; how the mind of youth expanded and gained knowledge; of brother, sister, and all the various relationships which bind one human being to another in mutual bonds.<seg th:eID="C19_app96-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p21">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app96-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“But where were my friends and relations? No father had watched my infant days, no mother had blessed me <seg th:eID="C19_app96-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app97-f1823"/>
               <pb n="15" xml:id="F1823_v2_288"/>with <seg th:eID="C19_app97-f1823"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app98-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>smiles and caresses; or if they had, all my past life was now a blot, a blind vacancy in which I distinguished nothing. From my earliest remembrance I had been as I then was in height and proportion. I had never yet seen a being resembling me, or who claimed any intercourse with me. What was I? The question again recurred, to be answered only with groans.<seg th:eID="C19_app98-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter12_div4_div13_p22">
               <seg th:sID="C19_app98-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>“I will soon explain to what these feelings tended; but allow me now to return to the cottagers, whose story excited in me such various feelings of indignation, delight, and wonder, but which all terminated in additional love and reverence for my protectors (for so I loved, in an innocent, half painful self-deceit, to call <seg th:eID="C19_app98-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
               <seg th:sID="C19_app99-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>them).<seg th:eID="C19_app99-f1823__Pt1" part="I"/>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" xml:id="F1823_v2_289"/>
            <milestone n="12" type="end" unit="chapter"/> 
            <seg th:eID="C19_app99-f1823__Pt2" part="F"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
