<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C15"/>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="8"/>
   <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
   <p>N<hi rend="smallcaps">OTHING</hi> is more painful to the human mind, than, after the
            feelings have been worked up by a quick succession of events, the dead calmness of
            inaction and certainty which follows, and deprives the soul both of hope and fear.
            Justine died; she rested; and I was alive. The blood flowed freely in my veins, but a
            weight of despair and remorse pressed on my heart, which <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_006" n="002"/>nothing could remove. Sleep fled from my eyes; I wandered like an evil
            spirit, for I had committed deeds of mischief beyond description horrible, and more,
            much more, (I persuaded myself) was yet behind. Yet my heart overflowed with kindness,
            and the love of virtue. I had begun life with benevolent intentions, and thirsted for
            the moment when I should put them in practice, and make myself useful to my
            fellow-beings. Now all was blasted: instead of that serenity of conscience, which
            allowed me to look back upon the past with self-satisfaction, and from thence to gather
            promise of new hopes, I was seized by remorse and the sense of guilt, which hurried me
            away to a hell of intense tortures, such as no language can describe.</p>
   <p>This state of mind preyed upon my health, which had entirely recovered <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_007" n="003"/>from the first shock it had sustained. I shunned the
            face of man; all sound of joy or complacency was torture to me; solitude was my only
            consolation—deep, dark, death-like solitude.</p>
   <p>My father observed with pain the alteration perceptible in my disposition and habits,
            <del rend="strikethrough">and endeavoured to reason with me on the folly of giving way to immoderate grief.</del><add place="bottom">At first he suspected some latent cause for my affliction, but when I assured him that the late events were the causes of my dejection, he called to his aid philosophy and reason, while he endeavoured to restore me to a calmer state of mind.</add> “Do
            you think, Victor,” said he, “that I do not suffer also? No one could love a child more
            than I loved your brother;” (tears came into his eyes as he spoke); “but is it not a
            duty to the survivors, that we should refrain from augmenting their unhappiness by an
            appearance of immoderate grief? It is also a duty owed to yourself; for excessive sorrow
            prevents improvement or enjoyment, or even the discharge of daily usefulness, without
            which no man is fit for society.”</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_008" n="004"/>This advice, although good, was totally
            inapplicable to my case; I should have been the first to hide my grief, and console my
            friends, if remorse had not mingled its bitterness with my other sensations. Now I could
            only answer my father with a look of despair, and endeavour to hide myself from his
            view.</p>
   <p>About this time we retired to our house at Belrive. This change was particularly
            agreeable to me. The shutting of the gates regularly at ten o’clock, and the
            impossibility of remaining on the lake after that hour, had rendered our residence
            within the walls of Geneva very irksome to me. I was now free. Often, after the rest of
            the family had retired for the night, I took the boat, and passed many hours upon the
            water. Sometimes, with my sails set, I was carried by the wind; and sometimes, after
            rowing into the middle of the lake, I <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_009" n="005"/>left the
            boat to pursue its own course, and gave way to my own miserable reflections. I was often
            tempted, when all was at peace around me, and I the only unquiet thing that wandered
            restless in a scene so beautiful and heavenly, if I except some bat, or the frogs, whose
            harsh and interrupted croaking was heard only when I approached the shore—often, I say,
            I was tempted to plunge into the silent lake, that the waters might close over me and my
            calamities for ever. But I was restrained, when I thought of the heroic and suffering
            Elizabeth, whom I tenderly loved, and whose existence was bound up in mine. I thought
            also of my father, and surviving brother: should I by my base desertion leave them
            exposed and unprotected to the malice of the fiend whom I had let loose among them?</p>
   <p>At these moments I wept bitterly, <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_010" n="006"/>and wished that
            peace would revisit my mind only that I might afford them consolation and happiness. But
            that could not be. Remorse extinguished every hope. I had been the author of unalterable
            evils; and I lived in daily fear, lest the monster whom I had created should perpetrate
            some new wickedness. I had an obscure feeling that all was not over, and that he would
            still commit some signal crime, which by its enormity should almost efface the
            recollection of the past. There was always scope for fear, so long as any thing I loved
            remained behind. My abhorrence of this fiend cannot be conceived. When I thought of him,
            I gnashed my teeth, my eyes became inflamed, and I ardently wished to extinguish that
            life which I had so thoughtlessly bestowed. When I reflected on his crimes and malice,
            my hatred and <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_011" n="007"/>revenge burst all bounds of
            moderation. I would have made a pilgrimage to the highest peak of the Andes, could I,
            when there, have precipitated him to their base. I wished to see him again, that I might
            wreak the utmost extent of anger on his head, and avenge the deaths of William and
            Justine.</p>
   <p>Our house was the house of mourning. My father’s health was deeply shaken by the horror
            of the recent events. Elizabeth was sad and desponding; she no longer took delight in
            her ordinary occupations; all pleasure seemed to her sacrilege toward the dead; eternal
            woe and tears she then thought was the just tribute she should pay to innocence so
            blasted and destroyed. She was no longer that happy creature, who in earlier youth
            wandered with me on the banks of the lake, and talked with ecstacy of our future
            prospects. She <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_012" n="008"/>had become grave, and often
            conversed of the inconstancy of fortune, and the instability of human life.</p>
   <p>“When I reflect, my dear cousin,” said she, “on the miserable death of Justine Moritz,
            I no longer see the world and its works as they before appeared to me. Before, I looked
            upon the accounts of vice and injustice, that I read in books or heard from others, as
            tales of ancient days, or imaginary evils; at least they were remote, and more familiar
            to reason than to the imagination; but now misery has come home, and men appear to me as
            monsters thirsting for each other’s blood. Yet I am certainly unjust. Every body
            believed that poor girl to be guilty; and if she could have committed the crime for
            which she suffered, assuredly she would have been the most depraved of human creatures.
            For the sake of a few jewels, <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_013" n="009"/>to have murdered the
            son of her benefactor and friend, a child whom she had nursed from its birth, and
            appeared to love as if it had been her own! I could not consent to the death of any
            human being; but certainly I should have thought such a creature unfit to remain in the
            society of men. Yet she was innocent. I know, I feel she was innocent; you are of the
            same opinion, and that confirms me. Alas! Victor, when falsehood can look so like the
            truth, who can assure themselves of certain happiness? I feel as if I were walking on the
            edge of a precipice, towards which thousands are crowding, and endeavouring to plunge me
            into the abyss. William and Justine were assassinated, and the murderer escapes; he
            walks about the world free, and perhaps respected. But even if I were condemned to
            suffer on the scaffold <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_014" n="010"/>for the same crimes, I
            would not change places with such a wretch.”</p>
   <p>I listened to this discourse with the extremest agony. I, not in deed, but in effect,
            was the true murderer. Elizabeth read my anguish in my countenance, and kindly taking my
            hand said, “My dearest cousin, you must calm yourself. These events have affected me,
            God knows how deeply; but I am not so wretched as you are. There is an expression of
            despair, and sometimes of revenge, in your countenance, that makes me tremble. Be calm,
            my dear Victor; I would sacrifice my life to your peace. We surely shall be happy: quiet
            in our native country, and not mingling in the world, what can disturb our
            tranquillity?”</p>
   <p>She shed tears as she said this, distrusting the very solace that she gave; but at the
            same time she smiled, that <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_015" n="011"/>she might chase away
            the fiend that lurked in my heart. My father, who saw in the unhappiness that was
            painted in my face only an exaggeration of that sorrow which I might naturally feel,
            thought that an amusement suited to my taste would be the best means of restoring to me
            my wonted serenity. It was from this cause that he had removed to the country; and,
            induced by the same motive, he now proposed that we should all make an excursion to the
            valley of Chamounix. I had been there before, but Elizabeth and Ernest never had; and
            both had often expressed an earnest desire to see the scenery of this place, which had
            been described to them as so wonderful and sublime. Accordingly we departed from Geneva
            on this tour about the middle of the month of August, nearly two months after the death
            of Justine.</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_016" n="012"/>The weather was uncommonly fine; and if mine had
            been a sorrow to be chased away by any fleeting circumstance, this excursion would
            certainly have had the effect intended by my father. As it was, I was somewhat
            interested in the scene; it sometimes lulled, although it could not extinguish my grief.
            During the first day we travelled in a carriage. In the morning we had seen the
            mountains at a distance, towards which we gradually advanced. We perceived that the
            valley through which we wound, and which was formed by the river Arve, whose course we
            followed, closed in upon us by degrees; and when the sun had set, we beheld immense
            mountains and precipices overhanging us on every side, and heard the sound of the river
            raging among rocks, and the dashing of water-falls around.</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_017" n="013"/>The next day we pursued our journey upon mules;
            and as we ascended still higher, the valley assumed a more magnificent and astonishing
            character. Ruined castles hanging on the precipices of piny mountains; the impetuous
            Arve, and cottages every here and there peeping forth from among the trees, formed a
            scene of singular beauty. But it was augmented and rendered sublime by the mighty Alps,
            whose white and shining pyramids and domes towered above all, as belonging to another
            earth, the habitations of another race of beings.</p>
   <p>We passed the bridge of Pelissier, where the ravine, which the river forms, opened
            before us, and we began to ascend the mountain that overhangs it. Soon after we entered
            the valley of Chamounix. This valley is more wonderful and sublime, but not so beautiful
              <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_018" n="014"/>and picturesque as that of Servox, through which
            we had just passed. The high and snowy mountains were its immediate boundaries; but we
            saw no more ruined castles and fertile fields. Immense glaciers approached the road; we
            heard the rumbling thunder of the falling avelânche, and marked the smoke of its
            passage. Mont Blanc, the supreme and magnificent Mont Blanc, raised itself from the
            surrounding <hi rend="italic">aiguilles</hi>, and its tremendous <hi rend="italic">dome</hi> overlooked the valley.</p>
   <p>During this journey, I sometimes joined Elizabeth, and exerted myself to point out to
            her the various beauties of the scene. I often suffered my mule to lag behind, and
            indulged in the misery of reflection. At other times I spurred on the animal before my
            companions, that I might forget them, the world, and, more than all, myself. When at <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_019" n="015"/>a distance, I alighted, and threw myself on the
            grass, weighed down by horror and despair. At eight in the evening I arrived at
            Chamounix. My father and Elizabeth were very much fatigued; Ernest, who accompanied us,
            was delighted, and in high spirits: the only circumstance that detracted from his
            pleasure was the south wind, and the rain it seemed to promise for the next day.</p>
   <p>We retired early to our apartments, but not to sleep; at least I did not. I remained
            many hours at the window, watching the pallid lightning that played above Mont Blanc,
            and listening to the rushing of the Arve, which ran below my window.</p>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="8"/>
</xml>
