<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml><anchor type="collate" xml:id="C12a"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p15"/>“Dear, dear Elizabeth!” I exclaimed when I had read her letter, “I will write
    instantly, and relieve them from the anxiety they must feel.” I wrote, and this exertion
    greatly fatigued me; but my convalescence had commenced, and proceeded regularly. In
    another fortnight I was able to leave my chamber.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p15"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p16"/>One of my first duties on my recovery was to introduce Clerval to the several
    professors of the university. In doing this, I underwent a kind of rough usage, ill
    befitting the wounds that my mind had sustained. Ever since the <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_137" n="125"/>fatal night, the end of my labours, and the
    beginning of my misfortunes, I had conceived a violent antipathy even to the name of
    natural philosophy. When I was otherwise quite restored to health, the sight of a
    chemical instrument would renew all the agony of my nervous symptoms. Henry saw this,
    and had removed all my apparatus from my view. He had also changed my apartment; for he
    perceived that I had acquired a dislike for the room which had previously been my
    laboratory. But these cares of Clerval were made of no avail when I visited the
    professors. M. Waldman inflicted torture when he praised, with kindness and warmth, the
    astonishing progress I had made in the sciences. He soon perceived that I disliked the
    subject; but, not guessing the real cause, he attributed my feelings to modesty, and <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_138" n="126"/>changed the subject from my improvement to the
    science itself, with a desire, as I evidently saw, of drawing me out. What could I do?
    He meant to please, and he tormented me. I felt as if he had placed carefully, one by
    one, in my view those instruments which were to be afterwards used in putting me to a
    slow and cruel death. I writhed under his words, yet dared not exhibit the pain I felt.
    Clerval, whose eyes and feelings were always quick in discerning the sensations of
    others, declined the subject, alleging, in excuse, his total ignorance; and the
    conversation took a more general turn. I thanked my friend from my heart, but I did not
    speak. I saw plainly that he was surprised, but he never attempted to draw my secret
    from me; and although I loved him with a mixture of affection and reverence that knew no
    <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_139" n="127"/>bounds, yet I could never persuade myself to
    confide to him that event which was so often present to my recollection, but which I
    feared the detail to another would only impress more deeply.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p16"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p17"/>M. Krempe was not equally docile; and in my condition at that time, of almost
    insupportable sensitiveness, his harsh blunt encomiums gave me even more pain than the
    benevolent approbation of M. Waldman. “D—n the fellow!” cried he; “why, M. Clerval, I
    assure you he has outstript us all. Aye, stare if you please; but it is nevertheless
    true. A youngster who, but a few years ago, believed Cornelius Agrippa as firmly as the
    gospel, has now set himself at the head of the university; and if he is not soon pulled
    down, we shall all be out of countenance.—Aye, aye,” continued he, ob<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_140" n="128"/>serving my face expressive of suffering, “M.
    Frankenstein is modest; an excellent quality in a young man. Young men should be
    diffident of themselves, you know, M. Clerval; I was myself when young: but that wears
    out in a very short time.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p17"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p18"/>M. Krempe had now commenced an eulogy on himself, which happily turned the conversation
    from a subject that was so annoying to me.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p18"/></xml>
