<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C12f"/>Their melancholy is
            soothing, and their joy elevating to a degree I never experienced in studying the
            authors of any other country. When you read their writings, life appears to consist in a
            warm sun and garden of roses,—in the smiles and frowns of a fair enemy, and the fire
            that consumes your own heart. How different from the manly and heroical poetry of Greece
            and Rome.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p19"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p20"/>Summer passed away in these occupations, and my return to Geneva was fixed for the
            latter end of autumn; but being delayed by several accidents, winter and snow arrived,
            the roads were deemed impassable, and my journey was retarded until the ensuing spring. <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_142" n="130"/>I felt this delay very bitterly; for I longed to
            see my native town, and my beloved friends. My return had only been delayed so long from
            an unwillingness to leave Clerval in a strange place, before he had become acquainted
            with any of its inhabitants. The winter, however, was spent cheerfully; and although the
            spring was uncommonly late, when it came, its beauty compensated for its
            dilatoriness.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p20"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p21"/>The month of May had already commenced, and I expected the letter daily which was to
            fix the date of my departure, when Henry proposed a pedestrian tour in the environs of
            Ingolstadt that I might bid a personal farewell to the country I had so long inhabited.
            I acceded with pleasure to this proposition: I was fond of exercise, and Clerval had
            always been my favourite companion in the rambles of this nature that I had <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_143" n="131"/>taken among the scenes of my native country.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p21"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p22"/>We passed a fortnight in these perambulations: my health and spirits had long been
            restored, and they gained additional strength from the salubrious air I breathed, the
            natural incidents of our progress, and the conversation of my friend. Study had before
            secluded me from the intercourse of my fellow-creatures, and rendered me unsocial; but
            Clerval called forth the better feelings of my heart; he again taught me to love the
            aspect of nature, and the cheerful faces of children. Excellent friend! how sincerely
            did you love me, and endeavour to elevate my mind, until it was on a level with your
            own. A selfish pursuit had cramped and narrowed me, until your gentleness and affection
            warmed and opened my senses; I became the same happy creature who, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_144" n="132"/>a few years ago, loving and beloved by all, had no
            sorrow or care. When happy, inanimate nature had the power of bestowing on me the most
            delightful sensations. A serene sky and verdant fields filled me with ecstasy. The
            present season was indeed divine; the flowers of spring bloomed in the hedges, while
            those of summer were already in bud: I was undisturbed by thoughts which during the
            preceding year had pressed upon me, notwithstanding my endeavours to throw them off,
            with an invincible burden.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p22"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p23"/>Henry rejoiced in my gaiety, and sincerely sympathized in my feelings: he exerted
            himself to amuse me, while he expressed the sensations that filled his soul. The
            resources of his mind on this occasion were truly astonishing: his conversation was full
            of imagination; and very often, in imitation <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_145" n="133"/>of
            the Persian and Arabic writers, he invented tales of wonderful fancy and passion. At
            other times he repeated my favourite poems, or drew me out into arguments, which he
            supported with great ingenuity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p23"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p24"/>We returned to our college on a Sunday afternoon: the peasants were dancing, and every
            one we met appeared gay and happy. My own spirits were high, and I bounded along with
            feelings of unbridled joy and hilarity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p24"/>
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_146" n="134"/>
        <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="5"/>
        </xml>
