<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C11o"/>was a great favourite of yours; and
            I recollect you once remarked, that if you were in an ill humour, one glance from
            Justine could dissipate it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning the beauty
            of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great attachment
            for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that which she
            had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most grateful
            little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions, I never heard
            one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her protectress.
            Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet she paid the
              <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_139" n="120"/>greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She
            thought her the model of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and
            manners, so that even now she often reminds me of her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p7"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/>“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to
            notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious
            affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p8"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/>“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her
            neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she
            began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise
            her partiality. She was a Roman Catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_140" n="121"/>the idea which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few
            months after your departure for Ingolstadt, Justine was called home by her repentant
            mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted our house; she was much altered since the
            death of my aunt; grief had given softness and a winning mildness to her manners, which
            had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor was her residence at her mother’s house of
            a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor woman was very vacillating in her repentance.
            She sometimes begged Justine to forgive her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of
            having caused the deaths of her brothers and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw
            Madame Moritz into a decline, which at first increased her irritability, but she is now
            at peace for ever. She died on the first approach of cold weather, at <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_141" n="122"/>the beginning of this last winter. Justine has returned
            to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very clever and gentle, and
            extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her expressions continually remind
            me of my dear aunt.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p9"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/>“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish
            you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark
            eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek,
            which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10_hi1"/>wives<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10_hi1"/>, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of
            age.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p10"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/>“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the
            good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_142" n="123"/>received the congratulatory visits on her approaching marriage with a young
            Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich
            banker, last autumn. Your favourite schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several
            misfortunes since the departure of Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his
            spirits, and is reported to be on the point of marrying a very lively pretty
            Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is
            very much admired, and a favourite with every body.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p11"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/>“I have written myself into good spirits, dear cousin; yet I cannot conclude without
            again anxiously inquiring concerning your health. Dear Victor, if you are not very ill,
            write yourself, and make your father and all <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_143" n="124"/>of us
            happy; or——I cannot bear to think of the other side of the question; my tears already
            flow. Adieu, my dearest cousin.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p12"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/>“E<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi1"/>LIZABETH<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi1"/> L<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi2"/>AVENZA<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13_hi2"/>.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p13"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p14"/>
      <comment text=" RM: location and date are 2 points smaller than body text "/> “Geneva,
            March 18th, 17—.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p14"/>
          </xml>
