<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C11o"/>was a great favourite of yours; and I recollect you once
            remarked, that if you were in an ill-humour, one glance from Justine could dissipate<pb xml:id="F1831_v_067" n="51"/> it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning
            the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great
            attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that
            which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most
            grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions; I
            never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her
            protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet
            she paid the greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model
            of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even
            now she often reminds me of her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p6"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7"/>“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to
            notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious
            affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8"/>“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her
            neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she
            began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise
            her partiality. She was a Roman catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed the idea
            which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt,
            Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted
            our house; she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and
            a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor
            was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor
            woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive
            her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers
            and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at
            first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace forever. She died on the first
            approach of cold weather, at the beginning of this<pb xml:id="F1831_v_068" n="52"/> last
            winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very
            clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her
            expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9"/>“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish
            you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark
            eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek,
            which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1"/>wives<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1"/>, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of
            age.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10"/>“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the
            good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already received the congratulatory
            visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her
            ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite
            schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of
            Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on
            the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a
            widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with
            everybody.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11"/>“I have written myself into better spirits, dear cousin; but my anxiety returns upon me
            as I conclude. Write, dearest Victor,—one line—one word will be a blessing to us. Ten
            thousand thanks to Henry for his kindness, his affection, and his many letters: we are
            sincerely grateful. Adieu! my cousin; take care of yourself; and, I entreat you,
            write!<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12"/>“E<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1"/>LIZABETH<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1"/> L<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2"/>AVENZA<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2"/>.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13"/>“Geneva, March 18th, 17—.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13"/>
      </xml>
