<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C13h"/>“requires consolation; she accused herself of having
    caused the death of my brother, and that made her very wretched. But since the murderer
    has been discovered—”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p36"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p37"/>“The murderer discovered! Good God! how can that be? who could attempt to pursue him?
    It is impossible; one might as well try to overtake the winds, or confine a
    mountain-stream with a straw. I saw him too; he was free last night!”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p37"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p38"/>“I do not know what you mean,” replied my brother, in accents of wonder, “but to us the
    discovery we have made completes our misery. No one would believe it at first; and even
    now Elizabeth will not be convinced, notwithstanding all the evidence. Indeed, who would
    credit that Justine Moritz, who was so amiable, and fond of all <pb xml:id="F1831_v_080" n="64"/>the family, could suddenly become capable of so frightful, so appalling a
    crime?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p38"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p39"/>“Justine Moritz! Poor, poor girl, is she the accused? But it is wrongfully; every one
    knows that; no one believes it, surely, Ernest?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p39"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p40"/>“No one did at first; but several circumstances came out, that have almost forced
    conviction upon us; and her own behaviour has been so confused, as to add to the
    evidence of facts a weight that, I fear, leaves no hope for doubt. But she will be tried
    to-day, and you will then hear all.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p40"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p41"/>He related that, the morning on which the murder of poor William had been discovered,
    Justine had been taken ill, and confined to her bed for several days. During this
    interval, one of the servants, happening to examine the apparel she had worn on the
    night of the murder, had discovered in her pocket the picture of my mother, which had
    been judged to be the temptation of the murderer. The servant instantly showed it to one
    of the others, who, without saying a word to any of the family, went to a magistrate;
    and, upon their deposition, Justine was apprehended. On being charged with the fact, the
    poor girl confirmed the suspicion in a great measure by her extreme confusion of
    manner.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p41"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p42"/>This was a strange tale, but it did not shake my faith; and I replied earnestly, “You
    are all mistaken; I know the murderer. Justine, poor, good Justine, is innocent.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p42"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p43"/>At that instant my father entered. I saw unhappiness deeply impressed on his
    countenance, but he endeavoured to welcome me cheerfully; and, after we had exchanged
    our mournful greeting, would have introduced some other topic than that of our disaster,
    had not Ernest exclaimed, “Good God, papa! Victor says that he knows who was the
    murderer of poor William.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p43"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p44"/>“We do also, unfortunately,” replied my father; “for indeed I had rather have been for
    ever ignorant than have discovered so much depravity and ingratitude in one I valued so
    highly.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p44"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p45"/>“My dear father, you are mistaken; Justine is innocent.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p45"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p46"/>“If she is, God forbid that she should suffer as guilty. <pb xml:id="F1831_v_081" n="65"/>She is to be tried to-day, and I hope, I sincerely hope, that she will be
    acquitted.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p46"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter7_div4_div7_p47"/>This speech calmed me. I was firmly convinced in my own mind that Justine, and indeed
    every human being, was guiltless of this murder. I had no fear, therefore, that any
    circumstantial evidence could be brought forward strong enough to convict her.</xml>
