<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C13c"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p21"/>Clerval spoke thus as we hurried through the streets; the words impressed themselves on
    my mind, and I remembered them afterwards in solitude. But now, as soon as the horses
    arrived, I hurried into a cabriole, and bade farewell to my friend.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p21"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p22"/>My journey was very melancholy. At first I wished to hurry on, for I longed to console
    and sympathize with <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_154" n="142"/>my loved and sorrowing
    friends; but when I drew near my native town, I slackened my progress. I could hardly
    sustain the multitude of feelings that crowded into my mind. I passed through scenes
    familiar to my youth, but which I had not seen for nearly six years. How altered every
    thing might be during that time? One sudden and desolating change had taken place; but a
    thousand little circumstances might have by degrees worked other alterations, which,
    although they were done more tranquilly, might not be the less decisive. Fear overcame
    me; I dared not advance, dreading a thousand nameless evils that made me tremble,
    although I was unable to define them.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p22"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p23"/>I remained two days at Lausanne, in this painful state of mind. I contemplated the
    lake: the waters were placid; all around was calm, and the snowy <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_155" n="143"/>mountains, “the palaces of nature,” were not
    changed. By degrees the calm and heavenly scene restored me, and I continued my journey
    towards Geneva.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p23"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p24"/>The road ran by the side of the lake, which became narrower as I approached my native
    town. I discovered more distinctly the black sides of Jura, and the bright summit of
    Mont Blanc; I wept like a child: “Dear mountains! my own beautiful lake! how do you
    welcome your wanderer? Your summits are clear; the sky and lake are blue and placid. Is
    this to prognosticate peace, or to mock at my unhappiness?”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p24"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p25"/>I fear, my friend, that I shall render myself tedious by dwelling on these preliminary
    circumstances; but they were days of comparative happiness, and I think of them with
    pleasure. My <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_156" n="144"/>country, my beloved country! who but
    a native can tell the delight I took in again beholding thy streams, thy mountains, and,
    more than all, thy lovely lake.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p25"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p26"/>Yet, as I drew nearer home, grief and fear again overcame me. Night also closed around;
    and when I could hardly see the dark mountains, I felt still more gloomily. The picture
    appeared a vast and dim scene of evil, and I foresaw obscurely that I was destined to
    become the most wretched of human beings. Alas! I prophesied truly, and failed only in
    one single circumstance, that in all the misery I imagined and dreaded, I did not
    conceive the hundredth part of the anguish I was destined to endure.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p26"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27"/>It was completely dark when I arrived in the environs of Geneva; the gates of the town
    were already shut; and I was obliged to pass the night at <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_157" n="145"/>Secheron, a village half a league to the east of the city. The sky <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add1"/>above <add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add1"/>was serene; <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_del1"/>and,<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_del1"/> as I was unable to rest, I resolved to visit the spot where my poor William
    had been murdered. As I could not pass through the town, I was obliged to cross the lake
    in a boat to arrive at Plainpalais. During this short voyage I saw the lightnings
    playing on the summit of Mont Blanc in the most beautiful figures. The storm appeared to
    approach rapidly; and, on landing, I ascended a low hill, that I might observe its
    progress. It advanced; the heavens were clouded, and I soon felt the rain coming slowly
    in large drops, but its violence quickly increased. <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2"/>
    <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2_del1"/>but<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2_del1"/>
    <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2_add1"/>And<add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2_add1"/> the clouds were gathering on the <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2_del2"/>ris<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2_del2"/> horison, mass rising above mass, while the lightning they emitted shewed their shapes and size.<add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27_add2"/>
    <p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p27"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p28"/>I quitted my seat, and walked on, although the darkness and storm increased every
    minute, and the thunder burst with a terrific crash over my head. It was echoed from
    Salêve, the <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_158" n="146"/>Juras, and the Alps of Savoy; vivid
    flashes of lightning dazzled my eyes, illuminating the lake, making it appear like a
    vast sheet of fire; then for an instant every thing seemed of a pitchy darkness, until
    the eye recovered itself from the preceding flash. The storm, as is often the case in
    Switzerland, appeared at once in various parts of the heavens. The most violent storm
    hung exactly north of the town, over that part of the lake which lies between the
    promontory of Belrive and the village of Copêt. Another storm enlightened Jura with
    faint flashes; and another darkened and sometimes disclosed the Môle, a peaked mountain
    to the east of the lake.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p28"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p29"/>While I watched the storm, so beautiful yet terrific, I wandered on with a hasty step.
    This noble war in the sky elevated my spirits; I clasped my hands, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_159" n="147"/>and exclaimed aloud, “William, dear angel! this is
    thy funeral, this thy dirge!” As I said these words, I perceived in the gloom a figure
    which stole from behind a clump of trees near me; I stood fixed, gazing intently: I
    could not be mistaken. A flash of lightning illuminated the object, and discovered its
    shape plainly to me; its gigantic stature, and the deformity of its aspect, more hideous
    than belongs to humanity, instantly informed me that it was the wretch, the filthy
    dæmon to whom I had given life. What did he there? Could he be (I shuddered at the
    conception) the murderer of my brother? No sooner did that idea cross my imagination,
    than I became convinced of its truth; my teeth chattered, and I was forced to lean
    against a tree for support. The figure passed me quickly, and I lost <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_160" n="148"/>it in the gloom. Nothing in human shape could have
    destroyed that fair child. <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p29_hi1"/>He<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p29_hi1"/> was the murderer! I could not doubt
    it. The mere presence of the idea was an irresistible proof of the fact. I thought of
    pursuing the devil; but it would have been in vain, for another flash discovered him to
    me hanging among the rocks of the nearly perpendicular ascent of Mont Salêve, a hill
    that bounds Plainpalais on the south. He soon reached the summit, and disappeared.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p29"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p30"/>I remained motionless. The thunder ceased; but the rain still continued, and the scene
    was enveloped in an impenetrable darkness. I revolved in my mind the events which I had
    until now sought to forget: the whole train of my progress towards the creation; the
    appearance of the work of my own hands alive at my bed side; its depar<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_161" n="149"/>ture. Two years had now nearly elapsed since the
    night on which he first received life; and was this his first crime? Alas! I had turned
    loose into the world a depraved wretch, whose delight was in carnage and misery; had he
    not murdered my brother?<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p30"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p31"/>No one can conceive the anguish I suffered during the remainder of the night, which I
    spent, cold and wet, in the open air. But I did not feel the inconvenience of the
    weather; my imagination was busy in scenes of evil and despair. I considered the being
    whom I had cast among mankind, and endowed with the will and power to effect purposes of
    horror, such as the deed which he had now done, nearly in the light of my own vampire,
    my own spirit let loose from the grave, and forced to destroy all that was dear to
    me.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p31"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p32"/>Day dawned; and I directed my steps <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_162" n="150"/>towards the
    town. The gates were open; and I hastened to my father’s house. My first thought was to
    discover what I knew of the murderer, and cause instant pursuit to be made. But I paused
    when I reflected on the story that I had to tell. A being whom I myself had formed, and
    endued with life, had met me at midnight among the precipices of an inaccessible
    mountain. I remembered also the nervous fever with which I had been seized just at the
    time that I dated my creation, and which would give an air of delirium to a tale
    otherwise so utterly improbable. I well knew that if any other had communicated such a
    relation to me, I should have looked upon it as the ravings of insanity. Besides, the
    strange nature of the animal would elude all pursuit, even if I were so far credited as
    to persuade my relatives to commence it. <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_163" n="151"/>
    <del sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p32_del1"/>Besides<del eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p32_del1"/>
    <add sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p32_add1"/>And<add eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p32_add1"/>,
    of what use would be pursuit? Who could arrest a creature capable of scaling the
    overhanging sides of Mont Salêve? These reflections determined me, and I resolved to
    remain silent.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p32"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p33"/>It was about five in the morning when I entered my father’s house. I told the servants
    not to disturb the family, and went into the library to attend their usual hour of
    rising.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p33"/>
    <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p34"/>Six years had elapsed, passed as a dream but for one indelible trace, and I stood in
    the same place where I had last embraced my father before my departure for Ingolstadt.
    Beloved and respectable parent! He still remained to me. I gazed on the picture of my
    mother, which stood over the mantlepiece. It was an historical subject, painted at my
    father’s desire, and represented Caroline Beaufort in an ago<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_164" n="152"/>ny of despair, kneeling by the coffin of her dead father. Her garb was
    rustic, and her cheek pale; but there was an air of dignity and beauty, that hardly
    permitted the sentiment of pity. Below this picture was a miniature of William; and my
    tears flowed when I looked upon it. While I was thus engaged, Ernest entered: he had
    heard me arrive, and hastened to welcome me. He expressed a sorrowful delight to see me:
    “Welcome, my dearest Victor,” said he. “Ah! I wish you had come three months ago, and
    then you would have found us all joyous and delighted.</xml>
