<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1831v2.ch11</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1252</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 11</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>
                        <name>Henry Colburn</name> and <name>Richard Bentley</name>
                     </publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1831</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">Rev., Corr. [2nd ed.]</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="ser">Bentley's Standard Novels series</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="no">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1831 EDITION : VOL. II</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 11</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>"IT is with
              considerable difficulty that I remember the original
              era of my being: all the events of that period
              appear confused and indistinct. A strange multiplicity
              of sensations seized me, and I saw, felt, heard,
              and smelt, at the same time; and it was, indeed, a
              long time before I learned to distinguish between the
              operations of my various senses. By degrees, I
              remember, a stronger light pressed upon my nerves, so
              that I was obliged to shut my eyes. Darkness then
              came over me, and troubled me; but hardly had I felt
              this, when, by opening my eyes, as I now suppose, the
              light poured in upon me again. I walked, and,
              
              I believe, descended; but I presently found a
              great alteration in my sensations. Before, dark and
              opaque bodies had surrounded me, impervious to my
              touch or sight; but I
              now found that I could wander on at liberty, with
              no obstacles which I could not either surmount or
              avoid. The light became more and more oppressive to
              me; and, the heat wearying me as I walked, I sought a
              place where I could receive shade. This was the
              forest near Ingolstadt; and here I lay by the side of
              a brook resting from my fatigue, until I felt
              tormented by hunger and thirst. This roused me from
              my nearly dormant state, and I ate some berries which
              I found hanging on the trees, or lying on the ground.
              I slaked my thirst at the brook; and then lying down,
              was overcome by sleep.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It was dark when I awoke; I
              felt cold also, and half-frightened, as it were
              instinctively,
              finding myself so desolate. Before I had quitted
              your apartment, on a sensation of cold, I had covered
              myself with some clothes; but these were insufficient
              to secure me from the dews of night. I was a poor,
              helpless, miserable
              wretch; I knew, and could distinguish, nothing;
              but feeling pain invade me on all sides, I
              sat down and wept.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Soon a
              gentle light stole over the heavens, and gave me
              a sensation of pleasure. I started up, and beheld a
              radiant form rise from among the trees. I gazed with
              a kind of wonder. It moved slowly, but it enlightened
              my path; and I again went out in search of berries. I
              was still cold, when under one of the trees I found a
              huge cloak, with which I covered myself, and sat down
              upon the ground. No distinct ideas occupied my mind;
              all was confused. I felt light, and hunger, and
              thirst, and darkness; innumerable sounds rung in my
              ears, and on all sides various scents saluted me: the
              only object that I could distinguish was the bright
              moon, and I fixed my eyes on that with pleasure.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Several changes of day and night passed, and the
              orb of night had greatly lessened, when I began to
              distinguish my sensations from each other. I
              gradually saw plainly the clear stream that supplied
              me with drink, and the trees that shaded me with
              their foliage. I was delighted when I first
              discovered that a pleasant sound, which often saluted
              my ears, proceeded from the throats of the little
              winged animals who had often intercepted the light
              from my eyes. I began also to observe, with greater
              accuracy, the forms that surrounded me, and to
              perceive the boundaries of the radiant roof of light
              which canopied me. Sometimes I tried to imitate the
              pleasant songs of the birds, but was unable.
              Sometimes I wished to express my sensations in my own
              mode, but the uncouth
              and inarticulate sounds which broke from me
              frightened me into silence again.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The moon had disappeared from the night, and
              again,
              with a lessened form, showed itself, while I
              still remained in the forest. My sensations had, by
              this time, become distinct, and my mind received
              every day additional ideas. My eyes became accustomed
              to the light, and to perceive objects in their right
              forms; I distinguished the insect from the herb, and,
              by degrees, one herb from another. I found that the
              sparrow uttered none but harsh notes, whilst those of
              the blackbird and thrush were sweet and enticing.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"One day, when I
              was oppressed by cold, I found a fire which had been
              left by some wandering
              beggars, and was overcome with delight at the
              warmth I experienced from it. In my joy I thrust my
              hand into the live embers, but quickly drew it out
              again with a cry of pain. How strange, I thought,
              that the same cause
              should produce such opposite effects! I examined
              the materials of the fire, and to my joy found it to
              be composed of wood. I quickly collected some
              branches; but they were wet, and would not burn. I
              was pained at this, and sat still watching the
              operation of the fire. The wet wood which I had
              placed near the heat dried, and itself became
              inflamed. I reflected on this; and, by touching the
              various branches, I discovered the cause, and busied
              myself in collecting a great quantity of wood, that I
              might dry it, and have a plentiful supply of fire.
              When night came on, and brought sleep with it, I was
              in the greatest fear lest my fire should be
              extinguished. I covered it carefully with dry wood
              and leaves, and placed wet branches upon it; and
              then, spreading my cloak, I lay on the ground, and
              sunk into sleep.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It was morning when I awoke, and my first care
              was to visit the fire. I uncovered it, and a gentle
              breeze quickly fanned it into a flame. I observed
              this also, and contrived a fan of branches, which
              roused the embers when they were nearly extinguished.
              When night came again, I found, with pleasure, that
              the fire gave light as well as heat; and that the
              discovery of this element was useful to me in my
              food; for I found some of the
              offals that the travellers had left had been
              roasted, and tasted much more savoury than the
              berries I gathered from the trees. I tried,
              therefore, to
              dress my food in the same manner, placing it on
              the live embers. I found that the berries were
              spoiled by this operation, and the nuts and roots
              much improved.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Food, however,
              became scarce; and I often spent the whole day
              searching in vain for a few acorns to assuage the
              pangs of hunger. When I found this, I resolved to
              quit the place that I had hitherto inhabited, to seek
              for one where the few wants I experienced would be
              more easily satisfied. In this emigration, I
              exceedingly lamented the loss of the fire which I had
              obtained through accident, and knew not how to
              reproduce it. I gave several hours to the serious
              consideration of this difficulty; but I was obliged
              to relinquish all attempt to supply it; and, wrapping
              myself up in my cloak, I struck across the wood
              towards
              the setting sun. I passed three days in these
              rambles, and at length discovered the open
              country. A great fall
              of snow had taken place the night before, and the
              fields were of one uniform white; the appearance was
              disconsolate, and I found my feet chilled by the cold
              damp substance that covered the ground.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It was about seven in the morning, and I longed
              to obtain food and shelter; at length I perceived a
              small hut, on a rising ground, which had doubtless
              been built for the convenience of some shepherd. This
              was a new sight to me; and I examined the structure
              with great curiosity. Finding the door open, I
              entered. An old man sat in it, near a fire, over
              which he was preparing his breakfast. He turned on
              hearing a noise; and, perceiving me, shrieked loudly,
              and, quitting the hut, ran across the fields with a
              speed of which his debilitated form hardly appeared
              capable. His appearance,
              different from any I had ever before seen, and
              his flight, somewhat surprised me. But I was
              enchanted by the appearance of the hut: here the snow
              and rain could not penetrate; the ground was dry; and
              it presented to me then as exquisite and divine a
              retreat as
              Pandæmonium appeared to the dæmons of
              hell after their sufferings in the lake of fire.
              I
              greedily devoured the remnants of the shepherd's
              breakfast, which consisted of bread, cheese, milk,
              and wine; the
              latter, however, I did not like. Then, overcome
              by fatigue, I lay down among some straw, and fell
              asleep.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It was noon when I
              awoke; and, allured by the warmth of the sun, which
              shone brightly on the white ground, I determined to
              recommence my travels; and, depositing the remains of
              the peasant's breakfast in a
              wallet I found, I proceeded across the fields for
              several
              hours, until at sunset I arrived at a village.
              How miraculous did this appear! the huts, the neater
              cottages, and stately houses, engaged my admiration
              by turns. The vegetables
              in the gardens, the milk and cheese that I saw
              placed at the windows of some of the cottages,
              allured my appetite. One of the best of these I
              entered; but I had hardly placed my foot within the
              door, before the children shrieked, and one of the
              women fainted. The whole village was roused; some
              fled, some attacked me, until, grievously bruised by
              stones and many other kinds of missile weapons, I
              escaped to the open country, and fearfully took
              refuge in a low hovel, quite bare, and making a
              wretched appearance after the palaces I had beheld in
              the village. This hovel, however, joined a cottage of
              a neat and pleasant appearance; but, after my late
              dearly bought experience, I
              dared not enter it. My place of refuge was
              constructed of wood, but so low, that I could with
              difficulty sit upright in it. No wood, however, was
              placed on the earth, which formed the floor, but it
              was dry; and although the wind entered it by
              innumerable chinks, I found it an agreeable asylum
              from the snow and rain.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Here then I retreated, and lay down happy to have
              found a shelter, however miserable, from the
              inclemency of the season, and still more from
              
              the barbarity of man.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Having thus
              arranged my dwelling, and carpeted it with clean
              straw, I retired; for I saw the figure of a man at a
              distance, and I remembered too well my treatment the
              night before, to trust myself in his power. I had
              first, however, provided for my sustenance for that
              day, by a loaf of coarse bread, which I purloined,
              and a cup with which I could drink, more conveniently
              than from my hand, of the pure water which flowed by
              my retreat. The floor was a little raised, so that it
              was kept perfectly dry, and by its vicinity to the
              chimney of the cottage it was tolerably warm.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Being thus provided, I resolved to reside in this
              hovel, until something should occur which might alter
              my determination. It was indeed a
              paradise, compared to the bleak forest, my former
              residence, the rain-dropping branches, and dank
              earth. I ate my breakfast with pleasure, and was
              about to remove a plank to procure myself a little
              water, when I heard a step, and looking through a
              small chink, I beheld a young creature, with a pail
              on her head, passing before my hovel. The girl was
              young, and of gentle demeanour, unlike
              what I have since found cottagers and farm-house
              servants to be. Yet she was meanly
              dressed, a coarse blue petticoat and a linen
              jacket being her only garb; her fair hair was
              plaited, but not adorned; she looked patient, yet
              sad. I lost sight of her; and in about a quarter of
              an hour she returned, bearing the pail, which was now
              partly filled with milk. As she walked along,
              seemingly incommoded by the burden, a young man met
              her, whose countenance expressed a deeper
              despondence. Uttering a few sounds with an air of
              melancholy, he took the pail from her head, and bore
              it to the cottage himself. She followed, and they
              disappeared. Presently I saw the young man again,
              with some tools in his hand, cross the field behind
              the cottage; and the girl was also busied, sometimes
              in the house, and sometimes in the yard.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"On examining my
              dwelling, I found that one of the windows of the
              cottage had formerly occupied a part of it, but the
              panes had been filled up with wood. In one of these
              was a small and almost imperceptible chink, through
              which the eye could just penetrate. Through this
              crevice a small room was visible, whitewashed and
              clean, but very
              bare of furniture. In one corner, near a small
              fire, sat an old man, leaning his head on his hands
              in a disconsolate attitude. The young girl was
              occupied in arranging the cottage; but presently she
              took something
              out of a drawer, which employed her hands, and
              she sat down beside the old man, who, taking up
              an
              instrument, began to play, and to produce sounds
              sweeter than the voice of the thrush or the
              nightingale. It was a lovely sight, even to me,
              poor
              wretch! who had never beheld aught beautiful
              before. The silver hair and benevolent countenance of
              the aged cottager won my reverence, while the gentle
              manners of the girl enticed my love. He played a
              sweet mournful air, which I perceived drew tears from
              the eyes of his amiable companion, of which the
              old
              man took no notice, until she sobbed audibly; he
              then pronounced a few sounds, and the fair creature,
              leaving her work, knelt at his feet. He raised her,
              and smiled with such kindness and affection, that I
              felt sensations of a peculiar and overpowering
              nature: they were a mixture
              of pain and pleasure, such as I had never before
              experienced, either from hunger or cold, warmth or
              food; and I withdrew from the window, unable to bear
              these emotions.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Soon after this the young man returned, bearing
              on his shoulders a load of wood. The girl met him at
              the door, helped to relieve him of his burden, and,
              taking some of the fuel into the cottage, placed it
              on the fire; then she and the youth went apart into a
              nook of the cottage, and he showed her a large loaf
              and a piece of cheese. She
              seemed pleased, and went into the garden for some
              roots
              and plants, which she placed in water, and then
              upon the fire. She afterwards continued her work,
              whilst the young man went into the garden, and
              appeared busily employed in digging and pulling up
              roots. After he had been employed thus about an hour,
              the young woman joined him, and they entered the
              cottage together.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The old man had,
              in the meantime, been pensive; but, on the appearance
              of his companions, he assumed a more cheerful air,
              and they sat down to eat. The meal was quickly
              dispatched. The young woman was again occupied in
              arranging the cottage; the old man walked before the
              cottage in the sun for a few minutes, leaning on the
              arm of the youth. Nothing could exceed in beauty the
              contrast between these two excellent creatures. One
              was old, with silver hairs and a countenance beaming
              with benevolence and love; the younger was slight and
              graceful in his figure, and his features were moulded
              with the finest symmetry; yet his eyes and attitude
              expressed the utmost sadness and despondency. The old
              man returned to the cottage; and the youth, with
              tools different from those he had used in the
              morning, directed his steps across the fields.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Night quickly shut in; but, to my extreme wonder,
              I found that the cottagers had a means of prolonging
              light by the use of tapers,
              and was delighted to find that the setting of the sun
              did not put an end to the pleasure I experienced in
              watching my human neighbours. In the evening, the
              young girl and her companion were employed in various
              occupations which I did not understand; and the old
              man again took up the instrument which produced the
              divine sounds that had enchanted me in the morning.
              So soon as he had finished, the youth began, not to
              play, but to
              utter sounds that were monotonous, and neither
              resembling the harmony of the old man's instrument
              nor the songs of the birds: I since found that he
              read aloud, but at that time I knew nothing of the
              science of words or letters.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>