<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1831v1.preface</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1236</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Preface</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>
                        <name>Henry Colburn</name> and <name>Richard Bentley</name>
                     </publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1831</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">Rev., Corr. [2nd ed.]</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="ser">Bentley's Standard Novels series</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="no">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1831 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Preface</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>THE event on which this fiction is founded has
              been supposed, by Dr.
              Darwin, and some of the
              physiological writers of Germany, as not of
              impossible occurrence. I shall not be supposed as
              according the remotest degree of serious faith to
              such an imagination; yet, in assuming it as the basis
              of a work of fancy, I have not considered myself as
              merely
              weaving a series of supernatural terrors. The
              event on which the interest of the story depends is
              exempt from the disadvantages of a mere tale of
              spectres or enchantment. It was recommended by the
              novelty of the situations which it developes; and,
              however impossible as a physical fact, affords
              a
              point of view to the imagination for the
              delineating of human passions more comprehensive and
              commanding than any which the ordinary relations of
              existing events can yield.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I have thus endeavoured to preserve the truth of
              the elementary principles of human nature, while
              I
              have not scrupled to innovate upon their
              combinations. The Iliad, the tragic poetry of
              Greece, Shakespeare, in the Tempest and
              Midsummer Night's Dream and most especially
              Milton, in Paradise Lost, conform to this
              rule; and the most humble novelist, who seeks to
              confer or receive amusement from his
              labours, may, without presumption, apply to prose
              fiction a licence, or rather a rule, from the
              adoption of which so many exquisite combinations of
              human feeling have resulted in the highest specimens
              of poetry.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The circumstance on which my story rests was
              suggested in casual conversation. It was commenced
              partly as a source of amusement, and partly as an
              expedient for exercising any untried resources of
              mind. Other motives were mingled with these as the
              work proceeded. I am by no means indifferent to the
              manner in which whatever moral tendencies exist in
              the sentiments or characters it contains shall affect
              the reader; yet my chief concern in this respect has
              been limited to the avoiding the enervating effects
              of the novels of the present day, and to the
              exhibition of the
              amiableness of domestic affection, and the
              excellence of universal virtue. The opinions which
              naturally spring from the character and situation of
              the hero are by no means to be conceived as existing
              always in my own conviction; nor is any inference
              justly to be drawn from the following pages as
              prejudicing any philosophical doctrine of whatever
              kind.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>It is a subject also of additional interest to the
              author that this story was begun in the majestic
              region where the scene is principally laid, and in
              society which cannot cease to be regretted. I passed
              the summer of 1816 in the environs of Geneva. The
              season was cold and rainy, and in the evenings we
              crowded around a blazing wood fire, and occasionally
              amused ourselves with some German
              stories of ghosts, which happened to fall into
              our hands. These tales excited in us a playful desire
              of imitation. Two
              other friends (a tale from the pen of one of whom
              would be far more acceptable to the public than any
              thing I can ever hope to produce) and myself agreed
              to write each a story founded on some supernatural
              occurrence.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The weather, however, suddenly became serene; and
              my two friends left me on a journey among the Alps,
              and lost, in the magnificent scenes which they
              present, all memory of their ghostly visions. The
              following tale is the only one which has been
              completed.</p>
               <p>MARLOW, September, 1817.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Introduction | Letter I &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>