<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1831v1.ch5</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1246</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 5</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>
                        <name>Henry Colburn</name> and <name>Richard Bentley</name>
                     </publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1831</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">Rev., Corr. [2nd ed.]</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="ser">Bentley's Standard Novels series</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="no">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1831 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 5</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>IT
              was on a dreary night of November, that I beheld
              the accomplishment of my toils. With an anxiety that
              almost amounted to agony,
              I collected the instruments of life around me, that I
              might infuse a spark
              of being into the lifeless thing that lay at my
              feet. It was already one in the morning; the rain
              pattered dismally against the panes, and my candle
              was nearly burnt out, when, by the glimmer of the
              half-extinguished light, I saw the dull yellow eye of
              the
              creature open; it breathed hard, and a convulsive
              motion agitated its limbs.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>How can I describe my emotions at this catastrophe,
              or how delineate the wretch
              whom with such infinite pains and care I had
              endeavoured to form? His limbs were in proportion,
              and I had selected his features as beautiful.
              
              Beautiful!—Great God! His yellow skin
              scarcely covered the work of muscles and arteries
              beneath; his hair was of a lustrous black, and
              flowing; his teeth of a pearly whiteness; but these
              luxuriances only formed a more horrid contrast with
              his watery eyes, that seemed almost of the same
              colour as the dun white sockets in which they were
              set, his shrivelled complexion and straight black
              lips.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The different accidents of life are not so
              changeable as the feelings of human nature. I had
              worked hard for nearly two years, for the sole
              purpose of infusing life into an inanimate body. For
              this I had deprived myself of rest and health. I had
              desired it with an ardour
              that far exceeded moderation; but now that I had
              finished, the beauty of the dream vanished, and
              breathless
              horror and disgust filled my heart. Unable to
              endure the aspect of the being I had created, I
              rushed out of the room, and continued a long time
              traversing my bed-chamber, unable
              to compose my mind to sleep. At length lassitude
              succeeded to the tumult I had before endured; and I
              threw myself on the bed in my clothes, endeavouring
              to seek a few moments of forgetfulness. But it was in
              vain: I slept indeed, but I was disturbed by the
              wildest dreams. I thought I saw Elizabeth, in the
              bloom of health, walking in the streets of
              Ingolstadt. Delighted and surprised, I embraced her;
              but as I imprinted the first kiss on her lips, they
              became livid with the hue of death; her features
              appeared to change, and I thought that I held the
              corpse
              of my dead mother in my arms; a shroud enveloped
              her form, and I saw the grave-worms crawling in the
              folds of the flannel. I started from my sleep with
              horror; a cold
              dew covered my forehead, my teeth chattered, and
              every limb became convulsed: when, by the dim and
              yellow light of the moon, as it forced its way
              through the window-shutters, I beheld the wretch
              —the miserable monster whom I had created.
              He held up the curtain of the bed; and his eyes, if
              eyes they may be called, were fixed on me. His jaws
              opened, and he muttered
              some inarticulate sounds, while a grin wrinkled
              his cheeks. He might have spoken, but I did not hear;
              one
              hand was stretched out, seemingly to detain
              me, but I escaped, and rushed down stairs. I took
              refuge in the court-yard belonging to the house which
              I inhabited; where I remained during the rest of the
              night, walking up and down in the greatest agitation,
              listening attentively, catching and fearing each
              sound as if it were to announce the approach of the
              demoniacal
              corpse to which I had so miserably given
              life.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Oh! no mortal could support the horror
              of that countenance. A mummy again endued with
              animation could not be so hideous as that wretch. I
              had gazed on him while unfinished; he was ugly then;
              but when those muscles and joints were rendered
              capable of motion, it became a thing such as even
              Dante
              could not have conceived.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I passed the night
              wretchedly.
              Sometimes my pulse beat so quickly and hardly, that I
              felt the palpitation of every artery; at others, I
              nearly sank to the ground through languor and extreme
              weakness. Mingled with this horror, I felt the
              bitterness of disappointment; dreams that had been my
              food and pleasant rest for so long a space, were now
              become
              a hell to me; and the change was so rapid, the
              overthrow
              so complete!</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Morning, dismal and wet, at length dawned, and
              discovered to my sleepless and aching eyes the church
              of Ingolstadt, its white
              steeple and clock, which indicated the sixth
              hour. The porter
              opened the gates of the court, which had that night
              been my asylum, and I issued into the streets, pacing
              them with quick steps, as if I sought to avoid the
              wretch whom I feared every turning of the street
              would present to my view. I did not dare return to
              the apartment which I inhabited, but felt impelled to
              hurry on, although drenched by the rain, which poured
              from a
              black and comfortless sky.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I continued walking in this manner for some time,
              endeavouring, by bodily exercise, to ease the load
              that weighed upon my mind. I traversed the streets,
              without any clear conception of where I was, or what
              I was doing. My heart palpitated in the sickness of
              fear; and I hurried on with irregular steps, not
              daring to look about me:—</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like one who, on a lonely road,<lb/>
                   Doth walk in fear and
                dread,<lb/>
                And, having once turned round, walks on,<lb/>
                   And turns no more his head;<lb/>
                Because he knows a frightful fiend<lb/>
                   Doth close behind him
                tread.*
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Continuing thus, I came at length opposite to the
              inn at which the various diligences and carriages
              usually stopped. Here I paused, I knew not why; but I
              remained some minutes with my
              eyes fixed on a coach that was coming towards me
              from the other end of the street. As it drew nearer,
              I observed that it was the Swiss diligence:
              it stopped just where I was standing; and, on the
              door being opened, I perceived Henry
              Clerval, who, on seeing me, instantly sprung out.
              "My dear Frankenstein," exclaimed he, "how glad I am
              to see you! how fortunate that you should be here at
              the very moment of my alighting!"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Nothing could equal my delight on seeing Clerval;
              his presence brought back to my thoughts my father,
              Elizabeth, and all those scenes of home so dear to my
              recollection. I grasped his hand, and in a moment
              forgot my horror and misfortune; I felt suddenly, and
              for the first time during many months, calm and
              serene joy. I welcomed my friend, therefore, in the
              most cordial manner, and we walked towards my
              college. Clerval continued talking for some time
              about our mutual friends, and his own good fortune in
              being permitted to come to Ingolstadt. "You may
              easily believe," said he, "how great was the
              difficulty to persuade my father that all necessary
              knowledge was not comprised in the noble art of
              book-keeping; and, indeed, I believe I left him
              incredulous to the last, for his constant answer to
              my unwearied entreaties was the same as that of the
              Dutch schoolmaster in the Vicar
              of Wakefield:—'I have ten thousand florins
              a year without Greek, I eat heartily without Greek.'
              But his affection for me at length overcame his
              dislike of learning, and he has permitted me to
              undertake
              a voyage of discovery to the land of
              knowledge."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It gives me the greatest delight to see you; but
              tell me how you left my father, brothers, and
              Elizabeth."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Very well, and very happy, only a little uneasy
              that they
              hear from you so seldom. By the bye, I mean to
              lecture you a little upon their account
              myself.—But, my dear Frankenstein," continued
              he, stopping short, and gazing full in my face, "I
              did not before remark how very ill you appear; so
              thin and pale; you look as if you had been watching
              for several nights."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"You have guessed right; I have lately been so
              deeply engaged in one occupation, that I have not
              allowed myself sufficient rest, as you see: but I
              hope, I sincerely hope, that all these employments
              are now at an end, and that I am
              at length free."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I trembled excessively; I could not endure to
              think of, and far less to allude to the occurrences
              of the preceding night. I walked with a quick pace,
              and we soon arrived at my college. I then reflected,
              and the thought made me shiver, that the creature
              whom I had left in my apartment might still be there,
              alive,
              and walking about. I dreaded to behold this
              monster; but I feared still more that Henry
              should see him. Entreating him, therefore, to remain
              a few minutes at the bottom of the stairs, I darted
              up towards my own room. My hand was already on the
              lock of the door before I recollected myself. I then
              paused; and a cold shivering came over me. I threw
              the door forcibly open, as children are accustomed to
              do when they
              expect a spectre to stand in waiting for them on
              the other side; but nothing appeared. I stepped
              fearfully in: the apartment was empty; and my
              bed-room was also freed from its hideous guest. I
              could hardly believe that so great a good fortune
              could have befallen me; but when I became assured
              that my
              enemy had indeed fled, I clapped my hands for
              joy, and ran down to Clerval.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>We ascended into my room, and the servant
              presently brought breakfast; but I was unable to
              contain myself. It was not joy only that possessed
              me; I felt
              my flesh tingle with excess of sensitiveness, and
              my pulse beat rapidly. I was unable to remain for a
              single instant in the same place; I jumped over the
              chairs, clapped my hands, and laughed aloud. Clerval
              at first attributed my unusual spirits to joy on his
              arrival; but when he observed me more attentively, he
              saw a wildness
              in my eyes for which he could not account; and my
              loud, unrestrained, heartless
              laughter, frightened and astonished him.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"My dear Victor," cried he, "what, for God's sake,
              is the matter? Do not laugh in that manner. How ill
              you are! What is the cause of all this?"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Do not ask me," cried I, putting my hands before
              my eyes, for I thought I saw the dreaded
              spectre glide into the room; "he can
              tell.—Oh, save me! save me!" I imagined that
              the monster
              seized me; I struggled furiously, and fell down in a
              fit.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Poor Clerval! what must have been his feelings? A
              meeting, which he anticipated with such joy, so
              strangely turned to bitterness. But I was not the
              witness of his grief; for I was lifeless,
              and did not recover my senses for a long, long
              time.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>This was the commencement of a nervous
              fever, which confined me for several months.
              During all that time Henry
              was my only nurse. I afterwards learned that,
              knowing my father's advanced age, and unfitness
              for so long a journey, and how wretched my
              sickness would make Elizabeth, he spared them this
              grief by concealing the extent of my disorder. He
              knew that I could not have a more kind and attentive
              nurse than himself; and, firm in the hope he felt of
              my recovery, he did not doubt that, instead
              of doing harm, he performed the kindest action
              that he could towards them.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>But I was in reality very ill; and surely nothing
              but the unbounded and unremitting attentions of my
              friend could have restored
              me to life. The form of the monster on whom I had
              bestowed existence was for ever before my eyes, and I
              raved incessantly concerning him. Doubtless my words
              surprised Henry: he at first believed them to be the
              wanderings of my disturbed
              imagination; but the pertinacity with which I
              continually recurred to the same subject, persuaded
              him that my disorder indeed owed its origin to some
              uncommon and terrible event.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>By very slow degrees, and with frequent relapses,
              that alarmed and grieved my friend, I recovered. I
              remember the first time I became capable
              of observing outward objects with any kind of
              pleasure, I perceived that the fallen leaves had
              disappeared, and that the young buds were shooting
              forth from the trees that shaded my window. It
              was a divine spring; and the season contributed
              greatly to my convalescence. I felt also sentiments
              of joy and affection revive in my bosom; my gloom
              disappeared, and in a short time I became as cheerful
              as before I was attacked by the fatal passion.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Dearest Clerval," exclaimed I, "how kind, how
              very good you are to me. This whole winter, instead
              of being spent in study, as you promised yourself,
              has been consumed in my sick room. How shall I ever
              repay you? I feel the
              greatest remorse for the disappointment of which
              I have been the occasion; but you will forgive
              me."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"You will repay me entirely, if you do not
              discompose yourself, but get well as fast as you can;
              and since you appear in such good spirits, I may
              speak to you on one subject, may I not?"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I trembled. One subject! what could it be? Could
              he allude to an object on whom I dared not even
              think?</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Compose yourself," said Clerval, who observed my
              change of colour, "I will not mention it, if it
              agitates you; but your father and cousin would be
              very happy if they received a letter from you in your
              own hand-writing. They hardly know how ill you have
              been, and are uneasy
              at your long silence."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Is that all, my dear Henry? How could you suppose
              that my
              first thought would not fly towards those dear, dear
              friends whom I love, and who are so deserving of
              my love."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"If this is your present temper, my friend, you
              will perhaps be glad to see a letter that has been
              lying here some days for you: it is from your cousin,
              I believe."<lb/>
                  <lb/>
              *Coleridge's "Ancient
              Mariner."</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 4 | Chapter
          6 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>