<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1818v2.ch2</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1219</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 2</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Lackington, Hughes, Harding, Mavor, &amp; Jones</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1818</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">The First Edition</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1818 EDITION : VOL. II</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 2</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p> THE next day, contrary to the
              prognostications of our guides, was fine, although
              clouded. We visited the source of the
              Arveiron, and rode about the valley until
              evening. These sublime and magnificent scenes
              afforded me the greatest consolation that I was
              capable of receiving. They elevated me from all
              littleness of feeling; and although they did not
              remove my grief, they subdued and tranquillized it.
              In some degree, also, they diverted my mind from the
              thoughts over which it had brooded for the last
              month. I returned in the evening, fatigued, but less
              unhappy, and conversed
              with my family with more cheerfulness than had
              been my custom for some time. My father was pleased,
              and Elizabeth overjoyed. "My dear cousin," said she,
              "you see what happiness you diffuse when you are
              happy; do not relapse again!"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The following morning
              the rain poured down in torrents, and thick mists hid
              the summits of the mountains. I rose early, but felt
              unusually melancholy. The rain depressed me; my old
              feelings recurred, and I was miserable. I knew how
              disappointed my father would be at this sudden
              change, and I
              wished to avoid him until I had recovered myself
              so far as to be enabled to conceal those feelings
              that overpowered me. I knew that they would remain
              that day at the inn; and as I had ever inured myself
              to rain, moisture, and cold, I resolved to go alone
              to the
              summit of Montanvert. I remembered the effect
              that the view of the tremendous
              and ever-moving glacier had produced upon my mind
              when I first saw it. It had then filled me with a
              sublime ecstasy that gave wings to the soul, and
              allowed it to soar from the obscure world to light
              and joy. The sight of the
              awful and majestic in nature had indeed always
              the effect of solemnizing my mind, and causing me to
              forget the passing cares of life. I
              determined to go alone, for I was well acquainted
              with the path, and the presence of another would
              destroy the solitary grandeur of the scene.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> The ascent is precipitous, but the path
              is cut into continual and short
              windings, which enable you to surmount the
              perpendicularity of the mountain. It is a scene
              terrifically desolate. In a thousand spots the traces
              of the winter avelanche may be perceived, where
              trees
              lie broken and strewed on the ground; some
              entirely destroyed, others bent, leaning upon the
              jutting rocks of the mountain, or transversely upon
              other trees. The path, as you ascend higher, is
              intersected by ravines of snow, down which stones
              continually roll from above; one of them is
              particularly dangerous, as the slightest sound, such
              as even speaking in a loud voice, produces a
              concussion of air sufficient to draw destruction upon
              the head of the speaker. The pines
              are not tall or luxuriant, but they are sombre, and
              add an air of severity to the scene. I looked on the
              valley beneath; vast mists were rising from the
              rivers which ran through it, and curling in thick
              wreaths around the opposite mountains, whose summits
              were hid in the uniform clouds, while rain poured
              from the dark sky, and added to the melancholy
              impression I received from the objects around me.
              Alas! why does man
              boast of sensibilities superior to those apparent
              in the brute; it only renders them more necessary
              beings. If our impulses were confined to hunger,
              thirst, and desire, we
              might be nearly free; but now we are moved by
              every wind that blows, and a chance word or scene
              that that word may convey to us.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                We rest; a dream has power to poison sleep.<lb/>
                   We rise; one wand'ring thought
                pollutes the day.<lb/>
                We feel, conceive, or reason; laugh, or weep,<lb/>
                   Embrace fond woe, or cast our
                cares away;<lb/>
                It is the same: for, be it joy or sorrow,<lb/>
                   The path of its departure still
                is free.<lb/>
                Man's yesterday may ne'er be like his morrow;<lb/>
                   Nought may endure but mutability!
              </l>
               </lg>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> It was nearly noon when I arrived at the
              top of the ascent. For some time I sat upon the rock
              that overlooks the sea
              of ice. A mist covered both that and the
              surrounding mountains. Presently a breeze dissipated
              the cloud, and I descended upon the glacier. The
              surface is very uneven, rising like the waves of a
              troubled sea, descending low, and interspersed by
              rifts that sink deep. The field of ice is almost
              a
              league in width, but I spent nearly two hours in
              crossing it. The opposite mountain is a bare
              perpendicular rock. From the side where I now stood
              Montanvert was exactly opposite, at the distance of a
              league; and above it rose Mont Blanc, in awful
              majesty. I remained in a recess of the rock, gazing
              on this wonderful and stupendous scene. The sea, or
              rather
              the vast river of ice, wound among its dependent
              mountains, whose aërial summits hung over its
              recesses. Their icy and glittering peaks shone in the
              sunlight over the clouds. My heart, which was before
              sorrowful, now swelled with something like joy;
              I
              exclaimed—"Wandering spirits, if indeed ye
              wander, and do not rest in your narrow beds, allow me
              this faint happiness, or take me, as your companion,
              away from the joys of life."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As I said this, I
              suddenly beheld the figure of a man, at some
              distance, advancing towards me with superhuman speed.
              He bounded over the crevices in the ice, among which
              I had walked with caution; his stature also, as he
              approached, seemed to exceed that of man. I was
              troubled: a mist came over my eyes, and I felt a
              faintness seize me; but I was quickly restored by the
              cold gale of the mountains. I perceived, as the shape
              came nearer, (sight
              tremendous and abhorred!) that it was the
              wretch whom I had created. I trembled with rage
              and horror, resolving to wait his approach, and then
              close with him in mortal combat. He approached;
              his
              countenance bespoke bitter anguish, combined with
              disdain and malignity, while its unearthly ugliness
              rendered it almost too horrible for human eyes. But I
              scarcely observed this; anger
              and hatred had at first deprived me of utterance,
              and I recovered only to overwhelm him with words
              expressive of furious detestation and contempt.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Devil!"
              I exclaimed, "do you dare approach me? and do not you
              fear the fierce vengeance of my arm wreaked on your
              miserable
              head?Begone,
              vile insect! or rather stay, that I may trample
              you to dust! and, oh, that I could, with the
              extinction of your miserable existence, restore those
              victims whom you have so diabolically murdered!"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I expected this
              reception," said the dæmon. "All men hate
              the
              wretched; how then must I be hated, who am
              miserable
              beyond all living things! Yet you, my
              creator, detest and spurn me, thy creature, to
              whom thou art bound
              by ties only dissoluble by the annihilation of
              one of us. You purpose to kill me. How dare
              you sport thus with life? Do your
              duty towards me, and I will do mine towards you
              and the rest of mankind. If you will comply with my
              conditions, I will leave them and you at peace; but
              if you refuse, I will glut the maw of death, until it
              be satiated with the blood of your remaining
              friends."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Abhorred monster!
              fiend that thou art! the tortures
              of hell are too mild a vengeance for thy crimes.
              Wretched devil! you reproach me with your creation;
              come on then, that I may extinguish the spark which I
              so negligently bestowed."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>My rage was without
              bounds; I sprang on him, impelled by all the
              feelings which can arm one being against the
              existence of another.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> He easily eluded me, and said,</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Be calm! I entreat you
              to hear me, before you give vent to your hatred on
              my
              devoted head. Have I not suffered enough, that
              you seek to increase my misery? Life, although it may
              only be an accumulation of anguish, is dear to me,
              and I will defend it. Remember, thou hast made me
              more powerful than thyself; my height is superior to
              thine; my joints more supple. But I will not be
              tempted to set
              myself in opposition to thee. I am thy creature,
              and I will be even mild and docile to my natural lord
              and king, if thou wilt also perform thy part, the
              which thou owest me. Oh, Frankenstein, be not
              equitable to every other, and trample upon me alone,
              to whom thy
              justice, and even thy clemency and affection, is
              most due. Remember that I am thy creature: I
              ought to be thy Adam; but I am rather the fallen
              angel, whom thou drivest from joy for no misdeed.
              Every where I see bliss, from which I alone am
              irrevocably excluded. I
              was benevolent and good; misery
              made me a fiend. Make me happy, and I shall again
              be virtuous."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Begone! I will not
              hear you. There
              can be no community between you and me; we are
              enemies.
              Begone, or let us try
              our strength in a fight, in which one must
              fall."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> "How
              can I move thee? Will no entreaties cause thee to
              turn a favourable eye upon thy creature, who implores
              thy goodness and compassion. Believe me,
              Frankenstein: I
              was benevolent; my soul glowed with love
              and humanity: but am I
              not alone, miserably alone? You, my creator,
              abhor me; what hope can I gather from your
              fellow-creatures, who owe me nothing? they spurn and
              hate me. The
              desert mountains and dreary glaciers are my
              refuge. I have wandered here many days; the caves of
              ice, which I only do not fear, are a dwelling to me,
              and the only one which man does not grudge. These
              bleak skies I hail, for they are kinder to me than
              your fellow-beings. If the multitude
              of mankind knew of my existence, they would do as
              you do, and arm themselves for my destruction. Shall
              I not then hate them who abhor me? I
              will keep no terms with my enemies. I am
              miserable, and they
              shall share my wretchedness. Yet it is in your
              power to recompense me, and deliver them from an evil
              which it only remains for you to make so great, that
              not
              only you and your family, but thousands of
              others, shall be swallowed up in the whirlwinds of
              its rage. Let your compassion be moved, and do not
              disdain me. Listen to my tale: when you have heard
              that, abandon or commiserate me, as you shall judge
              that I deserve. But hear me. The guilty
              are allowed, by human laws, bloody as they may
              be, to speak in their own defence before they are
              condemned. Listen to me, Frankenstein. You
              accuse me of murder; and yet you would, with a
              satisfied conscience, destroy your own creature. Oh,
              praise the eternal justice of man! Yet I ask you not
              to spare me: listen to me; and then, if you can, and
              if you will, destroy the work of your hands."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Why do you call to my
              remembrance circumstances of which I shudder to
              reflect, that I have been the miserable origin and
              author? Cursed be the day, abhorred
              devil, in which you first saw light! Cursed
              (although I curse myself) be the hands that
              formed you! You
              have made me wretched beyond expression. You have
              left me no
              power to consider whether I am just to you, or
              not. Begone! relieve me from the sight of your
              detested form."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Thus
              I relieve thee, my creator," he said, and placed
              his hated hands before my eyes, which I flung from me
              with violence; "thus I take from thee a sight which
              you abhor. Still thou canst listen to me, and grant
              me thy
              compassion. By the
              virtues that I once possessed, I demand this from
              you. Hear my tale; it is long and strange, and the
              temperature of this place is not fitting to your fine
              sensations; come to the
              hut upon the mountain. The sun is yet high in the
              heavens; before it descends to hide itself behind yon
              snowy precipices, and illuminate another world, you
              will have heard my story, and can decide. On you it
              rests, whether I quit forever the neighbourhood of
              man, and lead a harmless life, or become the scourge
              of your fellow-creatures, and the author of your own
              speedy ruin."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As he said this, he led
              the way across the ice: I followed. My heart was
              full, and I did not answer him; but, as I proceeded,
              I weighed the various arguments that he had used, and
              determined at least to listen to his tale. I was
              partly
              urged by curiosity, and compassion confirmed my
              resolution. I had hitherto supposed him to be the
              murderer of my brother, and I eagerly sought a
              confirmation or denial of this opinion. For the first
              time, also, I felt what the
              duties of a creator towards his creature were,
              and that I ought to render him happy before I
              complained of his wickedness. These motives urged me
              to comply with his demand. We crossed the ice,
              therefore, and ascended the opposite rock. The air
              was cold, and the rain again began to descend: we
              entered the hut, the
              fiend with an air of exultation, I with a heavy
              heart, and depressed spirits. But I consented to
              listen; and, seating myself by the fire which my
              odious companion had lighted, he
              thus began his tale.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 1 | Chapter
          3 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>