<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1818v1.ch3</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1211</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 3</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Lackington, Hughes, Harding, Mavor, &amp; Jones</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1818</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">The First Edition</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1818 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 3</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>FROM this day natural
              philosophy, and particularly chemistry, in the most
              comprehensive sense of the term, became nearly my
              sole occupation. I read with ardour
              those works, so full of genius and discrimination,
              which modern inquirers have written on these
              subjects. I attended the lectures, and cultivated the
              acquaintance, of the men of science of the
              university; and I found even in M. Krempe a great
              deal of sound sense and real information, combined,
              it is true, with a repulsive physiognomy
              and manners, but not on that account the less
              valuable. In M. Waldman I found a true friend. His
              gentleness was never tinged by dogmatism; and his
              instructions were given with an air of frankness and
              good nature that banished every idea of pedantry. It
              was, perhaps, the amiable character of this man that
              inclined me more to that branch of natural philosophy
              which he professed, than an intrinsic love for the
              science itself. But this state of mind had place only
              in the first steps towards knowledge: the more fully
              I entered into the science, the more exclusively I
              pursued
              it for its own sake. That application, which at
              first had been a matter of duty
              and resolution, now became so ardent and eager, that
              the stars often disappeared in the light of morning
              whilst I was yet engaged in my laboratory.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As I applied so
              closely, it may be easily conceived that I improved
              rapidly. My
              ardour was indeed the astonishment
              of the students; and my proficiency, that of the
              masters. Professor Krempe often asked me, with a sly
              smile, how Cornelius Agrippa went on? whilst M.
              Waldman expressed the most heartfelt exultation in my
              progress. Two years passed in this manner, during
              which I
              paid no visit to Geneva, but was engaged,
              heart and soul, in the pursuit of some
              discoveries, which I hoped to make. None but those
              who have experienced them can conceive of the
              enticements of science. In other studies you go as
              far as others have gone before you, and there is
              nothing more to know; but in a scientific pursuit
              there is continual
              food for discovery and wonder. A mind of moderate
              capacity, which closely pursues one study, must
              infallibly arrive at great proficiency in that study;
              and I, who continually sought the attainment of one
              object of pursuit, and was solely wrapped up in this,
              improved so rapidly, that, at the end of two years, I
              made some discoveries in the improvement of some
              chemical instruments, which procured me great esteem
              and admiration at the university. When I had arrived
              at this point, and had become as well acquainted with
              the theory and practice of natural philosophy as
              depended on the lessons of any of the professors at
              Ingolstadt, my residence there being no longer
              conducive to my improvements, I
              thought of returning to my friends and my native
              town, when an incident happened that protracted my
              stay.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>One of the
              phænomena which had peculiarly attracted my
              attention was the
              structure of the human frame, and, indeed, any
              animal endued with life. Whence, I often asked
              myself, did the principle of life proceed? It was a
              bold question, and one which has ever been considered
              as a mystery; yet with how many things are we upon
              the brink of becoming acquainted, if
              cowardice or carelessness did not restrain our
              inquiries. I revolved these circumstances in my mind,
              and determined thenceforth to apply myself more
              particularly to those branches of natural philosophy
              which relate to physiology. Unless I had been
              animated by an almost supernatural enthusiasm, my
              application to this study would have been irksome,
              and almost intolerable. To examine the causes of
              life, we must first have recourse to death. I became
              acquainted with the science
              of anatomy: but this was not sufficient; I must
              also observe the natural decay and corruption of the
              human body. In my education my father had taken the
              greatest precautions that my mind should be impressed
              with no
              supernatural horrors. I do not ever remember to
              have trembled at a tale of superstition, or to have
              feared the apparition of a spirit. Darkness had no
              effect upon my fancy; and a churchyard was to me
              merely the receptacle of bodies deprived of life,
              which, from being the seat of beauty and strength,
              had become food for the worm. Now I
              was led to examine the cause and progress of this
              decay, and forced to spend days and nights in
              vaults
              and charnel houses. My attention was fixed upon
              every object the most insupportable to the delicacy
              of the human feelings. I saw how the fine
              form of man was degraded and wasted; I beheld the
              corruption of death succeed to the blooming cheek of
              life; I saw how the worm inherited the wonders of the
              eye and brain. I paused, examining and analysing all
              the minutiae of causation, as exemplified in the
              change from life to death, and death to life, until
              from the midst of this darkness a sudden light broke
              in upon me—a light so brilliant and wondrous,
              yet so simple, that while I became dizzy with the
              immensity of the prospect which it illustrated, I was
              surprised that among so many men of genius, who had
              directed their inquiries towards the same science,
              that I alone should be reserved to discover so
              astonishing a secret.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Remember, I am not
              recording the vision
              of a madman. The sun does not more certainly
              shine in the heavens, than that which I now affirm is
              true. Some miracle might have produced it, yet the
              stages of the discovery were distinct and probable.
              After days
              and nights of incredible labour and fatigue, I
              succeeded in discovering the cause of generation and
              life; nay, more, I became myself capable of bestowing
              animation upon lifeless matter.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The astonishment which
              I had at first experienced on this discovery soon
              gave place to delight and rapture.
              After so much time spent in painful labour, to arrive
              at once at the summit
              of my desires, was the most gratifying consummation
              of my toils. But this discovery was so great and
              overwhelming, that all the steps by which I had been
              progressively led to it were obliterated, and I
              beheld only the result. What had been the study and
              desire of the wisest men since the creation of the
              world, was now within my grasp. Not that, like a
              magic
              scene, it all opened upon me at once: the
              information I had obtained was of a nature rather to
              direct my endeavours so soon as I should point them
              towards the object of my search, than to exhibit that
              object already accomplished. I was like the Arabian
              who had been buried with the dead, and found a
              passage to life aided only by one glimmering, and
              seemingly ineffectual, light.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I see
              by your eagerness, and the wonder and hope which
              your eyes express, my friend, that you expect to be
              informed of the secret with which I am acquainted;
              that cannot be: listen patiently until the end of my
              story, and you will easily perceive why I am reserved
              upon that subject. I will not lead you on, unguarded
              and ardent
              as I then was, to your destruction and infallible
              misery. Learn from me, if not by my precepts, at
              least by my example, how
              dangerous is the acquirement of knowledge, and
              how much happier that man is who believes his native
              town to be the world, than he who aspires to become
              greater than his nature
              will allow.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>When I found so
              astonishing a power placed within my hands, I
              hesitated a long time concerning the
              manner in which I should employ it. Although I
              possessed the capacity of bestowing animation, yet to
              prepare a frame for the reception of it, with all its
              intricacies of fibres,
              muscles, and veins, still remained a work of
              inconceivable difficulty and labour. I doubted at
              first whether I should attempt the creation
              of a being like myself or one of simpler
              organization; but my
              imagination was too much exalted by my first
              success to permit me to doubt of my ability to give
              life to an animal as complex and wonderful as man.
              The materials at present within my command hardly
              appeared adequate to so arduous an undertaking; but I
              doubted not that I should ultimately succeed. I
              prepared myself for a multitude of reverses; my
              operations might be incessantly baffled, and at last
              my work be imperfect: yet, when I considered the
              improvement which every day takes place in science
              and mechanics, I was encouraged to hope my present
              attempts would at least lay the foundations of future
              success. Nor could I consider the magnitude and
              complexity of my plan as any argument of its
              impracticability. It was with these feelings that I
              began the creation of a human being. As the
              minuteness of the parts formed a great hindrance to
              my speed, I resolved, contrary to my first intention,
              to make the being of a gigantic stature; that is to
              say, about eight
              feet in height, and proportionably large. After
              having formed this determination, and having spent
              some months in successfully collecting and arranging
              my materials, I
              began.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>No one can conceive the
              variety of feelings which bore me onwards, like a
              hurricane, in the first enthusiasm
              of success. Life and death appeared to me ideal
              bounds, which I should first break through, and pour
              a torrent of light into our dark world. A new species
              would bless me as its creator
              and source; many happy and excellent natures
              would owe their being to me. No
              father could claim the gratitude of his child so
              completely as I should deserve their's.
              Pursuing these reflections, I thought, that if I
              could bestow animation upon lifeless matter, I might
              in process of time (although I now found it
              impossible) renew
              life where death had apparently devoted the body
              to corruption.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>These thoughts
              supported my spirits, while I pursued my undertaking
              with unremitting
              ardour. My cheek had grown pale with study, and
              my
              person had become emaciated with confinement.
              Sometimes, on the very brink of certainty, I failed;
              yet still I clung to the hope which the next day or
              the next hour might realise. One secret which I alone
              possessed was the hope to which I had dedicated
              myself; and the moon gazed on my midnight labours,
              while, with unrelaxed and breathless eagerness, I
              pursued nature to her hiding-places. Who shall
              conceive the horrors of my secret toil, as I dabbled
              among the unhallowed damps of the grave, or tortured
              the living animal to animate the lifeless clay?
              My limbs now tremble, and my eyes swim with the
              remembrance; but then a resistless, and almost
              frantic impulse, urged me forward; I
              seemed to have lost all soul or sensation but for
              this one pursuit. It was indeed but a passing trance,
              that only made me feel with renewed acuteness so soon
              as, the unnatural stimulus ceasing to operate, I had
              returned to my old habits. I collected bones from
              charnel houses; and disturbed, with profane fingers,
              the tremendous secrets of the human frame. In a
              solitary chamber, or rather cell, at the top of the
              house, and separated from all the other apartments by
              a gallery
              and staircase, I kept my
              workshop of filthy creation; my eyeballs were
              starting from their sockets in attending to the
              details of my employment. The dissecting
              room and the slaughter-house
              furnished many of my materials; and often did my
              human nature turn with loathing from my occupation,
              whilst, still urged on by an eagerness which
              perpetually increased, I brought my work near to a
              conclusion.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The summer months
              passed while I was thus engaged, heart
              and soul, in one pursuit. It was a most beautiful
              season; never did the fields bestow a more plentiful
              harvest, or the vines yield a more luxuriant vintage:
              but my
              eyes were insensible to the charms of nature. And
              the same feelings which made me neglect the scenes
              around me caused me also to
              forget those friends who were so many miles
              absent, and whom I had not seen for so long a time. I
              knew my silence disquieted them; and I well
              remembered the words of my father: "I know that while
              you are pleased with yourself, you will think of us
              with affection, and we shall hear regularly from you.
              You must pardon me, if I regard any interruption in
              your correspondence as a proof that your
              other duties are equally neglected."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I knew well therefore
              what would be my father's feelings; but I could not
              tear my thoughts from my employment, loathsome in
              itself, but which had
              taken an irresistible hold of my imagination. I
              wished, as it were, to procrastinate
              all that related to my feelings of affection
              until the great object, which swallowed up every
              habit of my nature, should be completed.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I then thought
              that my father would be unjust if he ascribed my
              neglect to vice, or faultiness on my part; but I am
              now convinced that he was justified in conceiving
              that I should not be altogether free from blame.
              A human being in perfection ought always to preserve
              a calm and peaceful mind, and never to allow passion
              or a transitory desire to disturb his tranquillity. I
              do not think that the pursuit
              of knowledge is an exception to this rule. If the
              study to which you apply yourself has a tendency to
              weaken your affections, and to destroy your taste for
              those simple pleasures in which no alloy can possibly
              mix, then that study is certainly unlawful, that is
              to say, not befitting the human mind. If this rule
              were always observed; if no man allowed any pursuit
              whatsoever to interfere with the tranquillity of his
              domestic
              affections, Greece had not been enslaved; Caesar
              would have spared his country; America would have
              been discovered more gradually; and the empires of
              Mexico and Peru had not been
              destroyed.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>But I forget that I am
              moralizing in the most
              interesting part of my tale; and your looks
              remind me to proceed.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>My father made no
              reproach in his letters; and only took notice of my
              silence by inquiring into my occupations more
              particularly than before. Winter, spring, and summer
              passed away during my labours; but I did not watch
              the blossom or the expanding leaves—sights
              which before always yielded me supreme delight, so
              deeply was I engrossed in my occupation. The leaves
              of that year had withered before my work drew near to
              a close; and now every day shewed me more plainly how
              well I had succeeded. But my enthusiasm
              was checked by my anxiety, and I appeared rather
              like one doomed
              by slavery to toil in the mines, or any other
              unwholesome trade, than an artist occupied by his
              favourite employment. Every night I was oppressed by
              a slow
              fever, and I became nervous to a most painful
              degree; a disease that I regretted the more because I
              had hitherto enjoyed most excellent health, and had
              always boasted of the firmness of my nerves. But I
              believed that exercise and amusement would soon drive
              away such symptoms; and I promised myself both of
              these, when my creation should be complete.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 2 | Chapter
          4 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>