<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1831v2.ch13</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1254</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 13</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>
                        <name>Henry Colburn</name> and <name>Richard Bentley</name>
                     </publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1831</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">Rev., Corr. [2nd ed.]</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="ser">Bentley's Standard Novels series</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="no">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1831 EDITION : VOL. II</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 13</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>"I NOW hasten
              to the more
              moving part of my story. I shall relate events,
              that impressed me with feelings
              which, from what I had been, have made me what I
              am.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Spring advanced rapidly; the weather became fine,
              and the skies cloudless. It surprised me, that what
              before was desert and gloomy should now bloom with
              the most beautiful flowers and verdure. My senses
              were gratified and refreshed by a thousand scents of
              delight, and a thousand sights of beauty.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It was on one of these days, when my cottagers
              periodically rested from labour—the old man
              played on his guitar, and the children listened to
              him—that I observed the countenance of Felix
              was melancholy beyond expression; he sighed
              frequently; and once his father paused in his music,
              and I conjectured by his manner that he inquired the
              cause of his son's sorrow. Felix replied in a
              cheerful accent, and the old man was recommencing his
              music, when some one tapped at the door.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"It was a
              lady on horseback, accompanied by a countryman as
              a guide. The lady was dressed in a dark suit, and
              covered with a thick black veil. Agatha asked a
              question; to which the stranger only replied by
              pronouncing, in a sweet accent, the name of Felix.
              Her voice was musical, but unlike that of either of
              my friends. On hearing this word, Felix came up
              hastily to the lady; who, when she saw him, threw up
              her veil, and I
              beheld a countenance of angelic beauty and
              expression. Her hair of a shining raven black, and
              curiously braided; her eyes were dark, but gentle,
              although animated; her features of a regular
              proportion, and her complexion wondrously fair, each
              cheek tinged with a lovely pink.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Felix seemed
              ravished with delight when he saw her, every trait of
              sorrow vanished from his face, and it instantly
              expressed a degree of ecstatic joy, of which I could
              hardly have believed it capable; his eyes sparkled,
              as his cheek flushed with pleasure; and at that
              moment I
              thought him as beautiful as the stranger. She
              appeared affected by different feelings; wiping a few
              tears from her lovely eyes, she held out her hand to
              Felix, who kissed it rapturously, and called her, as
              well as I could distinguish, his sweet Arabian. She
              did not appear to understand him, but smiled. He
              assisted her to dismount, and, dismissing her guide,
              conducted her into the cottage. Some conversation
              took place between him and his father; and the young
              stranger knelt at the old man's feet, and would have
              kissed his hand, but he raised her, and embraced her
              affectionately.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I soon perceived, that although the stranger
              uttered articulate sounds, and appeared to have a
              language of her own, she
              was neither understood by, nor herself understood,
              the cottagers. They made many signs which I did
              not comprehend; but I saw that her presence diffused
              gladness through the cottage, dispelling their sorrow
              as the sun dissipates the morning mists. Felix seemed
              peculiarly happy, and with smiles of delight welcomed
              his Arabian. Agatha, the ever-gentle Agatha, kissed
              the hands of the lovely stranger; and, pointing to
              her brother, made signs which appeared to me to mean
              that he had been sorrowful until she came. Some hours
              passed thus, while they, by their countenances,
              expressed joy, the cause of which I did not
              comprehend. Presently I found, by the frequent
              recurrence of some sound which the stranger repeated
              after them, that she was endeavouring to learn their
              language; and the idea instantly occurred to me, that
              I
              should make use of the same instructions to the same
              end. The stranger learned about twenty words at
              the first lesson, most of them, indeed, were those
              which I had before understood, but I profited by the
              others.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"As night came on,
              Agatha and the Arabian retired early. When they
              separated, Felix kissed the hand of the stranger, and
              said, 'Good night, sweet Safie.' He sat up much
              longer, conversing with his father; and, by the
              frequent repetition of her name, I conjectured that
              their lovely guest was the subject of their
              conversation. I
              ardently desired to understand them, and bent
              every faculty towards that purpose, but found it
              utterly impossible.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The next morning Felix went out to his work; and,
              after the usual occupations of Agatha were finished,
              the Arabian sat at the feet of the old man, and,
              taking his guitar, played some airs so entrancingly
              beautiful, that they at once drew tears
              of sorrow and delight from my eyes. She sang, and
              her voice flowed in a rich cadence, swelling or dying
              away, like a nightingale of the woods.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"When she had finished, she gave the guitar to
              Agatha, who at first declined it. She played a simple
              air, and her voice accompanied it in sweet accents,
              but unlike the wondrous strain of the stranger. The
              old man appeared enraptured, and said some words,
              which Agatha endeavoured to explain to Safie, and by
              which he appeared to wish to express that she
              bestowed on him the greatest delight by her
              music.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The days now passed as peacefully as before, with
              the sole alteration, that joy had taken the place of
              sadness in the countenances of my friends. Safie was
              always gay and happy; she
              and I improved rapidly in the knowledge of
              language, so that in two months I began to
              comprehend most of the words uttered by my
              protectors.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"In the meanwhile
              also the black ground was covered with herbage, and
              the green banks interspersed with innumerable
              flowers, sweet to the scent and the eyes, stars
              of pale radiance among the moonlight woods; the
              sun became warmer, the nights clear and balmy; and my
              nocturnal rambles were an extreme pleasure to me,
              although they were considerably shortened by the late
              setting and early rising of the sun; for I never
              ventured abroad during day-light, fearful of meeting
              with the same treatment I had formerly endured in the
              first village which I entered.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"My days were spent in close attention, that I
              might more speedily master the language; and I may
              boast that I
              improved more rapidly than the Arabian, who
              understood very little, and conversed in broken
              accents, whilst I comprehended and could imitate
              almost every word that was spoken.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"While I improved in speech, I also learned the
              science
              of letters, as it was taught to the stranger; and
              this opened before me a wide field for wonder and
              delight.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The book from which Felix instructed Safie was
              Volney's 'Ruins
              of Empires.' I should not have understood the
              purport of this book, had not Felix, in reading it,
              given very minute explanations. He had chosen this
              work, he said, because the declamatory style was
              framed in imitation of the eastern authors. Through
              this work I obtained a cursory knowledge of history,
              and a view of the several empires at present existing
              in the world; it gave me an insight into the manners,
              governments, and religions of the different nations
              of the earth. I heard of the slothful Asiatics; of
              the stupendous genius and mental activity of the
              Grecians; of the wars and wonderful virtue of the
              early Romans -- of their subsequent degenerating --
              of the decline of that mighty empire; of chivalry,
              Christianity, and kings. I heard of the discovery of
              the American hemisphere, and wept with Safie over
              the
              hapless fate of its original inhabitants.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"These wonderful
              narrations inspired me with strange feelings. Was
              man, indeed, at once so
              powerful, so virtuous, and magnificent, yet so
              vicious and base? He appeared at one time a mere
              scion of the evil principle, and at another, as all
              that can be conceived of noble and godlike. To be a
              great and virtuous man appeared the highest honour
              that can befall a sensitive being; to be base and
              vicious, as many on record have been, appeared the
              lowest degradation, a condition more abject than that
              of the blind mole or harmless worm. For a long time I
              could not conceive how one man could go forth to
              murder his fellow, or even why there were laws and
              governments; but when I heard details of vice and
              bloodshed, my wonder ceased, and I turned away with
              disgust and loathing.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Every conversation of the cottagers now opened
              new wonders to me. While I listened to the
              instructions which Felix bestowed upon the Arabian,
              the strange
              system of human society was explained to me. I
              heard of the division of property, of immense wealth
              and squalid poverty; of rank,
              descent, and noble blood.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The words induced me to turn towards myself. I
              learned that the possessions most esteemed by your
              fellow-creatures were, high and unsullied descent
              united with riches. A man might be respected with
              only one of these advantages; but, without either, he
              was considered, except in very rare instances, as a
              vagabond and a slave, doomed
              to waste his powers for the profits of the chosen
              few. And what was I? Of my creation and creator I
              was absolutely ignorant; but I knew that I
              possessed no money, no friends, no kind of
              property. I was, besides, endued with a figure
              hideously deformed and loathsome; I was not even of
              the same nature as man. I was more agile than they,
              and could subsist upon coarser diet; I bore the
              extremes of heat and cold with less injury to my
              frame; my stature far exceeded theirs. When I looked
              around, I saw and heard of none like me. Was
              I then a monster, a blot upon the earth, from
              which all men fled, and whom all men disowned?</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I cannot describe
              to you the agony that these reflections inflicted
              upon me: I tried to dispel them, but sorrow
              only increased with knowledge. Oh, that I had for
              ever remained in my native wood, nor known nor felt
              beyond the
              sensations of hunger, thirst, and heat!</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Of
              what a strange nature is knowledge! It clings to
              the mind, when it has once seized on it, like a
              lichen on the rock. I wished sometimes to shake off
              all thought and feeling; but I learned that there was
              but one means to overcome the sensation of pain, and
              that was death—a state which I feared yet did
              not understand. I admired virtue and good feelings,
              and loved the gentle manners and amiable qualities of
              my cottagers; but I was shut out from intercourse
              with them, except through means which I obtained by
              stealth, when I was unseen and unknown, and which
              rather increased than satisfied the desire I had of
              becoming one among my fellows. The gentle words of
              Agatha, and the animated smiles of the charming
              Arabian, were not for me. The mild exhortations of
              the old man, and the lively conversation of the loved
              Felix, were not for me. Miserable,
              unhappy wretch!</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Other
              lessons were impressed upon me even more deeply.
              I heard of the difference of sexes; and the birth and
              growth of children; how the father doated on the
              smiles of the infant, and the lively sallies of the
              older child; how all the life and cares of the mother
              were wrapped up in the precious charge; how the mind
              of youth expanded and gained knowledge; of brother,
              sister, and all the various relationships which bind
              one human being to another in mutual
              bonds.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"But where were my
              friends and relations? No father had watched my
              infant days, no mother had blessed me with smiles and
              caresses; or if they had, all my past life was now a
              blot, a blind
              vacancy in which I distinguished nothing. From my
              earliest remembrance I had been as I then was in
              height and proportion. I had never yet seen a being
              resembling me, or who claimed any intercourse with
              me. What was I? The question again recurred, to be
              answered only with groans.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I will soon explain to what these feelings
              tended; but allow me now to return to the cottagers,
              whose story excited in me such various feelings of
              indignation, delight, and wonder, but which all
              terminated in additional love and reverence for my
              protectors (for so I loved, in an innocent, half
              painful self-deceit,
              to call them).</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 12 | Chapter
          14 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>