<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1831v1.let1</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1238</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Letter I</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>
                        <name>Henry Colburn</name> and <name>Richard Bentley</name>
                     </publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1831</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">Rev., Corr. [2nd ed.]</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="ser">Bentley's Standard Novels series</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="no">9</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1831 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Letter
          I</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>To Mrs.
              SAVILLE, England.</p>
               <p>St. Petersburgh, December 11,
              17--.</p>
               <p>YOU will rejoice to
                hear that no disaster has accompanied the
                commencement of an enterprise which you have
                regarded with such evil
                forebodings. I arrived here yesterday; and my
                first task is to assure my dear sister of my
                welfare, and increasing confidence in the success
                of my undertaking.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I am already far north of London; and as I walk in
              the streets of Petersburgh, I feel a cold northern
              breeze play upon my cheeks, which braces my nerves,
              and fills me with delight. Do you understand this
              feeling? This breeze, which has travelled from the
              regions towards which I am advancing, gives me a
              foretaste of those icy climes. Inspirited
              by this wind of promise, my day
              dreams become more fervent and vivid. I try in
              vain to be persuaded that the pole is the seat of
              frost and desolation; it ever presents itself to my
              imagination as the region of beauty and delight.
              There, Margaret, the
              sun is for ever visible; its broad disk just
              skirting the horizon, and diffusing a perpetual
              splendour. There—for with your leave, my
              sister, I will put some trust in preceding navigators—there
              snow
              and frost are banished; and, sailing over a calm
              sea, we may be wafted to a land surpassing in wonders
              and in beauty every region hitherto discovered on the
              habitable globe. Its productions and features may be
              without example, as the phenomena of the heavenly
              bodies undoubtedly are in those undiscovered
              solitudes. What may not be expected in a country of
              eternal light? I may there discover the wondrous
              power which attracts the needle; and may regulate
              a thousand celestial
              observations, that require only this voyage to
              render their seeming eccentricities consistent for
              ever. I shall satiate my ardent
              curiosity with the sight of a part of the world
              never before visited, and may tread a land never
              before imprinted by the foot of man. These are my
              enticements, and they are sufficient to conquer all
              fear of danger or death, and to induce me to commence
              this laborious voyage with the joy a child feels when
              he embarks in a little boat, with his holiday mates,
              on an expedition of discovery up his native river.
              But, supposing all these conjectures to be false, you
              cannot contest the inestimable benefit which I shall
              confer on all mankind to the last generation, by
              discovering a passage
              near the pole to those countries, to reach which
              at present so many months are requisite; or by
              ascertaining the secret
              of the magnet, which, if at all possible, can
              only be effected by an undertaking such as mine.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>These
              reflections have dispelled the agitation with
              which I began my letter, and I feel my heart glow
              with an enthusiasm
              which elevates me to heaven; for nothing contributes
              so much to tranquilise the mind as a steady
              purpose,—a point on which the soul may fix its
              intellectual eye. This expedition has been the
              favourite dream of my early years. I have read with
              ardour the accounts of the various voyages which have
              been made in the prospect of arriving at the North
              Pacific Ocean through the seas which surround the
              pole. You may remember that a history of all
              the voyages made for purposes of discovery
              composed the whole of our good uncle Thomas's
              library. My education was neglected, yet I was
              passionately fond of reading. These volumes were my
              study day and
              night, and my familiarity with them increased
              that regret which I had felt, as a child, on learning
              that my father's
              dying injunction had forbidden my uncle to allow
              me to embark in a seafaring life.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>These visions faded when I perused, for the first
              time, those poets whose effusions entranced my soul,
              and lifted it to heaven. I also
              became a poet, and for one year lived in a
              Paradise of my own creation; I imagined that I also
              might obtain a niche in the temple where the names of
              Homer and Shakespeare are consecrated. You are well
              acquainted with my failure, and how heavily I bore
              the disappointment. But just at that time I inherited
              the fortune of my cousin,
              and my thoughts were turned into the channel of their
              earlier bent.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Six years have passed
              since I resolved on my present undertaking. I can,
              even now, remember the hour from which I dedicated
              myself to this
              great enterprise. I commenced by inuring my body
              to hardship. I accompanied the whale-fishers on
              several expeditions to the North Sea; I voluntarily
              endured cold, famine, thirst, and want of sleep; I
              often worked harder than the common sailors during
              the day, and devoted my nights to the study of
              mathematics, the theory of medicine, and those
              branches of physical
              science from which a naval adventurer might
              derive the greatest practical advantage. Twice I
              actually hired myself as an under-mate in a Greenland
              whaler, and acquitted myself to admiration. I must
              own I felt a little proud, when my captain offered me
              the second
              dignity in the vessel, and entreated me to remain
              with the greatest earnestness; so valuable did he
              consider my services.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>And now, dear Margaret, do I not deserve to
              accomplish some great purpose? My life might have
              been passed in ease and luxury; but I preferred
              glory
              to every enticement that wealth
              placed in my path. Oh, that some encouraging voice
              would answer in the affirmative! My courage
              and my resolution
              is firm;
              but my hopes fluctuate, and my spirits are often
              depressed. I am about to proceed on a long and
              difficult voyage, the emergencies of which will
              demand all my fortitude: I am required not only to
              raise the spirits of others, but sometimes to sustain
              my own, when theirs are failing.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>This is the most favourable period for travelling
              in Russia. They fly quickly over the snow in their
              sledges; the motion is pleasant, and, in my opinion,
              far more agreeable than that of an English
              stage-coach. The cold is not excessive, if you are
              wrapped in furs—a dress which I have already
              adopted; for there is a great difference between
              walking the deck and remaining seated motionless for
              hours, when no exercise prevents the blood from
              actually freezing in your veins. I have no ambition
              to lose my life on the post-road between St.
              Petersburgh and Archangel.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I shall depart for the latter town in a fortnight
              or three weeks; and my intention is to hire a ship
              there, which can easily be done by paying the
              insurance for the owner, and to engage as many
              sailors as I think necessary among those who are
              accustomed to the whale-fishing. I do not intend to
              sail until the month of June:
              and when shall I return? Ah, dear sister, how can I
              answer this question? If I succeed, many, many
              months, perhaps years, will pass before you and I may
              meet. If I fail, you will see me again soon, or
              never.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Farewell, my dear, excellent Margaret. Heaven
              shower down blessings on you, and save me, that I may
              again
              and again testify my gratitude for all your love
              and kindness.</p>
               <p>Your affectionate brother,</p>
               <p>R. WALTON.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Preface | Letter
          II &gt;</p>
         <p>YOU will rejoice to
                hear that no disaster has accompanied the
                commencement of an enterprise which you have
                regarded with such evil
                forebodings. I arrived here yesterday; and my
                first task is to assure my dear sister of my
                welfare, and increasing confidence in the success
                of my undertaking.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>