<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">frank27.1818v1.ch2</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce1210</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in
														any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
														reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
														amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by
														the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
														copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
														republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
														advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
														to Romantic Circles:&gt;
														<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
																written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
																current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own
														servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our
														holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited
														resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally
														available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at
														Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Chapter 2</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <author>
                     <persName>Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851</persName>
                  </author>
                  <title type="main" level="m">Frankenstein, </title>
                  <title type="subordinate" level="m">Or, the Modern Prometheus</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Lackington, Hughes, Harding, Mavor, &amp; Jones</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <date>1818</date>
                     <biblScope type="ed">The First Edition</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for
														’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML
														entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
														http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
														2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g12"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2009-05-01" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2009-05-01" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#MQ" when="2009-05-01" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
            <list>
               <item>XHTML Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TEXTS : 1818 EDITION : VOL. I</head>
         <p rend="emph">Chapter 2</p>
         <p> </p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>
               <p>WHEN I had attained the
              age of seventeen, my parents resolved that I should
              become a student at the university
              of Ingolstadt.
              I had hitherto attended the schools of Geneva; but my
              father thought it necessary, for the completion of my
              education,
              that I should be made acquainted with other customs
              than those of my native country. My departure was
              therefore fixed at an early date; but, before the day
              resolved upon could arrive, the first misfortune of
              my life occurred— an
              omen, as it were, of my future misery.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Elizabeth had caught
              the scarlet
              fever; but her illness was not severe, and she
              quickly recovered. During her confinement, many
              arguments had been urged to persuade my mother to
              refrain from attending upon her. She had, at first,
              yielded to our entreaties; but when she heard that
              her favourite was recovering, she could no longer
              debar herself from her society, and entered her
              chamber long before the danger of infection was past.
              The consequences of this imprudence were fatal. On
              the third day my mother sickened; her fever was very
              malignant, and the looks of her attendants
              prognosticated the worst event. On her death-bed
              the fortitude and benignity of this admirable woman
              did not desert her. She joined the hands of Elizabeth
              and myself: "My children," she said, "my firmest
              hopes of future happiness were placed on the prospect
              of your union. This expectation will now be the
              consolation of your father. Elizabeth, my love, you
              must supply my place to your younger cousins. Alas! I
              regret that I am taken from you; and, happy and
              beloved as I have been, is it not hard to quit you
              all? But these are not thoughts befitting me; I will
              endeavour to resign myself cheerfully to death, and
              will indulge a hope of meeting you in another
              world."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>She died calmly; and
              her countenance expressed affection even in death. I
              need not describe the feelings of those whose dearest
              ties are rent by that most irreparable evil, the void
              that presents itself to the soul, and the despair
              that is exhibited on the countenance. It is so long
              before the mind can persuade itself that she,
              whom we saw every day, and whose very existence
              appeared a part of our own, can have departed for
              ever—that the brightness of a beloved eye can
              have been extinguished, and the sound of a voice so
              familiar, and dear to the ear, can be hushed, never
              more to be heard. These are the reflections of the
              first days; but when the lapse of time proves the
              reality of the evil, then the actual bitterness of
              grief commences. Yet from whom has not that rude hand
              rent away some dear connexion; and why should I
              describe a sorrow which all have felt, and must feel?
              The time at length arrives, when grief is rather an
              indulgence than a necessity; and the smile that plays
              upon the lips, although it may be deemed a sacrilege,
              is not banished. My
              mother was dead, but we had still duties
              which we ought to perform; we must continue our
              course with the rest, and learn to think ourselves
              fortunate, whilst one remains whom the spoiler has
              not seized.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>My journey to
              Ingolstadt, which had been deferred by these events,
              was now again determined upon. I obtained from my
              father a respite of some weeks. This period was spent
              sadly; my mother's death, and my speedy departure,
              depressed our spirits; but Elizabeth endeavoured to
              renew the spirit of cheerfulness in our little
              society. Since the death of her aunt, her mind had
              acquired new firmness and vigour. She determined to
              fulfil
              her duties with the greatest exactness; and she
              felt that that most imperious duty, of rendering her
              uncle and cousins happy, had devolved upon her. She
              consoled me, amused her uncle, instructed my
              brothers; and I never beheld her so enchanting as at
              this time, when she was continually endeavouring to
              contribute to the happiness of others, entirely
              forgetful
              of herself.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The day of my departure
              at length arrived. I had taken leave of all my
              friends, excepting Clerval, who spent the last
              evening with us. He bitterly lamented that he was
              unable to accompany me: but his
              father could not be persuaded to part with him,
              intending that he should become a partner with him in
              business, in compliance with his favourite theory,
              that learning was superfluous in the commerce of
              ordinary life. Henry had a refined mind; he had no
              desire to be idle, and was well pleased to become his
              father's partner, but he believed that a man might
              become a very good trader,
              and yet possess a cultivated understanding.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>We sat late, listening
              to his complaints, and making many little
              arrangements for the future. The next morning early I
              departed. Tears gushed from the eyes of Elizabeth;
              they proceeded partly from sorrow at my departure,
              and partly because she reflected that the same
              journey was to have taken place three months before,
              when a mother's blessing would have accompanied
              me.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I threw myself into the
              chaise that was to convey me away, and indulged in
              the most melancholy reflections. I, who had ever been
              surrounded by amiable companions, continually engaged
              in endeavouring to bestow mutual pleasure, I
              was now alone. In the university, whither I was
              going, I must form my own friends, and be my own
              protector. My life had hitherto been remarkably
              secluded and domestic; and this had given me
              invincible repugnance to new countenances. I loved my
              brothers, Elizabeth, and Clerval; these were
              "old
              familiar faces;" but I believed myself totally
              unfitted for the company of strangers. Such were my
              reflections as I commenced my journey; but as I
              proceeded, my spirits and hopes rose. I
              ardently desired the acquisition of knowledge. I
              had often, when at home, thought it hard to remain
              during my youth cooped up in one place, and had
              longed to enter the world, and take my station among
              other human beings. Now my desires were complied
              with, and it would, indeed, have been folly to
              repent.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I had sufficient
              leisure for these and many other reflections during
              my journey to Ingolstadt, which was long
              and fatiguing. At length the high
              white steeple of the town met my eyes. I
              alighted, and was conducted to my solitary apartment,
              to spend the evening as I pleased.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The next morning I
              delivered my letters of introduction, and paid a
              visit to some of the principal professors, and among
              others to M.
              Krempe, professor
              of natural philosophy. He received me with
              politeness, and asked me several questions concerning
              my progress in the different branches of science
              appertaining to natural philosophy. I mentioned, it
              is true, with fear and trembling, the only authors I
              had ever read upon those subjects. The professor
              stared: "Have you," he said, "really spent your time
              in studying such nonsense?"</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I replied in the
              affirmative. "Every minute," continued M. Krempe with
              warmth, "every instant that you have wasted on those
              books is utterly and entirely lost. You have burdened
              your memory with exploded systems, and useless names.
              Good God! in what desert land have you lived, where
              no one was kind enough to inform you that these
              fancies, which you have so greedily imbibed, are a
              thousand years old, and as musty as they are ancient?
              I little expected in this enlightened and scientific
              age to find a disciple of Albertus Magnus and
              Paracelsus. My dear Sir, you must begin your studies
              entirely anew."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>So saying, he stepped
              aside, and wrote down a list of several books
              treating of natural philosophy, which he desired me
              to procure, and dismissed me, after mentioning that
              in the beginning of the following week he intended to
              commence a course of lectures upon natural philosophy
              in its general relations, and that M.
              Waldman, a fellow-professor, would lecture upon
              chemistry the alternate days that he missed.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I returned home, not
              disappointed, for I had long considered those authors
              useless whom the professor had so strongly
              reprobated; but I did not feel much inclined to study
              the books which I had procured at his recommendation.
              M. Krempe was a little squat
              man, with a gruff voice and repulsive
              countenance; the teacher, therefore, did not
              prepossess me in favour of his doctrine. Besides, I
              had a contempt
              for the uses of modern natural philosophy. It was
              very different, when the masters of the science
              sought immortality and power; such views, although
              futile, were grand: but now the scene was changed.
              The ambition of the inquirer seemed to limit
              itself to the annihilation of those visions on
              which my interest in science was chiefly founded. I
              was required to exchange chimeras
              of boundless grandeur for realities of little
              worth.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Such were my
              reflections during the first two or three days
              spent
              almost in solitude. But as the ensuing week
              commenced, I thought of the information which M.
              Krempe had given me concerning the lectures. And
              although I could not consent to go and hear that
              little conceited fellow deliver sentences out of a
              pulpit, I recollected what he had said of M. Waldman,
              whom I had never seen, as he had hitherto been out of
              town.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Partly
              from curiosity, and partly from idleness, I went
              into the lecturing room, which M.
              Waldman entered shortly after. This professor was
              very unlike his colleague. He appeared about fifty
              years of age, but with an aspect expressive of the
              greatest benevolence; a few grey hairs covered his
              temples, but those at the back of his head were
              nearly black. His person was short, but remarkably
              erect; and his voice the sweetest I had ever heard.
              He began his lecture by a recapitulation of the
              history of chemistry, and the various improvements
              made by different men of learning, pronouncing with
              fervour the names of the most distinguished
              discoverers. He then took a cursory view of the
              present state of the science, and explained many of
              its elementary terms. After having made a few
              preparatory experiments, he concluded with a
              panegyric upon modern chemistry, the terms of which I
              shall never forget:—</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"The ancient teachers
              of this science," said he, "promised impossibilities,
              and performed nothing. The modern masters promise
              very little; they know that metals
              cannot be transmuted, and that the elixir of life
              is a chimera. But these philosophers, whose
              hands seem only made to dabble in dirt, and their
              eyes to pore over the microscope
              or crucible,
              have indeed performed miracles. They penetrate into
              the recesses of nature, and shew how she works in her
              hiding places. They ascend
              into the heavens; they have discovered how the
              blood
              circulates, and the nature
              of the air we breathe. They have acquired new and
              almost unlimited powers; they can command the
              thunders of heaven, mimic the earthquake, and even
              mock the invisible world with its own shadows."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>I departed highly
              pleased with the professor and his lecture, and paid
              him a visit the same evening. His manners in private
              were even more mild and attractive than in public;
              for there was a certain dignity in his mien during
              his lecture, which in his own house was replaced by
              the greatest affability and kindness. He heard with
              attention my little narration concerning my studies,
              and smiled at the names of Cornelius Agrippa and
              Paracelsus, but without the contempt that M. Krempe
              had exhibited. He said, that "these were men to whose
              indefatigable zeal modern philosophers were indebted
              for most of the foundations of their knowledge. They
              had left to us, as an easier task, to give new names,
              arrange
              in connected classifications, the facts which
              they in a great degree had been the instruments of
              bringing to light. The labours of men of genius,
              however erroneously directed, scarcely ever fail in
              ultimately turning to the solid advantage of
              mankind." I listened to his statement, which was
              delivered without any presumption or affectation; and
              then added, that his lecture had removed my
              prejudices against modern chemists; and I, at the
              same time, requested his advice concerning the books
              I ought to procure.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"I am happy," said M.
              Waldman, "to have gained a disciple; and if your
              application equals your ability, I have no doubt of
              your success. Chemistry
              is that branch of natural philosophy in which the
              greatest improvements have been and may be made; it
              is on that account that I have made it my peculiar
              study; but at the same time I have not neglected the
              other branches of science. A man would make but a
              very sorry chemist, if he attended to that department
              of human knowledge alone. If your wish is to become
              really a man of science, and not merely a petty
              experimentalist, I should advise you to apply to
              every branch of natural philosophy, including
              
              mathematics."</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>He then took me into
              his laboratory, and explained to me the uses of his
              various machines; instructing me as to what I ought
              to procure, and promising me the use of his own, when
              I should have advanced far enough in the science not
              to derange their mechanism. He also gave me the list
              of books which I had requested; and I took my
              leave.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Thus ended a day
              memorable to me; it decided my future destiny.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>&lt; Chapter 1 | Chapter
          3 &gt;</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>