<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C12"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p15"/>“Dear, dear Elizabeth!” I exclaimed when I had read her letter, “I will write
            instantly, and relieve them from the anxiety they must feel.” I wrote, and this exertion
            greatly fatigued me; but my convalescence had commenced, and proceeded regularly. In
            another fortnight I was able to leave my chamber.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p15"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p16"/>One of my first duties on my recovery was to introduce Clerval to the several
            professors of the university. In doing this, I underwent a kind of rough usage, ill
            befitting the wounds that my mind had sustained. Ever since the fatal <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_144" n="125"/>night, the end of my labours, and the beginning of my
            misfortunes, I had conceived a violent antipathy even to the name of natural philosophy.
            When I was otherwise quite restored to health the sight of a chemical instrument would
            renew all the agony of my nervous symptoms. Henry saw this, and had removed all my
            apparatus from my view. He had also changed my apartment; for he perceived that I had
            acquired a dislike for the room which had previously been my laboratory. But these cares
            of Clerval were made of no avail when I visited the professors. M. Waldman inflicted
            torture when he praised, with kindness and warmth, the astonishing progress I had made
            in the sciences. He soon perceived that I disliked the subject; but not guessing the
            real cause, he attributed my feelings to modesty, and changed the subject from my im<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_145" n="126"/>provement, to the science itself, with a desire, as I
            evidently saw, of drawing me out. What could I do? He meant to please, and he tormented
            me. I felt as if he had placed carefully, one by one, in my view those instruments which
            were to be afterwards used in putting me to a slow and cruel death. I writhed under his
            words, yet dared not exhibit the pain I felt. Clerval, whose eyes and feelings were
            always quick in discerning the sensations of others, declined the subject, alleging, in
            excuse, his total ignorance; and the conversation took a more general turn. I thanked my
            friend from my heart, but I did not speak. I saw plainly that he was surprised, but he
            never attempted to draw my secret from me; and although I loved him with a mixture of
            affection and reverence that knew no bounds, yet I could never persuade <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_146" n="127"/>myself to confide to him that event which was so often
            present to my recollection, but which I feared the detail to another would only impress
            more deeply.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p16"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p17"/>M. Krempe was not equally docile; and in my condition at that time, of almost
            insupportable sensitiveness, his harsh blunt encomiums gave me even more pain than the
            benevolent approbation of M. Waldman. “D—n the fellow!” cried he; “why, M. Clerval, I
            assure you he has outstript us all. Ay, stare if you please; but it is nevertheeless
            true. A youngster who, but a few years ago, believed Cornelius Agrippa, as firmly as the
            gospel, has now set himself at the head of the university; and if he is not soon pulled
            down, we shall all be out of countenance.—Ay, ay,” continued he, observing my face
            expressive of suffering, <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_147" n="128"/>“M. Frankenstein is modest;
            an excellent quality in a young man. Young men should be diffident of themselves, you
            know, M. Clerval; I was myself when young: but that wears out in a very short time.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p17"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p18"/>M. Krempe had now commenced an eulogy on himself, which happily turned the conversation
            from a subject that was so annoying to me.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p18"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p19"/>Clerval was no natural philosopher. His imagination was too vivid for the minutæ of
            science. Languages were his principal study; and he sought, by acquiring their elements,
            to open a field for self-instruction on his return to Geneva. Persian, Arabic, and
            Hebrew, gained his attention, after he had made himself perfectly master of Greek and
            Latin. For my own part, idleness had ever been irksome to me; and now that I wished to
            fly from reflection, and hated my for<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_148" n="129"/>mer studies, I
            felt great relief in being the fellow-pupil with my friend, and found not only
            instruction but consolation in the works of the orientalists. Their melancholy is
            soothing, and their joy elevating to a degree I never experienced in studying the
            authors of any other country. When you read their writings, life appears to consist in a
            warm sun and garden of roses,—in the smiles and frowns of a fair enemy, and the fire
            that consumes your own heart. How different from the manly and heroical poetry of Greece
            and Rome.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p19"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p20"/>Summer passed away in these occupations, and my return to Geneva was fixed for the
            latter end of autumn; but being delayed by several accidents, winter and snow arrived,
            the roads were deemed impassable, and my journey was retarded until the ensuing spring.
            I felt this delay very bitterly; for I <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_149" n="130"/>longed to see
            my native town, and my beloved friends. My return had only been delayed so long from an
            unwillingness to leave Clerval in a strange place, before he had become acquainted with
            any of its inhabitants. The winter, however, was spent cheerfully; and although the
            spring was uncommonly late, when it came its beauty compensated for its
            dilatoriness.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p20"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p21"/>The month of May had already commenced, and I expected the letter daily which was to
            fix the date of my departure, when Henry proposed a pedestrian tour in the environs of
            Ingolstadt, that I might bid a personal farewell to the country I had so long inhabited.
            I acceded with pleasure to this proposition: I was fond of exercise, and Clerval had
            always been my favourite companion in the rambles of this nature that I had taken among
            the scenes of my native country.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p21"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p22"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_150" n="131"/>We passed a fortnight in these perambulations: my
            health and spirits had long been restored, and they gained additional strength from the
            salubrious air I breathed, the natural incidents of our progress, and the conversation
            of my friend. Study had before secluded me from the intercourse of my fellow-creatures,
            and rendered me unsocial; but Clerval called forth the better feelings of my heart; he
            again taught me to love the aspect of nature, and the cheerful faces of children.
            Excellent friend! how sincerely did you love me, and endeavour to elevate my mind, until
            it was on a level with your own. A selfish pursuit had cramped and narrowed me, until
            your gentleness and affection warmed and opened my senses; I became the same happy
            creature who, a few years ago, loving and beloved by all, had no sorrow or care. When
              hap<pb xml:id="F1823_v1_151" n="132"/>py, inanimate nature had the power of bestowing
            on me the most delightful sensations. A serene sky and verdant fields filled me with
            ecstasy. The present season was indeed divine; the flowers of spring bloomed in the
            hedges, while those of summer were already in bud: I was undisturbed by thoughts which
            during the preceding year had pressed upon me, notwithstanding my endeavours to throw
            them off, with an invincible burden.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p22"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p23"/>Henry rejoiced in my gaiety, and sincerely sympathized in my feelings: he exerted
            himself to amuse me, while he expressed the sensations that filled his soul. The
            resources of his mind on this occasion were truly astonishing: his conversation was full
            of imagination; and very often, in imitation of the Persian and Arabic writers, he
            invented tales of wonderful fancy and <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_152" n="133"/>passion. At
            other times he repeated my favourite poems, or drew me out into arguments, which he
            supported with great ingenuity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p23"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p24"/>We returned to our college on a Sunday afternoon: the peasants were dancing, and every
            one we met appeared gay and happy. My own spirits were high, and I bounded along with
            feelings of unbridled joy and hilarity.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter5_div4_div5_p24"/>
          <pb xml:id="F1823_v1_153" n="134"/>
        <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="5"/>
        </xml>
