<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C11"/>
        <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="6"/>
          <head sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_head1"/>CHAPTER VI.<head eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_head1"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1"/> C<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1_hi1"/>LERVAL<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1_hi1"/> then put the following letter into my hands. It was
            from my own Elizabeth:—<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p1"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p2"/>“My dearest Cousin,<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p2"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p3"/>“You have been ill, very ill, and even the constant letters of dear kind Henry are not
            sufficient to reassure me on your account. You are forbidden to write—to hold a pen; yet
            one word from you, dear Victor, is necessary to calm our apprehensions. For a long time
            I have thought that each post would bring this line, and my persuasions have restrained
            my uncle from undertaking a journey to Ingolstadt. I have prevented his encountering the
            inconveniences and perhaps dangers of so long a journey; yet how often have I regretted
            not being able to perform it myself! I figure to myself that the task of attending on
            your sick bed has devolved on some mercenary old nurse, who could never guess your
            wishes, nor minister to them with the care and affection of your poor cousin. Yet that
            is over now: Clerval writes that indeed you are getting better. I eagerly hope that you
            will confirm this intelligence soon in your own handwriting.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p3"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p4"/>“Get well—and return to us. You will find a happy, cheerful home, and friends who love
            you dearly. Your father’s health is vigorous, and he asks but to see you,—but to be
            assured that you are well; and not a care will ever cloud his benevolent countenance.
            How pleased you would be to remark the improvement of our Ernest! He is now sixteen, and
            full of activity and spirit. He is desirous to be a true Swiss, and to enter into
            foreign service;<pb xml:id="F1831_v_066" n="50"/> but we cannot part with him, at least
            until his elder brother return to us. My uncle is not pleased with the idea of a
            military career in a distant country; but Ernest never had your powers of application.
            He looks upon study as an odious fetter;—his time is spent in the open air, climbing the
            hills or rowing on the lake. I fear that he will become an idler, unless we yield the
            point, and permit him to enter on the profession which he has selected.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p4"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p5"/>“Little alteration, except the growth of our dear children, has taken place since you
            left us. The blue lake, and snow-clad mountains, they never change;—and I think our
            placid home, and our contented hearts are regulated by the same immutable laws. My
            trifling occupations take up my time and amuse me, and I am rewarded for any exertions
            by seeing none but happy, kind faces around me. Since you left us, but one change has
            taken place in our little household. Do you remember on what occasion Justine Moritz
            entered our family? Probably you do not; I will relate her history, therefore, in a few
            words. Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was
            the third. This girl had always been the favourite of her father; but, through a strange
            perversity, her mother could not endure her, and, after the death of M. Moritz, treated
            her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age,
            prevailed on her mother to allow her to live at our house. The republican institutions
            of our country have produced simpler and happier manners than those which prevail in the
            great monarchies that surround it. Hence there is less distinction between the several
            classes of its inhabitants; and the lower orders being neither so poor nor so despised,
            their manners are more refined and moral. A servant in Geneva does not mean the same
            thing as a servant in France and England. Justine, thus received in our family, learned
            the duties of a servant; a condition which, in our fortunate country, does not include
            the idea of ignorance, and a sacrifice of the dignity of a human being.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p5"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p6"/>“Justine, you may remember, was a great favourite of yours; and I recollect you once
            remarked, that if you were in an ill-humour, one glance from Justine could dissipate<pb xml:id="F1831_v_067" n="51"/> it, for the same reason that Ariosto gives concerning
            the beauty of Angelica—she looked so frank-hearted and happy. My aunt conceived a great
            attachment for her, by which she was induced to give her an education superior to that
            which she had at first intended. This benefit was fully repaid; Justine was the most
            grateful little creature in the world: I do not mean that she made any professions; I
            never heard one pass her lips; but you could see by her eyes that she almost adored her
            protectress. Although her disposition was gay, and in many respects inconsiderate, yet
            she paid the greatest attention to every gesture of my aunt. She thought her the model
            of all excellence, and endeavoured to imitate her phraseology and manners, so that even
            now she often reminds me of her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p6"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7"/>“When my dearest aunt died, every one was too much occupied in their own grief to
            notice poor Justine, who had attended her during her illness with the most anxious
            affection. Poor Justine was very ill; but other trials were reserved for her.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p7"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8"/>“One by one, her brothers and sister died; and her mother, with the exception of her
            neglected daughter, was left childless. The conscience of the woman was troubled; she
            began to think that the deaths of her favourites was a judgment from heaven to chastise
            her partiality. She was a Roman catholic; and I believe her confessor confirmed the idea
            which she had conceived. Accordingly, a few months after your departure for Ingolstadt,
            Justine was called home by her repentant mother. Poor girl! she wept when she quitted
            our house; she was much altered since the death of my aunt; grief had given softness and
            a winning mildness to her manners, which had before been remarkable for vivacity. Nor
            was her residence at her mother’s house of a nature to restore her gaiety. The poor
            woman was very vacillating in her repentance. She sometimes begged Justine to forgive
            her unkindness, but much oftener accused her of having caused the deaths of her brothers
            and sister. Perpetual fretting at length threw Madame Moritz into a decline, which at
            first increased her irritability, but she is now at peace forever. She died on the first
            approach of cold weather, at the beginning of this<pb xml:id="F1831_v_068" n="52"/> last
            winter. Justine has returned to us; and I assure you I love her tenderly. She is very
            clever and gentle, and extremely pretty; as I mentioned before, her mien and her
            expressions continually remind me of my dear aunt.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p8"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9"/>“I must say also a few words to you, my dear cousin, of little darling William. I wish
            you could see him; he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark
            eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little dimples appear on each cheek,
            which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little <hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1"/>wives<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9_hi1"/>, but Louisa Biron is his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of
            age.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p9"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10"/>“Now, dear Victor, I dare say you wish to be indulged in a little gossip concerning the
            good people of Geneva. The pretty Miss Mansfield has already received the congratulatory
            visits on her approaching marriage with a young Englishman, John Melbourne, Esq. Her
            ugly sister, Manon, married M. Duvillard, the rich banker, last autumn. Your favourite
            schoolfellow, Louis Manoir, has suffered several misfortunes since the departure of
            Clerval from Geneva. But he has already recovered his spirits, and is reported to be on
            the point of marrying a very lively pretty Frenchwoman, Madame Tavernier. She is a
            widow, and much older than Manoir; but she is very much admired, and a favourite with
            everybody.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p10"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11"/>“I have written myself into better spirits, dear cousin; but my anxiety returns upon me
            as I conclude. Write, dearest Victor,—one line—one word will be a blessing to us. Ten
            thousand thanks to Henry for his kindness, his affection, and his many letters: we are
            sincerely grateful. Adieu! my cousin; take care of yourself; and, I entreat you,
            write!<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p11"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12"/>“E<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1"/>LIZABETH<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi1"/> L<hi sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2"/>AVENZA<hi eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12_hi2"/>.<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p12"/>
          <p sID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13"/>“Geneva, March 18th, 17—.”<p eID="novel1_letter4_chapter6_div4_div6_p13"/>
      </xml>
