<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml>
    
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C33"/>
    <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" lrx="5410" lry="6660" partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii" ulx="0" uly="0" mith:folio="31r" mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58" xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0061.xml" xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0061"><graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0061.jp2"/><zone type="main"> <lb n="c58-0061_main_1"/><del rend="strikethrough"><add hand="#library">A11</add></del><handShift medium="pen" new="#mws"/> <lb n="c58-0061_main_2"/>whilst I destroyed his hopes, I did not satisfy my own <lb n="c58-0061_main_3"/>desires. They were forever ardent and craving; <del rend="strikethrough">still</del> <lb n="c58-0061_main_4"/>Still I desired love and fellowship, and I was still <lb n="c58-0061_main_5"/>spurned. W<mod>
             
             <add place="intralinear">a</add>
          </mod>s there no injustice in this? Am I to <lb n="c58-0061_main_6"/>be thought the only criminal when all <w ana="start"/>human<lb n="c58-0061_main_7"/>kind<w ana="end"/> sinned against me? Why do you not hate <w ana="start"/>Fe<lb n="c58-0061_main_8"/>lix<w ana="end"/> who drove his friend from his door with contumely? <lb n="c58-0061_main_9"/>Why do you not execrate the rustic who sought <lb n="c58-0061_main_10"/>to destroy the saviour of his child? Nay, these are <lb n="c58-0061_main_11"/>virtuous and immalculate beings! I, the miserable <lb n="c58-0061_main_12"/>and the abandoned am an abortion to be spurned <lb n="c58-0061_main_13"/>at and kicked and trampled on. Even now my <lb n="c58-0061_main_14"/>blood boils at the recollection of this injustice.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> <lb n="c58-0061_main_15"/>But i<mod>
             
             <add place="intralinear">t</add>
          </mod> is true that I am a <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">wrecth</del> wretch. <lb n="c58-0061_main_16"/>I have murdered the lovely and the helpless. I have <lb n="c58-0061_main_17"/>strangled the innocent as they slept and grasped <lb n="c58-0061_main_18"/>to death his throat who never injured me or any</zone></surface>
    <surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#" lrx="5410" lry="6660" partOf="ox-frankenstein_notebook_c1.xml#ox-frankenstein_volume_iii" ulx="0" uly="0" mith:folio="31v" mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 58" xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c58/ox-ms_abinger_c58-0062.xml" xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c58-0062"><graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c58/ms_abinger_c58-0062.jp2"/><zone type="main"><handShift medium="pen" new="#mws"/> <lb n="c58-0062_main_1"/>other living thing. I have devoted my creator, the <lb n="c58-0062_main_2"/>select specimen of all that is worthy of love and <lb n="c58-0062_main_3"/>admiration among men, to misery<unclear reason="illegible">:</unclear> I have pursued <lb n="c58-0062_main_4"/>him even to that irremediable ruin. There he <lb n="c58-0062_main_5"/>lies, white and cold in death. You hate me, but <lb n="c58-0062_main_6"/>your abhorrence cannot equal that with <lb n="c58-0062_main_7"/>which I regard myself. I look on the hands which <lb n="c58-0062_main_8"/>executed the deed, I think on the heart in which the <lb n="c58-0062_main_9"/>imagination of it was conceived, and long for the <lb n="c58-0062_main_10"/>moment when they will meet my eyes, when it <lb n="c58-0062_main_11"/>will haunt my thoughts no <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">longe</del> more.<milestone unit="tei:p"/> <lb n="c58-0062_main_12"/>Fear not that I shall be the instrument <lb n="c58-0062_main_13"/>of future mischief. My work is nearly <del instant="true" rend="strikethrough">finished</del> <w ana="start"/>com<lb n="c58-0062_main_14"/>plete<w ana="end"/>. Neither yours nor any mans death is needed to <lb n="c58-0062_main_15"/>consummate the series of my being, and accomplish <lb n="c58-0062_main_16"/>that which must be done; but it requires my own. <lb n="c58-0062_main_17"/>Do not think that I shall be slow to perform this</zone></surface>
    
</xml>