<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C03"/>
   <milestone unit="letter" type="start" n="2"/>
   <head>LETTER II.</head>
   <ab rend="center">
      <hi rend="italic">To Mrs.</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">AVILLE</hi>, <hi rend="italic">England.</hi>
   </ab>
   <p>Archangel, 28th March, 17—.</p>
   <p>How slowly the time passes here, encompassed as I am by frost and snow; yet a second step
          is taken towards my enterprise. I have hired a vessel, and am occupied in collecting my
          sailors; those whom I have already engaged appear to be men on whom I can depend, and are
          certainly possessed of dauntless courage.</p>
   <p>But I have one want which I have never yet been able to satisfy; and the absence of the
          object of which I <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_023" n="011"/>now feel as a most severe evil. I
          have no friend, Margaret: when I am glowing with the enthusiasm of success, there will be
          none to participate my joy; if I am assailed by disappointment, no one will endeavour to
          sustain me in dejection. I shall commit my thoughts to paper, it is true; but that is a
          poor medium for the communication of feeling. I desire the company of a man who could
          sympathize with me; whose eyes would reply to mine. You may deem me romantic, my dear
          sister, but I bitterly feel the want of a friend. I have no one near me, gentle yet
          courageous, possessed of a cultivated as well as of a capacious mind, whose tastes are
          like my own, to approve or amend my plans. How would such a friend repair the faults of
          your poor brother! I am too ardent in execution, and too impatient of difficul<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_024" n="012"/>ties. But it is a still greater evil to me that I am
          self-educated: for the first fourteen years of my life I ran wild on a common, and read
          nothing but our uncle Thomas’s books of voyages. At that age I became acquainted with the
          celebrated poets of our own country; but it was only when it had ceased to be in my power
          to derive its most important benefits from such a conviction, that I perceived the
          necessity of becoming acquainted with more languages than that of my native country. Now I
          am twenty-eight, and am in reality more illiterate than many school-boys of fifteen. It is
          true that I have thought more, and that my day dreams are more extended and magnificent;
          but they want (as the painters call it) <hi rend="italic">keeping;</hi> and I greatly need
          a friend who would have sense enough not to despise me as romantic, and affection <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_025" n="013"/>enough for me to endeavour to regulate my mind.</p>
   <p>Well, these are useless complaints; I shall certainly find no friend on the wide ocean,
          nor even here in Archangel, among merchants and seamen. Yet some feelings, unallied to the
          dross of human nature, beat even in these rugged bosoms. My lieutenant, for instance, is a
          man of wonderful courage and enterprise; he is madly desirous of glory. He is an
          Englishman, and in the midst of national and professional prejudices, unsoftened by
          cultivation, retains some of the noblest endowments of humanity. I first became acquainted
          with him on board a whale vessel: finding that he was unemployed in this city, I easily
          engaged him to assist in my enterprise.</p>
   <p>The master is a person of an excellent disposition, and is remarkable in <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_026" n="014"/>the ship for his gentleness, and the mildness of his
          discipline. He is, indeed, of so amiable a nature, that he will not hunt (a favourite, and
          almost the only amusement here), because he cannot endure to spill blood. <del rend="strikethrough">He is, moreover, heroically generous.</del><add place="bottom" anchor="yes">I will relate to you an anecdote of his life, recounted to me by the parties themselves, which exemplifies the generosity, I had almost said the heroism of his nature.</add> Some years ago he loved a young Russian lady, of moderate fortune;
          and having amassed a considerable sum in prize-money, the father of the girl consented to
          the match. He saw his mistress once before the destined ceremony; but she was bathed in
          tears, and, throwing herself at his feet, entreated him to spare her, confessing at the
          same time that she loved another, but that he was poor, and that her father would never
          consent to the union. My generous friend reassured the suppliant, and on being informed of
          the name of her lover instantly abandoned his pursuit. He had <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_027" n="015"/>already bought a farm with his money, on which he had designed to pass the
          remainder of his life; but he bestowed the whole on his rival, together with the remains
          of his prize-money to purchase stock, and then himself solicited the young woman’s father
          to consent to her marriage with her lover. But the old man decidedly refused, thinking
          himself bound in honour to my friend; who, when he found the father inexorable, quitted
          his country, nor returned until he heard that his former mistress was married according to
          her inclinations. “What a noble fellow!” you will exclaim. He is so; but then he has
          passed all his life on board a vessel, and has scarcely an idea beyond the <del rend="strikethrough">rope</del><add place="above">ship</add> and the
      <del rend="strikethrough">shroud</del><add place="above">crew</add>.</p>
   <p>But do not suppose that, because I complain a little, or because I can conceive a
          consolation for my toils which I <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_028" n="016"/>may never know,
          that I am wavering in my resolutions. Those are as fixed as fate; and my voyage is only
          now delayed until the weather shall permit my embarkation. The winter has been dreadfully
          severe; but the spring promises well, and it is considered as a remarkably early season;
          so that, perhaps, I may sail sooner than I expected. I shall do nothing rashly; you know
          me sufficiently to confide in my prudence and considerateness whenever the safety of
          others is committed to my care.</p>
   <p>I cannot describe to you my sensations on the near prospect of my undertaking. It is
          impossible to communicate to you a conception of the trembling sensation, half pleasurable
          and half fearful, with which I am preparing to depart. I am going to unexplored regions,
          to “the land of mist and <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_029" n="017"/>snow;”<note place="bottom" anchored="yes" resp="#MWS">Coleridge's Antient Mariner.</note> but I shall kill no
          albatross, therefore do not be alarmed for my safety.</p>
   <p>Shall I meet you again, after having traversed immense seas, and returned by the most
          southern cape of Africa or America? I dare not expect such success, yet I cannot bear to
          look on the reverse of the picture. Continue to write to me by every opportunity: I may
          receive your letters (though the chance is very doubtful) on some occasions when I need
          them most to support my spirits. I love you very tenderly. Remember me with affection,
          should you never hear from me again.</p>
   <p>Your affectionate brother,</p>
   <p>R<hi rend="smallcaps">OBERT</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">ALTON</hi>.</p>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_030" n="018"/>
   <milestone unit="letter" type="end" n="2"/>
</xml>
