<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C02"/>
   <milestone unit="novel" type="start" n="1"/>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_013"/>
   <head>FRANKENSTEIN;</head>
   <head>
      <hi rend="smallcaps">OR, THE</hi>
   </head>
   <head>
      <hi rend="italic">MODERN PROMETHEUS.</hi>
   </head>
   <comment text=" RM: centered ornamental "/>
   <milestone unit="letter" type="start" n="1"/>
   <head>LETTER I</head>
   <ab rend="center">
      <hi rend="italic">To Mrs.</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">AVILLE</hi>, <hi rend="italic">England.</hi>
   </ab>
   <p>St. Petersburgh, Dec. 11th, 17—.</p>
   <p>Y<hi rend="smallcaps">OU</hi> will rejoice to hear that no disaster has accompanied the
          commencement of an enterprise which you have regarded with such evil forebodings. I
          arrived here yesterday; and my first task is to assure my dear sister of my welfare, and
          increasing confidence in the success of my undertaking.</p>
   <p>I am already far north of London; and as I walk in the streets of Peters<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_014" n="002"/>burgh, I feel a cold northern breeze play upon my
          cheeks, which braces my nerves, and fills me with delight. Do you understand this feeling?
          This breeze, which has travelled from the regions towards which I am advancing, gives me a
          foretaste of those icy climes. Inspirited by this wind of promise, my day dreams become
          more fervent and vivid. I try in vain to be persuaded that the pole is the seat of frost
          and desolation; it ever presents itself to my imagination as the region of beauty and
          delight. There, Margaret, the sun is <del rend="strikethrough">for ever</del><add place="above">constantly</add> visible <add place="margin">for more than half the year</add>; its broad disk just skirting the
          horizon, and diffusing a perpetual splendour. There—for with your leave, my sister, I will
          put some trust in preceding navigators—there snow and frost are banished; and, sailing
          over a calm sea, we may be wafted to a land surpassing in wonders <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_015" n="003"/>and in beauty every region hitherto discovered on the
          habitable globe. Its productions and features may be without example, as the phænomena of
          the heavenly bodies undoubtedly are in those undiscovered solitudes. What may not be
          expected in a country <del rend="strikethrough">of eternal light?</del><add place="margin">ruled by different laws and in which numerous circumstances enforce a belief that the aspect of nature differs essentially from anything of which we have any experience.</add> I may there discover the wondrous power which
          attracts the needle; and may regulate a thousand celestial observations, that require only
          this voyage to render their seeming eccentricities consistent for ever. I shall satiate my
          ardent curiosity with the sight of a part of the world never before visited, and may tread
          a land never before imprinted by the foot of man. These are my enticements, and they are
          sufficient to conquer all fear of danger or death, and to induce me to commence this
          laborious voyage with the joy a child feels when he embarks <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_016" n="004"/>in a little boat, with his holiday mates, on an expedition of discovery up
          his native river. But, supposing all these conjectures to be false, you cannot contest the
          inestimable benefit which I shall confer on all mankind to the last generation, by
          discovering a passage near the pole to those countries, to reach which at present so many
          months are requisite; or by ascertaining the secret of the magnet, which, if at all
          possible, can only be effected by an undertaking such as mine.</p>
   <p>These reflections have dispelled the agitation with which I began my letter, and I feel
          my heart glow with an enthusiasm which elevates me to heaven; for nothing contributes so
          much to tranquillize the mind as a steady purpose,—a point on which the soul may fix its
          intellectual eye. This expedition has been the favourite dream of my <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_017" n="005"/>early years. I have read with ardour the accounts of
          the various voyages which have been made in the prospect of arriving at the North Pacific
          Ocean through the seas which surround the pole. You may remember, that a history of all
          the voyages made for purposes of discovery composed the whole of our good uncle Thomas’s
          library. My education was neglected, yet I was passionately fond of reading. These volumes
          were my study day and night, and my familiarity with them increased that regret which I
          had felt, as a child, on learning that my father’s dying injunction had forbidden my uncle
          to allow me to embark in a sea-faring life.</p>
   <p>These visions faded when I perused, for the first time, those poets whose effusions
          entranced my soul, and lifted it to heaven. I also became a poet, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_018" n="006"/>and for one year lived in a Paradise of my own
          creation; I imagined that I also might obtain a niche in the temple where the names of
          Homer and Shakespeare are consecrated. You are well acquainted with my failure, and how
          heavily I bore the disappointment. But just at that time I inherited the fortune of my
          cousin, and my thoughts were turned into the channel of their earlier bent.</p>
   <p>Six years have passed since I resolved on my present undertaking. I can, even now,
          remember the hour from which I dedicated myself to this great enterprise. I commenced by
          inuring my body to hardship. I accompanied the whale-fishers on several expeditions to the
          North Sea; I voluntarily endured cold, famine, thirst, and want of sleep; I often worked
          harder than the common sailors during the day, and devoted my <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_019" n="007"/>nights to the study of mathematics, the theory of medicine, and those
          branches of physical science from which a naval adventurer might derive the greatest
          practical advantage. Twice I actually hired myself as an under-mate in a Greenland whaler,
          and acquitted myself to admiration. I must own I felt a little proud, when my captain
          offered me the second dignity in the vessel, and entreated me to remain with the greatest
          earnestness; so valuable did he consider my services.</p>
   <p>And now, dear Margaret, do I not deserve to accomplish some great purpose? My life might
          have been passed in ease and luxury; but I preferred glory to every enticement that wealth
          placed in my path. Oh, that some encouraging voice would answer in the affirmative! My
          courage and my resolution is firm; but my hopes fluctuate, <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_020" n="008"/>and my spirits are often depressed. I am about to proceed on a long and
          difficult voyage; the emergencies of which will demand all my fortitude: I am required not
          only to raise the spirits of others, but sometimes to sustain my own, when their’s are
          failing.</p>
   <p>This is the most favourable period for travelling in Russia. They fly quickly over the
          snow in their sledges; the motion is pleasant, and, in my opinion, far more agreeable than
          that of an English stage-coach. The cold is not excessive, if you are wrapt in furs, a
          dress which I have already adopted; for there is a great difference between walking the
          deck and remaining seated motionless for hours, when no exercise prevents the blood from
          actually freezing in your veins. I have no ambition to lose my life on the post-road
          between St. Petersburgh and Archangel.</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_021" n="009"/>I shall depart for the latter town in a fortnight
          or three weeks; and my intention is to hire a ship there, which can easily be done by
          paying the insurance for the owner, and to engage as many sailors as I think necessary
          among those who are accustomed to the whale-fishing. I do not intend to sail until the
          month of June: and when shall I return? Ah, dear sister, how can I answer this question?
          If I succeed, many, many months, perhaps years, will pass before you and I may meet. If I
          fail, you will see me again soon, or never.</p>
   <p>Farewell, my dear, excellent, Margaret. Heaven shower down blessings on you, and save me,
          that I may again and again testify my gratitude for all your love and kindness.</p>
   <p>Your affectionate brother,</p>
   <p>R. W<hi rend="smallcaps">ALTON</hi>.</p>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_022" n="010"/>
   <milestone unit="letter" type="end" n="1"/>
</xml>
