<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
  <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C01"/>
      <milestone unit="volume" n="1"/>
      <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="start" n="1"/>
      <include href="standOff_Includes/1818_frontMatter1.xml" parse="xml"/>
      <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="end" n="1"/>
      <milestone unit="preface" type="start" n="1"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_007" n="viii"/>
      <head sID="preface1_head1"/>PREFACE.<head eID="preface1_head1"/>
      <comment text="rm: centered ornamental "/>
      <p sID="preface1_p1"/>T<hi sID="preface1_p1_hi1"/>HE<hi eID="preface1_p1_hi1"/> event on which this fiction is founded has been supposed, by
        Dr. Darwin, and some of the physiological writers of Germany, as not of impossible
        occurrence. I shall not be supposed as according the remotest degree of serious faith to
        such an imagination; yet, in assuming it as the basis of a work of fancy, I have not
        considered myself as merely weaving a series of supernatural terrors. The event on <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_008" n="viii"/>which the interest of the story depends is exempt from
        the disadvantages of a mere tale of spectres or enchantment. It was recommended by the
        novelty of the situations which it developes; and, however impossible as a physical fact,
        affords a point of view to the imagination for the delineating of human passions more
        comprehensive and commanding than any which the ordinary relations of existing events can
        yield.<p eID="preface1_p1"/>
      <p sID="preface1_p2"/>I have thus endeavoured to preserve the truth of the elementary principles of human nature,
        while I have not scrupled to innovate upon their combinations. The <hi sID="preface1_p2_hi1"/>Iliad<hi eID="preface1_p2_hi1"/>, the tragic poetry of Greece,—Shakespeare, in the <hi sID="preface1_p2_hi2"/>Tempest<hi eID="preface1_p2_hi2"/> and <hi sID="preface1_p2_hi3"/>Mid<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_009" n="ix"/>summer Night’s
          Dream<hi eID="preface1_p2_hi3"/>,—and most especially Milton, in <hi sID="preface1_p2_hi4"/>Paradise Lost<hi eID="preface1_p2_hi4"/>, conform to
        this rule; and the most humble novelist, who seeks to confer or receive amusement from his
        labours, may, without presumption, apply to prose fiction a licence, or rather a rule, from
        the adoption of which so many exquisite combinations of human feeling have resulted in the
        highest specimens of poetry.<p eID="preface1_p2"/>
      <p sID="preface1_p3"/>The circumstance on which my story rests was suggested in casual conversation. It was
        commenced partly as a source of amusement, and partly as an expedient for exercising any
        untried resources of mind. Other motives were mingled with these, as the work pro<pb xml:id="F1818_v1_010" n="x"/>ceeded. I am by no means indifferent to the manner in
        which whatever moral tendencies exist in the sentiments or characters it contains shall
        affect the reader; yet my chief concern in this respect has been limited to the avoiding the
        enervating effects of the novels of the present day, and to the exhibition of the
        amiableness of domestic affection, and the excellence of universal virtue. The opinions
        which naturally spring from the character and situation of the hero are by no means to be
        conceived as existing always in my own conviction; nor is any inference justly to be drawn
        from the following pages as prejudicing any philosophical doctrine of whatever kind.<p eID="preface1_p3"/>
      <p sID="preface1_p4"/>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_011" n="xi"/>It is a subject also of additional interest to the
        author, that this story was begun in the majestic region where the scene is principally
        laid, and in society which cannot cease to be regretted. I passed the summer of 1816 in the
        environs of Geneva. The season was cold and rainy, and in the evenings we crowded around a
        blazing wood fire, and occasionally amused ourselves with some German stories of ghosts,
        which happened to fall into our hands. These tales excited in us a playful desire of
        imitation. Two other friends (a tale from the pen of one of whom would be far more
        acceptable to the public than any thing I can ever hope to produce) and <pb xml:id="F1818_v1_012" n="xii"/>myself agreed to write each a story, founded on some
        supernatural occurrence.<p eID="preface1_p4"/>
      <p sID="preface1_p5"/>The weather, however, suddenly became serene; and my two friends left me on a journey among
        the Alps, and lost, in the magnificent scenes which they present, all memory of their
        ghostly visions. The following tale is the only one which has been completed.<p eID="preface1_p5"/>
      <milestone unit="preface" type="end" n="1"/>

      </xml>
