<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C23"/>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="16"/>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_146" n="142"/>
   <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
   <p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> being finished speaking, and fixed his looks upon me in
            expectation of a reply. But I was bewildered, perplexed, and unable to arrange my ideas
            sufficiently to understand the full extent of his proposition. He continued—</p>
   <p>“You must create a female for me, with whom I can live in the interchange of those
            sympathies necessary for my being. This you alone can do; and I demand it of you as a
            right which you must not refuse.”</p>
   <p>The latter part of his tale had kindled anew in me the anger that had <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_147" n="143"/>died away while he narrated his peaceful life among
            the cottagers, and, as he said this, I could no longer suppress the rage that burned
            within me.</p>
   <p>“I do refuse it,” I replied; “and no torture shall ever extort a consent from me. You
            may render me the most miserable of men, but you shall never make me base in my own
            eyes. Shall I create another like yourself, whose joint wickedness might desolate the
            world. Begone! I have answered you; you may torture me, but I will never consent.”</p>
   <p>“You are in the wrong,” replied the fiend; “and, instead of threatening, I am content
            to reason with you. I am malicious because I am miserable; am I not shunned and hated by
            all mankind? You, my creator, would tear me to pieces, and triumph; remember that, and
            tell me why I should pity man <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_148" n="144"/>more than he pities
            me? You would not call it murder, if you could precipitate me into one of those
            ice-rifts, and destroy my frame, the work of your own hands. Shall I respect man, when
            he contemns me? Let him live with me in the interchange of kindness, and, instead of
            injury, I would bestow every benefit upon him with tears of gratitude at his acceptance.
            But that cannot be; the human senses are insurmountable barriers to our union. Yet mine
            shall not be the submission of abject slavery. I will revenge my injuries: if I cannot
            inspire love, I will cause fear; and chiefly towards you my arch-enemy, because my
            creator, do I swear inextinguishable hatred. Have a care: I will work at your
            destruction, nor finish until I desolate your heart, so that you curse the hour of your
            birth.”</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_149" n="145"/>A fiendish rage animated him as he said this; his
            face was wrinkled into contortions too horrible for human eyes to behold; but presently
            he calmed himself, and proceeded—</p>
   <p>“I intended to reason. This passion is detrimental to me; for you do not reflect that
            you are the cause of its excess. If any being felt emotions of benevolence towards me, I
            should return them an hundred and an hundred fold; for that one creature’s sake, I would
            make peace with the whole kind! But I now indulge in dreams of bliss that cannot be
            realized. What I ask of you is reasonable and moderate; I demand a creature of another
            sex, but as hideous as myself: the gratification is small, but it is all that I can
            receive, and it shall content me. It is true, we shall be monsters, cut off from all the
            world; but on that account we shall be <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_150" n="146"/>more
            attached to one another. Our lives will not be happy, but they will be harmless, and
            free from the misery I now feel. Oh! my creator, make me happy; let me feel gratitude
            towards you for one benefit! Let me see that I excite the sympathy of some existing
            thing; do not deny me my request!”</p>
   <p>I was moved. I shuddered when I thought of the possible consequences of my consent; but
            I felt that there was some justice in his argument. His tale, and the feelings he now
            expressed, proved him to be a creature of fine sensations; and did I not, as his maker,
            owe him all the portion of happiness that it was in my power to bestow? He saw my change
            of feeling, and continued—</p>
   <p>“If you consent, neither you nor any other human being shall ever see us <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_151" n="147"/>again: I will go to the vast wilds of South America.
            My food is not that of man; I do not destroy the lamb and the kid, to glut my appetite;
            acorns and berries afford me sufficient nourishment. My companion will be of the same
            nature as myself, and will be content with the same fare. We shall make our bed of dried
            leaves; the sun will shine on us as on man, and will ripen our food. The picture I
            present to you is peaceful and human, and you must feel that you could deny it only in
            the wantonness of power and cruelty. Pitiless as you have been towards me, I now see
            compassion in your eyes; let me seize the favourable moment, and persuade you to promise
            what I so ardently desire.”</p>
   <p>“You propose,” replied I, “to fly from the habitations of man, to dwell in those wilds
            where the beasts of the <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_152" n="148"/>field will be your only
            companions. How can you, who long for the love and sympathy of man, persevere in this
            exile? You will return, and again seek their kindness, and you will meet with their
            detestation; your evil passions will be renewed, and you will then have a companion to
            aid you in the task of destruction. This may not be; cease to argue the point, for I
            cannot consent.”</p>
   <p>“How inconstant are your feelings! but a moment ago you were moved by my
            representations, and why do you again harden yourself to my complaints? I swear to you,
            by the earth which I inhabit, and by you that made me, that, with the companion you
            bestow, I will quit the neighbourhood of man, and dwell, as it may chance, in the most
            savage of places. My evil passions will have fled, for <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_153" n="149"/>I shall meet with sympathy; my life will flow quietly away, and, in my
            dying moments, I shall not curse my maker.”</p>
   <p>His words had a strange effect upon me. I compassionated him, and sometimes felt a wish
            to console him; but when I looked upon him, when I saw the filthy mass that moved and
            talked, my heart sickened, and my feelings were altered to those of horror and hatred. I
            tried to stifle these sensations; I thought, that as I could not sympathize with him, I
            had no right to withhold from him the small portion of happiness which was yet in my
            power to bestow.</p>
   <p>“You swear,” I said, “to be harmless; but have you not already shewn a degree of malice
            that should reasonably make me distrust you? May not even this be a feint that will
            increase <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_154" n="150"/>your triumph by affording a wider scope
            for your revenge?”</p>
   <p>“How is this? I thought I had moved your compassion, and yet you still refuse to bestow
            on me the only benefit that can soften my heart, and render me harmless. If I have no
            ties and no affections, hatred and vice must be my portion; the love of another will
            destroy the cause of my crimes, and I shall become a thing, of whose existence every one
            will be ignorant. My vices are the children of a forced solitude that I abhor; and my
            virtues will necessarily arise when I live in communion with an equal. I shall feel the
            affections of a sensitive being, and become linked to the chain of existence and events,
            from which I am now excluded.”</p>
   <p>I paused some time to reflect on all he had related, and the various argu<pb xml:id="F1818_v2_155" n="151"/>ments which he had employed. I thought of the
            promise of virtues which he had displayed on the opening of his existence, and the
            subsequent blight of all kindly feeling by the loathing and scorn which his protectors
            had manifested towards him. His power and threats were not omitted in my calculations: a
            creature who could exist in the ice caves of the glaciers, and hide himself from pursuit
            among the ridges of inaccessible precipices, was a being possessing faculties it would
            be vain to cope with. After a long pause of reflection, I concluded, that the justice
            due both to him and my fellow-creatures demanded of me that I should comply with his
            request. Turning to him, therefore, I said—</p>
   <p>“I consent to your demand, on your solemn oath to quit Europe for ever, and every other
            place in the neighbourhood <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_156" n="152"/>of man, as soon as I
            shall deliver into your hands a female who will accompany you in your exile.”</p>
   <p>“I swear,” he cried, “by the sun, and by the blue sky of heaven, that if you grant my
            prayer, while they exist you shall never behold me again. Depart to your home, and
            commence your labours: I shall watch their progress with unutterable anxiety; and fear
            not but that when you are ready I shall appear.”</p>
   <p>Saying this, he suddenly quitted me, fearful, perhaps, of any change in my sentiments.
            I saw him descend the mountain with greater speed than the flight of an eagle, and
            quickly lost him among the undulations of the sea of ice.</p>
   <p>His tale had occupied the whole day; and the sun was upon the verge of the horizon when
            he departed. I knew <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_157" n="153"/>that I ought to hasten my
            descent towards the valley, as I should soon be encompassed in darkness; but my heart
            was heavy, and my steps slow. The labour of winding among the little paths of the
            mountains, and fixing my feet firmly as I advanced, perplexed me, occupied as I was by
            the emotions which the occurrences of the day had produced. Night was far advanced, when
            I came to the half-way resting-place, and seated myself beside the fountain. The stars
            shone at intervals, as the clouds passed from over them; the dark pines rose before me,
            and every here and there a broken tree lay on the ground: it was a scene of wonderful
            solemnity, and stirred strange thoughts within me. I wept bitterly; and, clasping my
            hands in agony, I exclaimed, “Oh! stars, and clouds, and winds, ye are all about to mock 
            <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_158" n="154"/>me: if ye really pity me, crush sensation and
            memory; let me become as nought; but if not, depart, depart and leave me in
            darkness.”</p>
   <p>These were wild and miserable thoughts; but I cannot describe to you how the eternal
            twinkling of the stars weighed upon me, and how I listened to every blast of wind, as if
            it were a dull ugly siroc<add place="margin">co</add> on its way to consume me.</p>
   <p>Morning dawned before I arrived at the village of Chamounix; but my presence, so
            haggard and strange, hardly calmed the fears of my family, who had waited the whole
            night in anxious expectation of my return.</p>
   <p>The following day we returned to Geneva. The intention of my father in coming had been
            to divert my mind, and to restore me to my lost tranquillity; but the medicine had been
            fatal. And, unable to account for the excess of <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_159" n="155"/>misery I appeared to suffer, he hastened to return home, hoping the quiet and monotony
            of a domestic life would by degrees alleviate my sufferings from whatsoever cause they
            might spring.</p>
   <p>For myself, I was passive in all their arrangements; and the gentle affection of my
            beloved Elizabeth was inadequate to draw me from the depth of my despair. The promise I
            had made to the dæmon weighed upon my mind, like Dante’s iron cowl on the heads of the
            hellish hypocrites. All pleasures of earth and sky passed before me like a dream, and
            that thought only had to me the reality of life. Can you wonder, that sometimes a kind
            of insanity possessed me, or that I saw continually about me a multitude of filthy
            animals inflicting on me incessant torture, that often extorted screams and bitter
            groans?</p>
   <p>
      <pb xml:id="F1818_v2_160" n="156"/>By degrees, however, these feelings became
            calmed. I entered again into the every-day scene of life, if not with interest, at least
            with some degree of tranquillity.</p>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="16"/>
   <head>END OF VOL. II</head>
   <milestone unit="volume" n="3"/>
   <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="start" n="3"/>
   <include href="standOff_Includes/1818_frontMatter3.xml" parse="xml"/>
   <milestone unit="frontmatter" type="end" n="3"/>
</xml>
