<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
   <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C28"/>
   <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="21"/>
   <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_095" n="091"/>
   <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
   <p>W<hi rend="smallcaps">E</hi> had resolved not to go to London, but to cross the
            country to Portsmouth, and thence to embark for Havre. I preferred this plan principally
            because I dreaded to see again those places in which I had enjoyed a few moments of
            tranquillity with my beloved Clerval. I thought with horror of seeing again those
            persons whom we had been accustomed to visit together, and who might make inquiries
            concerning an event, the very remembrance of which made me again feel the pang I endured
              <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_096" n="092"/> when I gazed on his lifeless form in the inn
            at——.</p>
   <p>As for my father, his desires and exertions were bounded to the again seeing me
            restored to health and peace of mind. His tenderness and attentions were unremitting; my
            grief and gloom was obstinate, but he would not despair. Sometimes he thought that I
            felt deeply the degradation of being obliged to answer a charge of murder, and he
            endeavoured to <del rend="strikethrough"><hi rend="underline">prove to me the futility of pride.</hi></del><add>inspire me with more philosophic sentiments. But his arguments drawn from general observation failed in reaching the core of my incurable disease.</add></p>
   <p>“Alas! my father,” said I, “how little do you know me. Human beings, their feelings and
            passions, would indeed be degraded, if such a wretch as I felt pride. Justine, poor
            unhappy Justine, was as innocent as I, and she suffered the same charge; she died for
            it; and I am the cause of this—I murdered her. William, Justine, <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_097" n="093"/> and Henry—they all died by my hands.”</p>
   <p>My father had often, during my imprisonment, heard me make the same assertion; when I
            thus accused myself, he sometimes seemed to desire an explanation, and at others he
            appeared to consider it as caused by delirium, and that, during my illness, some idea of
            this kind had presented itself to my imagination, the remembrance of which I preserved
            in my convalescence. I avoided explanation, and maintained a continual silence
            concerning the wretch I had created. <hi rend="underline">I had a feeling that I should be supposed mad</hi>, and
            this for ever chained my tongue, when I would have given the whole world to have
            confided the fatal secret.</p>
   <p>
            <comment elem="note"
               type="editor"
               resp="rm"
               text="This block at this point in the PAEE is NOT in the 1818 PDF. rm: Yet still words like those I have recorded would burst uncontrollably from me. I could               offer no explanation of them; but their truth in part relieved the burden of my               mysterious woe."/>
          </p>
   <p>Upon this occasion my father said, with an expression of unbounded wonder, “What do you
            mean, Victor? <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_098" n="094"/>are you mad? My dear son, I entreat
            you never to make such an assertion again.”</p>
   <p>“I am not mad,” I cried energetically; “the sun and the heavens, who have viewed my
            operations, can bear witness of my truth. I am the assassin of those most innocent
            victims; they died by my machinations. A thousand times would I have shed my own blood,
            drop by drop, to have saved their lives; but I could not, my father, indeed I could not
            sacrifice the whole human race.” <add place="bottom_and_following_pages">What could induce me to talk thus incoherently of the dread<del>ful subject</del> that I dared not explain?—In truth, it was insanity, not of the understanding but of the heart, which <del rend="strikethrough">produced a state of reckless</del>caused me always to think of one thing, of one<pb n="95"/> sentiment, and <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> thus there would at times escape to my lips, as a half stifled <del>groan</del>sigh may; though else unseen &amp; unheard, just move<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> the flame that surrounds the marty at the stake. But though he sigh, he will not recant, &amp; though I, more weak, gave vent to my pent up thoughts in words such as these, yet I shrunk unalterably from any thing that should reveal the existence of my enemy.</add></p>
   <p>The conclusion of this speech convinced my father that my ideas were deranged, and he
            instantly changed the subject of our conversation, and endeavoured to alter the course
            of my thoughts. He wished as much as possible to obliterate the memory of the scenes
            that had taken place in Ireland, <pb xml:id="F1818_v3_099" n="095"/>and never alluded
            to them, or suffered me to speak of my misfortunes.</p>
   <p>As time passed away I became more calm: misery had her dwelling in my heart, but I no
            longer talked in the same incoherent manner of my own crimes; sufficient for me was the
            consciousness of them. By the utmost self-violence, I curbed the imperious voice of
            wretchedness, which sometimes desired to declare itself to the whole world; and my
            manners were calmer and more composed than they had ever been since <hi rend="underline">my journey to <add place="margin">Montavert and</add> the
            sea of ice.</hi></p>
   <p>We arrived at Havre on the 8th of May, and instantly proceeded to Paris, where my
            father had some business which detained us a few weeks. In this city, I received the
            following letter from Elizabeth:—</p>
</xml>
